<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
    <eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" findaidstatus="Completed" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-DSI-AAA" url="http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/findingaids/xml/alexjohn.xml">alexjohn.xml</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Finding Aid to the John White Alexander Papers, 1775-1968, bulk 1870-1915, in the Archives of American Art
                    <num>AAA.alexjohn</num>
                </titleproper>
                <titleproper type="filing">Alexander (John White)</titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by Megan McShea</author>
                <sponsor>Funding for the processing and digitization of this collection was provided by the Terra Foundation for American Art</sponsor>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Archives of American Art</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>750 9th Street, NW</addressline>
                    <addressline>Victor Building, Suite 2200</addressline>
                    <addressline>Washington, D.C., 20001</addressline>
                    <addressline>Phone: 202-633-7950</addressline>
                    <addressline>http://www.aaa.si.edu/askus</addressline>
                </address>
                <date>September 06, 2007</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <notestmt>
                <note>
                    <p>This finding aid is associated with MARC collection-level record. 
                        <num type="siris_bib">210817</num></p>
                </note>
            </notestmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2015-01-28T14:29-0500</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>
                <language>English</language></langusage>
            <descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
        </profiledesc>
        <revisiondesc>
            <change>
                <date>January 26, 2015</date>
                <item>Anna Rimel glass plate re-housing with CCPF grant</item>
            </change>
        </revisiondesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>John White Alexander papers</unittitle>
            <unitid>AAA.alexjohn</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>Archives of American Art</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>11.2 Linear feet</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1870/1915" type="bulk">bulk 1870-1915</unitdate>
            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">1775-1968</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref1" label="Abstract">The papers of the painter, muralist, and illustrator John White Alexander measure 11.2 linear feet and date from 1775 to 1968, with the bulk of materials dating from 1870 to 1915. Papers document Alexander's artistic career and many connections to figures in the art world through biographical documentation, correspondence (some illustrated), writings, 13 sketchbooks, additonal artwork and loose sketches, scrapbooks, photographs, awards and medals, artifacts, and other records. Also found is a souvenir engraving of a Mark Twain self-portrait.</abstract>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Alexander, John White</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <acqinfo id="ref2">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Papers were donated to the Archives of American Art by Irina Reed, granddaughter of John White Alexander, in 1978 and 1981.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <altformavail id="ref3">
            <head>Existence and Location of Copies note</head>
            <p>The papers of 
                <emph render="bold">John White Alexander</emph> in the Archives of American Art were digitized in 
                <date type="scan_date">2009-2010</date>, and total 
                <num type="scan_count">5592</num> images.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <processinfo id="ref4">
            <head>Processing Information note</head>
            <p>The papers were arranged and microfilmed upon receipt on reels 1727-1731, 1807, and 3483. The accessions were merged, re-processed, and fully described in this finding aid in 2007 by Megan McShea with funding from the Terra Foundation for American Art. Glass plate negatives were re-housed in 2015 with a grant from the Smithsonian Collections Care and Preservation Fund.</p>
        </processinfo>
        <prefercite id="ref5">
            <head>Preferred Citation note</head>
            <p>John White Alexander papers, 1775-1968, bulk 1870-1915. Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <accessrestrict id="ref6">
            <head>Conditions Governing Access note</head>
            <p>Use of the original papers requires an appointment. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict id="ref7">
            <head>Conditions Governing Use note</head>
            <p>The John White Alexander papers are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
        </userestrict>
        <bioghist id="ref8">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>John White Alexander was born in 1856 in Allegheny City, Pennsylvania. He was orphaned at age five and taken in by relatives of limited means. When Alexander left school and began working at a telegraph company, the company's vice-president, former civil war Colonel Edward Jay Allen, took an interest in his welfare. Allen became his legal guardian, brought him into the Allen household, and saw that he finished Pittsburgh High School. At eighteen, he moved to New York City and was hired by Harper and Brothers as an office boy in the art department. He was soon promoted to apprentice illustrator under staff artists such as Edwin A. Abbey and Charles Reinhart. During his time at Harpers, Alexander was sent out on assignment to illustrate events such as the Philadelphia Centennial celebration in 1876 and the Pittsburgh Railroad Strike in 1877, which erupted in violence.</p>
            <p>Alexander carefully saved money from his illustration work and traveled to Europe in 1877 for further art training. He first enrolled in the Royal Art Academy of Munich, Germany, but soon moved to the village of Polling, where a colony of American artists was at its peak in the late 1870s. Alexander established a painting studio there and stayed for about a year. Despite his absence from the Munich Academy, he won the medal of the drawing class for 1878, the first of many honors. While in Polling, he became acquainted with J. Frank Currier, Frank Duveneck, William Merritt Chase, and other regular visitors to the colony. He later shared a studio and taught a painting class in Florence with Duveneck and traveled to Venice, where he met James Abbott McNeill Whistler.</p>
            <p>Alexander returned to New York in 1881 and resumed his commercial artwork for Harpers and Century. Harpers sent him down the Mississippi river to complete a series of sketches. He also began to receive commissions for portraits, and in the 1880s painted Charles Dewitt Bridgman, a daughter of one of the Harper brothers, Parke Godwin, Thurlow Weed, Walt Whitman, and Oliver Wendell Holmes. Alexander met his wife Elizabeth, whose maiden name was also Alexander, through her father, James W. Alexander, who was sometimes mistaken for the artist. Elizabeth and John White Alexander married in 1887 and had a son, James, in 1888.</p>
            <p>Alexander and his family sailed for France in 1890, where they became a part of the lively literary and artistic scene in Paris at the time. Among their many contacts there were Puvis de Chavannes, Auguste Rodin, and Whistler, who arrived in Paris shortly thereafter. Alexander absorbed the new aesthetic ideas around him such as those of the symbolists and the decorative style of art nouveau. Critics often note how such ideas are reflected in his boldly composed paintings of women from this period, who titles drew attention to the sensual and natural elements of the paintings. His first exhibition in Paris was three paintings at the Société Nationale des Beaux Arts in 1893, and by 1895 he has become a full member of the Société.</p>
            <p>Independent and secession artist societies emerged throughout Europe during this period, and Alexander exhibited with several of them, including the Société Neuvelle in Paris, the Munich Secession, and the Vienna Secession. He was also elected an honorary member of the Royal Society of Belgian Artists and the Royal Society of British Painters in London. His exhibited works sold well, and his influence began to be felt back in the United States. Andrew Carnegie and John Beatty of the Carnegie Institute consulted closely with Alexander in the planning and execution of the first Carnegie International Exhibitions. Alexander also became active in supporting younger American artists who wanted to exhibit in Europe, a stance which resulted in his resignation from the Society of American Artists in Paris, which he felt had become a barrier to younger artists. His promotion of American art became an central aspect of his career for the remainder of his life, most visibly through his presidency of the National Academy of Design from 1909 until shortly before his death in 1915. He also served frequently on juries for high-profile exhibitions, and was a trustee at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the New York Public Library, and the national Institute of Arts and Letters. Around 1912, he helped to form the School Art League in New York, which provided art instruction to high school students.</p>
            <p>Alexander returned to the United States nearly every summer while based in Paris, and among his commissioned paintings were murals for the newly-constructed Library of Congress, completed around 1896. In 1901, the Alexanders returned to New York permanently. The demand for portraits continued, and he had his first solo exhibition at the Durand-Ruel Galleries in 1902. Around 1905 he received a commission for murals at the new Carnegie Institute building in Pittsburgh for the astounding sum of $175,000. He created 48 panels there through 1908. During this period, the Alexanders spent summers in Onteora, New York, where Alexander painted his well-known "Sunlight" paintings. There they became friends and collaborators with the actress Maude Adams, with Alexander designing lighting and stage sets, and Elizabeth Alexander designing costumes for Adams' productions such as 
                <emph render="italic">Peter Pan</emph>, the 
                <emph render="italic">Maid of Orleans</emph>, and 
                <emph render="italic">Chanticleer</emph>. The couple became known for their "theatricals" or tableaux, staged at the MacDowell Club and elsewhere, and Elizabeth Alexander continued her design career when her husband died in 1915.</p>
            <p>Alexander left several commissions unfinished upon his death at age 59, including murals in Wisconsin, Ohio, and Harrisburg, Pennsylvania. Elizabeth Alexander held a memorial exhibition at Arden Galleries a few months after his death, and a larger memorial exhibition was held by the Carnegie Institute in 1916. Alexander won dozens of awards for artwork in his lifetime, including the Lippincott Prize at the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts in 1899, the Gold Medal of Honor at the Paris Exposition Universelle in 1900, the Gold Medal at the Panama Pacific Exposition of 1901, and the Medal of the First Class at the Carnegie Institute International Exhibition in 1911. In 1923, the Alexander Memorial Studio was built at the MacDowell colony in New Hampshire to honor his memory.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref9">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>The papers of the painter, muralist, and illustrator John White Alexander measure 11.2 linear feet and date from 1775 to 1968, with the bulk of materials dating from 1870 to 1915. Papers document Alexander's artistic career and many connections to figures in the art world through biographical documentation, correspondence (some illustrated), writings, 13 sketchbooks, additonal artwork and loose sketches, scrapbooks, photographs, awards and medals, artifacts, and other records. Also found is a souvenir engraving of a Mark Twain self-portrait.</p>
            <p>Biographical Information includes multiple essays related to Alexander, his family, and others in his circle. Also found is an extensive oral history of Alexander's wife Elizabeth conducted in 1928. Correspondence includes letters written by Alexander to his family from New York and Europe at the start of his career, and later letters from fellow artists, art world leaders, and portrait sitters of Alexander's. Significant correspondents include Charles Dana Gibson, Florence Levy, Frederick Remington, Robert Louis Stevenson, Henry James, John La Farge, Francis Davis Millet, and Andrew Carnegie. Correspondence includes some small sketches as enclosures and illustrated letters.</p>
            <p>Certificates and records related to Alexander's career are found in Associations and Memberships, Legal and Financial Records, and Notes and Writings, which contain documentation of Alexander's paintings and exhibitions. Scattered documentation of Alexander's memberships in various arts association exists for the American Academy of Arts and Letters, the American Academy in Rome, the National Academy of Design, the Onteora Club in New York, the Royal Academy of Fine Arts in Munich, Germany, the Ministère de L'Instruction Publique et des Beaux-Arts, the Union Internationale des Beaux Arts et des Lettres, and the Metropolitan Museum of Art. Notes and Writings include speeches written by Alexander, short stories and essays written by his wife, and articles by various authors about Alexander. Extensive documentation of the planning and construction of the Alexander Memorial Studio by the MacDowell Club is found, along with other awards, medals, and memorial resolutions adopted by arts organizations after Alexander's death.</p>
            <p>Artwork includes thirteen sketchbooks with sketches related to Alexander's commercial illustration and cartooning, murals, paintings, and travels. Dozens of loose drawings and sketches are also found, along with two volumes and several dozen loose reproductions of artwork, among which are found fine prints by named printmakers. Many sketches are also interspersed throughout the correspondence. Eight Scrapbooks contain mostly clippings, but also scattered letters, exhbition catalogs, announcements, invitations, and photographs related to Alexander's career between 1877 and 1915. Additional Exhibition Catalogs and later clippings, as well as clippings related to the career of his wife and other subjects, are found in Printed Materials.</p>
            <p>Photographs include many portraits of Alexander taken by accomplished photographers such as Zaida Ben-Yusuf, Aimé Dupont, Curtis Bell, Elizabeth Buehrmann, and several signed Miss Huggins, who may have been Estelle Huntington Huggins, a New York painter and photographer. Portraits of others include Alexander's friends William Merritt Chase and Edward Austin Abbey. Also found are photographs of groups, juries, family, friends, and studios in New York, Paris, and New Jersey, and a handful of scenic photographs of Polling, Bavaria, where Alexander had an early studio. A large number of photographs of works of art are found, many with annotations. Among the photographs of murals are a small collection of snapshots of the Carnegie Institute murals in progress. Miscellaneous artifacts include a palette, several printing plates, and an inscribed souvenir engraving of a self-portrait caricature of Mark Twain.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement id="ref10">
            <head>Arrangement note</head>
            <p>The collection is arranged into 11 series. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.</p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>Series 1: Biographical Information, circa 1887-1968 (Box 1, OV 23; 0.1 linear feet)</item>
                <item>Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1870-1942 (Box 1; 0.7 linear feet)</item>
                <item>Series 3: Associations and Memberships, circa 1897-1918 (Box 1; 2 folders)</item>
                <item>Series 4: Legal and Financial Records, 1775, 1896-1923 (Box 1; 5 folders)</item>
                <item>Series 5: Notes and Writings, circa 1875-1943 (Boxes 1-2; 0.3 linear feet)</item>
                <item>Series 6: Awards and Memorials, circa 1870-1944 (Box 2, OV 24; 0.8 linear feet)</item>
                <item>Series 7: Artwork, circa 1875-1915 (Boxes 2-3, 14-16, OV 23; 1.5 linear feet)</item>
                <item>Series 8: Scrapbooks, circa 1877-1915 (Boxes 17-22; 1.8 linear feet)</item>
                <item>Series 9: Printed Materials, circa 1891-1945 (Boxes 3-4, OV 23; 1.5 linear feet)</item>
                <item>Series 10: Photographs, circa 1870-1915 (Boxes 4-8, MGP 1-2, OV 25-43, RD 44-45; 4.2 linear feet)</item>
                <item>Series 11: Artifacts, circa 1899-1915 (Box 6, artifact cabinet; 0.4 linear feet)</item>
            </list>
        </arrangement>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname source="naf">Abbey, Edwin Austin, 1852-1911</persname>
            <persname source="naf">Alexander, Elizabeth A., d. 1947</persname>
            <persname source="naf">Alexander, John White, 1856-1915</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Chase, William Merritt, 1849-1916</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Gibson, Charles Dana, 1867-1944</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">James, Henry, 1843-1916</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">La Farge, John, 1835-1910</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Levy, Florence N. (Florence Nightingale), 1870-1947</persname>
            <corpname source="ingest">MacDowell Club of New York</corpname>
            <persname source="ingest">Millet, Francis Davis, 1846-1912</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Remington, Frederic, 1861-1909</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Stevenson, Robert Louis, 1850-1894</persname>
            <persname source="naf">Whistler, James McNeill, 1834-1903</persname>
            <genreform source="aat">Awards</genreform>
            <subject source="aat">Illustrators--New York (State)--New York</subject>
            <genreform source="aat">Interviews</genreform>
            <genreform source="aat">Medals</genreform>
            <subject source="aat">Muralists--New York (State)--New York</subject>
            <genreform source="lcsh">Photographs</genreform>
            <subject source="aat">Portrait painters--New York (State)--New York</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Portrait painting, American</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Portrait painting--19th century</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Portrait painting--20th century</subject>
            <genreform source="aat">Scrapbooks</genreform>
            <genreform source="aat">Sketchbooks</genreform>
            <genreform source="aat">Works of art</genreform>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc>
            <c01 id="ref13" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Biographical Information</unittitle>
                    <unitid>Series 1</unitid>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>0.1 Linear feet</extent>
                        <extent>Box 1, OV 23</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1882/1968" type="inclusive">circa 1887-1968</unitdate>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref22">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>This series contains notes, writings, and printed materials that describe the life of John White Alexander, as well as ephemera and personal documents related to specific life events.</p>
                    <p>Notes and narratives include biographical essays about Alexander and his guardian, Colonel Edward Jay Allen, taken from published reference works, and notes made by Elizabeth Alexander in preparation of those entries. Personal documents and ephemera include a wedding invitation, an identity card issued for the Paris International Exposition of 1900, a calling card, a circular about an artist named Jacques Alexander, examples of Alexander's signature, and a French visa. Also found are drafts of essays by Elizabeth Alexander about her husband and others in their circle, and an oral history interview of Elizabeth Alexander in three parts taken by DeWitt M. Lockman, a later president of the National Academy of Design.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <arrangement id="ref23">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>This series has been scanned in its entirety.</p>
                </arrangement>
                <c02 id="ref14" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Biographical Notes and Essays</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146209" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146209" type="Folder">1</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1908/1968" type="inclusive">circa 1913-1968</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref15" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Personal Documents and Ephemera</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146208" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146208" type="Folder">2</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1882/1900" type="inclusive">circa 1887-1900</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref16">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Oversized items housed in OV 23)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref17" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Essays by Elizabeth Alexander about John White Alexander</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146207" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146207" type="Folder">3-5</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(3 folders) </extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce">after 1915</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref18" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Essays by Elizabeth Alexander about Others in their Circle</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146206" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146206" type="Folder">6</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref19" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oral History Interview of Elizabeth Alexander by DeWitt M. Lockman</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146205" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146205" type="Folder">7-9</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(3 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1928/1928">1928</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref20" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Personal Documents and Ephemera</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146204" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">23
                            (OV)</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1882/1900" type="inclusive">circa 1887-1900</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref21">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Items scanned with Box 1, f2</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref24" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                    <unitid>Series 2</unitid>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>0.7 Linear feet</extent>
                        <extent>Box 1</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1865/1942" type="inclusive">circa 1870-1942</unitdate>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref86">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>This series contains personal and business correspondence of John White Alexander and his wife, Elizabeth Alexander. Correspondence from the 1870s and 1880s consists primarily of Alexander's letters home to his guardian, Colonel Edward Jay Allen, the Allen family, and his friend, E.E. Phelps, all in Pittsburgh, written from New York and Europe. 1876 letters detail his visit to the Centennial Exposition in Philadelphia. Many of these letters are found with typed transcriptions which contain scattered annotations which appear to be in Elizabeth Alexander's handwriting. In a couple of cases, transcripts exist for letters which are no longer found in the collection.</p>
                    <p>The remainder of correspondence consists of letters to Alexander from fellow artists, patrons, museums, arts organizations, and friends. Significant correspondents include Charles Dana Gibson, Florence Levy, Frederick Remington, Robert Louis Stevenson, Henry James, John La Farge, Francis Davis Millet, and Andrew Carnegie. These and other significant correspondents are noted in the folder listing. Letters dated after Alexander's death in 1915 are addressed to Elizabeth Alexander, with a single letter addressed to the Alexanders' son James.</p>
                    <p>A number of sketches by Alexander are found in his letters from Europe dated from 1877 to 1880. There are also scattered illustrated letters and an Illustrated letter from Ivan P. Pranishnikoff is found from 1898. Additional types of records found include scattered receipts and clippings.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <arrangement id="ref87">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>Correspondence is arranged chronologically, with undated correspondence filed at the beginning of the series. Additional correspondence is found in Scrapbooks. See Scrapbook series description and folder listing for more details. This series has been scanned in its entirety.</p>
                </arrangement>
                <c02 id="ref25" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Undated Correspondence, Adams to Garland</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146203" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146203" type="Folder">10</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref26">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include John White Alexander, W.K. Austin, Charles Curran, M.K. Gage, Charles Dana Gibson, and H. Garland)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref27" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Undated Correspondence, Johnston to Whistler</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146202" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146202" type="Folder">11</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref28">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include Ella Bond Johnston, O. Latrobe, Florence Levy, E.L. Ryerson, Ebin R. Smith, Robert Louis Stevenson, Harry Watrous, and James McNeill Whistler)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref29" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146201" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146201" type="Folder">12</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1870/1874" type="inclusive">1870-1874</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref30" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146200" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146200" type="Folder">13-20</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(8 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1875/1875">1875</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref31">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(ink drawing found)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref32" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146199" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146199" type="Folder">21-25</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(5 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1876/1876">1876</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref33" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146198" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146198" type="Folder">26-29</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(4 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1877/1877">1877</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref34">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(sketches found)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref35" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146197" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146197" type="Folder">30-34</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(5 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1878/1878">1878</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref36">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(sketches found)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref37" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146196" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146196" type="Folder">35</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1879/1879">1879</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref38">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(sketches found)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref39" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146195" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146195" type="Folder">36</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1880/1882" type="inclusive">1880-1882</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref40">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(sketches found)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref41" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146194" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146194" type="Folder">37</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1883/1886" type="inclusive">1883-1886</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref42" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146193" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146193" type="Folder">38-42</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(5 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1887/1887">1887</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref43">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include Harry Alexander, John Burroughs, and Henry James)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref44" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146192" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146192" type="Folder">43</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1888/1889" type="inclusive">1888-1889</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref45" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146191" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146191" type="Folder">44</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1891/1892" type="inclusive">1891-1892</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref46">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include Ministry of Art Education in France and Elizabeth Alexander)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref47" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146190" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146190" type="Folder">45</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1893/1895" type="inclusive">1893-1895</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref48" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146189" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146189" type="Folder">46</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1896/1897" type="inclusive">1896-1897</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref49">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include M.R. Blair, J.J. Cowan, Lydia E. Grosvenor Davis, Mayor F. Grimani of Venice, William Turner Dannat, and Puvis de Chavannes)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref50" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146188" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146188" type="Folder">47</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1898/1900" type="inclusive">1898-1900</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref51">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include Frantz Jourdain, Fr. Linley Sanbourne, and Cowan family members)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref52" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146187" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146187" type="Folder">48</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1901/1903" type="inclusive">1901-1903</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref53">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include Samuel Huey, Andrew Carnegie, John La Farge, the Pan American Exposition of 1901, Princeton University, Mabel Carleton Gage, Homer Gage, Hester Knowles, and Harper Brothers to Elizabeth Alexander)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref54" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146186" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146186" type="Folder">49</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1904/1904">1904</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref55">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Includes many letters from John White Alexander written in Boston; also letters from Anne Bradley)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref56" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146185" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146185" type="Folder">50</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1905/1905">1905</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref57">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include Anne Bradley, R.D. Alexander, Carnegie Library, H.N. Matzen, F.D. Millet, and D. Webster King)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref58" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146184" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146184" type="Folder">51</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1906/1908" type="inclusive">1906-1908</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref59">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include Stanford White, Charles Dana Gibson, Joseph Pennell, Alfred East, and John La Farge)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref60" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146183" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146183" type="Folder">52-53</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(2 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1909/1909">1909</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref61">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Includes many letters of congratulations written to Alexander on his election as president of the National Academy of Design. Also contains a note indicating that several letters in this folder were removed from Alexander's scrapbook of 1909. See Scrapbooks for more information. Correspondents include Albert Sternan, John W. Beatty, Charles Dana Gibson, Florence (probably Levy), Elbert Baldwin, Edward Robsinon, Samuel Swift, Edwin Howland Blashfield, Anna M. Clarke, William Laurel Harris, Harrison S. Morris, Thomas Hastings, Frank D. Millet, C. Russell, Jeannette Gilder, Robert Underwood Johnson, John La Farge, Fred Crowninshield, Leon Dabo, Henri Martin, and Edward Bok.)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref62" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146182" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146182" type="Folder">54</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1910/1911" type="inclusive">1910-1911</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref63">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include Andrew Carnegie, Houston Lowe, Birge Harrison, William Hyde, M.A. Dixon, Yale University regarding an honorary degree, Alfred East, John F. Weir, and DeWitt Parshall)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref64" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, 1912</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146181" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146181" type="Folder">55</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref65">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include Edward Redfield, W.D. Howells, Potter Palmer, Geo. Dudley Seymour, Mary Hearn Greims, Josephine L. Goodyear, Geo. Peabody Wetmore, and Leslie J. Skelton.)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref66" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146180" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146180" type="Folder">56</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1913/1913">1913</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref67">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include George Hearn, Hugo Reisinger, C. Grant La Farge, Leslie Skelton, Trinity Church, Fred Crowninshield, Geo. Dudley Seymour, the Panama-Pacific Exposition, Timothy Cole, and Edward Redfield)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref68" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146179" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146179" type="Folder">57</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1914/1914">1914</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref69">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include Francis Newton, George Hopkins, Cass Gilbert, H.C. Mansfield, Robert Underwood Johnson, and Woodrow Wilson)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref70" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146178" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146178" type="Folder">58-62</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(5 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1915/1915">1915</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref71">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Letters to Alexander are found from Campbell Cooper, Carl Becker, Henry B. Snell, and Douglas Volk. Letters of condolence to the Alexanders are found from Charles Dana Gibson, E.J. Allen, E.A.S. Clarke, Maude (probably Adams), Ernest Peix (probably Peixotto), Geo. Wharton Edwards, Edward Woods, Robert Abbe, Robert Underwood Johnson, Franklin Babbitt, Edwin H. Blashfield, Harrison Morris, J. Alden Weir, Janet Van Buskirk, Edwin Baldwin, J. Henry Harper, William Laurel Harris, Adolph Lewisohn, Earl Stetson Crawford, Ernest T. Rosen, C.H. Russell, Frances M. Ward, S.H. Church, Robert De Forest, John H. Finley, John F. Weir, Ben Foster, William Bailey Faxon, William Walton, Charles H. Caffin, Bruce Crane, Herbert Adams, Ed Phelps, Elizabeth W. Roberts, Augusta H.S. Gaudens, Frederic Allen Whiting, Florence Levy, John Beatty, Harry Watrous, and C. Powell Minnigerode.)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref72" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146177" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146177" type="Folder">63</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1916/1916">1916</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref73">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include Howard Mansfield, Jane Potter Russell, J. Howland Hunt, Robert Underwood Johnson, John Beatty, John H. Finley, May Allen, Cooper Union, National Arts Club, M. MacDowell, N. H. Carpenter, and S.H. Church)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref74" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146176" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146176" type="Folder">64</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1917/1923" type="inclusive">1917-1923</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref75">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include Carroll Beckwith, whose letter includes a photographer of her portrait by Alexander, Francis Wilson, Leila Mechlin, Edward Bok, Jean MacLane, Julian Clarence Levi, and W.H. Holmes)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref76" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146175" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146175" type="Folder">65</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1924/1929" type="inclusive">1924-1929</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref77">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include R.M. MacIntyre, Alex Simpson, Edwin Blashfield, DuBon and Dorothy, L.M. Lockhart, E.C. Babcock, Homer Saint Gaudens, Grace Vanamee, Walter Crittenden, and William Henry Fox.)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref78" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146174" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146174" type="Folder">66</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1930/1936" type="inclusive">1930-1936</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref79">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include William Barclay Parsons, Gertrude Herdle Moore, Norbert Heerman, Horace Moran, and Edwin Blashfield)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref80" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146173" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146173" type="Folder">67</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1937/1939" type="inclusive">1937-1939</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref81">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include William Weldon, Norbert Heerman, Harrison Morris, Agnes Holden, and the Museum of the City of New York.)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref82" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146172" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146172" type="Folder">68</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1935/1942" type="inclusive">circa 1940-1942</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref83">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Correspondents include Homer Saint Gaudens, Carnegie Magazine, John O'Connor, C. Bernard Shea, and Hobart Nichols.)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref84" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, Envelopes</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146171" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146171" type="Folder">69</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1874/1904" type="inclusive">1874-1904</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref85" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Typescript Copies of Selected Correspondence (1912-1916)</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146170" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146170" type="Folder">70</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref88" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Associations and Memberships</unittitle>
                    <unitid>Series 3</unitid>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>2 Folders</extent>
                        <extent>Box 1</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1892/1918" type="inclusive">circa 1897-1918</unitdate>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref90">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>This series contains membership certificates, cards, circulars, rosters, and other records associated with European and American art organizations in which Alexander participated, or which solicited his participation. Organizations represented in this series include the American Academy of Arts and Letters, the American Academy in Rome, the National Academy of Design, the Onteora Club (New York), the Royal Academy of Fine Arts (Munich, Germany), the Ministère de L'Instruction Publique et des Beaux-Arts, the Union Internationale des Beaux Arts et des Lettres, and the Metropolitan Museum of Art.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <arrangement id="ref91">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>Items in this series are arranged chronologically. This series has been scanned in its entirety.</p>
                </arrangement>
                <c02 id="ref89" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Associations and Memberships</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146169" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146169" type="Folder">71-72</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(2 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1892/1918" type="inclusive">circa 1897-1918</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref92" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Legal and Financial Records</unittitle>
                    <unitid>Series 4</unitid>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>5 Folders</extent>
                        <extent>Box 1</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1775">1775</unitdate>
                    <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1896/1923" type="inclusive">1896-1923</unitdate>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref98">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>This series includes an 18th century road report, copyright forms, a contract, royalty statements, and receipts. Among receipts are insurance payments, membership dues, and financial transactions. Scattered receipts are also found among Correspondence.</p>
                    <p>Additional records documenting Alexander's artwork are found in Notes and Writings.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <arrangement id="ref99">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>This series has been scanned in its entirety.</p>
                </arrangement>
                <c02 id="ref93" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Virginia Road Report Signed by a John Alexander</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146168" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146168" type="Folder">73</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1775">1775</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref94" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Copyright Forms for Library of Congress Murals</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146167" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146167" type="Folder">74</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1896/1896">1896</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref95" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Contract for Carnegie Institute Murals</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146166" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146166" type="Folder">75</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1905/1905">1905</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref96" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Royalties of the Detroit Publishing Company</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146165" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146165" type="Folder">76</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1923/1923">1923</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref97" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Miscellaneous Receipts</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146164" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146164" type="Folder">77</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1901/1917" type="inclusive">circa 1906-1917</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref100" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Notes and Writings</unittitle>
                    <unitid>Series 5</unitid>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>0.3 Linear feet</extent>
                        <extent>Boxes 1-2</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1870/1943" type="inclusive">circa 1875-1943</unitdate>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref111">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>This series contains notes, essays, speeches, short stories, news articles, poems, and records of artwork written by John White Alexander, his wife Elizabeth Alexander, and others.</p>
                    <p>Notes appear to be fragments of essays or speeches, typed and handwritten. A few rough sketches are found among the notes. Speeches by John White Alexander are mainly on art subjects. These include a 1901 talk for New York City's founder's Day entitled "Our Tariff on Art," and a 1912 address to the Onteora Club on the formation of the School Art League.</p>
                    <p>Short stories by Elizabeth Alexander are found in typescript and handwritten form. Tear sheets for several of her published stories illustrated by John White Alexander are also found. Original drawings of some of these illustrations are found in Artwork.</p>
                    <p>Articles about Alexander include typescripts of two critical essays by his contemporaries Sadakichi Hartmann and Anne Webb Kamaghan, a catalog description by Julia deWolf Addision, and a collection of transcribed news stories and editorials about his resignation from the Society of American Painters in Paris.</p>
                    <p>Records of artwork include two bound volumes with information about paintings and many lists of paintings related to exhibitions and storage. The second folder of lists appears to be related to a memorial exhibitions held for Alexander in 1916, and the fourth contains a small notebook with the heading "List of Portraits and Paintings by Alexander painted before 1887."</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <arrangement id="ref112">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>This series has been scanned in its entirety.</p>
                </arrangement>
                <c02 id="ref101" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Notes</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146163" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146163" type="Folder">78-79</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(2 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref102" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Speeches by John White Alexander</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146162" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146162" type="Folder">80-84</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(5 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1896/1912" type="inclusive">circa 1901-1912</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref103" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Short Stories by Elizabeth Alexander</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146161" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146161" type="Folder">1-3</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(3 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref104" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Short Stories by Elizabeth Alexander, Tear Sheets of Published Stories with Illustrations by John White Alexander</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146160" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146160" type="Folder">4</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1896/1897" type="inclusive">1896-1897</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref105" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Essays and Speeches by Elizabeth Alexander</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146159" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146159" type="Folder">5</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref106" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Articles about John White Alexander</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146158" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146158" type="Folder">6-7</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(2 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1900/1901" type="inclusive">1900-1901</unitdate>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref107" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Poems Removed from Sketchbook</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146157" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146157" type="Folder">8</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1870/1875" type="inclusive">circa 1875</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref108" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Poems Written for and to John White Alexander</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146156" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146156" type="Folder">9</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1892/1912" type="inclusive">circa 1897-1912</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref109" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Registers of Paintings and Exhibitions</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146155" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146155" type="Folder">10-11</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(2 volumes in 2 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1882/1913" type="inclusive">circa 1887-1913</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref110" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Lists of Paintings</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146154" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146154" type="Folder">12-15</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(4 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1888/1943" type="inclusive">circa 1893-1943</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref113" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Awards and Memorials</unittitle>
                    <unitid>Series 6</unitid>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>0.8 Linear feet</extent>
                        <extent>Box 2, OV 24</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1865/1944" type="inclusive">circa 1870-1944</unitdate>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref132">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>This series contains award certificates and medals awarded to Alexander during his lifetime, and memorial resolutions and projects carried out after his death in 1915.</p>
                    <p>Award certificates and medals are found from the Royal Academy of Art in Munich, the Carnegie Institute, and the Panama Pacific Exposition. Additional medals awarded for Alexander's artwork are found from the Societé National des Beaux-Arts, the Paris Exposition of 1900, the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, the Pan American Exposition, the Saint Louis Exposition, the Buenos Aires Exposition, and the School Arts League. Additional medals from civic organizations are also found.</p>
                    <p>Extensive materials are found documenting the creation of the Alexander Memorial Studio at the McDowell Colony in New Hampshire, including published reports of the McDowell Club and Colony, images in the form of photo postcards and engravings, and a studio book containing photographs of the studio's construction, a history of the studio, and the signatures of resident artists. Notes and correspondence concerning the history of the studio are found tucked in the book.</p>
                    <p>Over a dozen memorial resolutions issued upon Alexander's death by arts organizations to which he contributed during his lifetime are found. Several of these resolutions exist in ornate, calligraphic, bound volumes.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <arrangement id="ref133">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>Additional photographs of the Alexander Memorial Studio are found in Photographs. This series has been scanned in its entirety.</p>
                </arrangement>
                <c02 id="ref114" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Award Certificates</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146153" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146153" type="Folder">16</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1873/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1878-1915</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref115">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Oversized items housed in OV 24</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref116" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Medals</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146152" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146152" type="Folder">17-19</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(20 items in 3 shoe boxes) </extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1865/1922" type="inclusive">circa 1870-1922</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref117" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Notes</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146151" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146151" type="Folder">20</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref118" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Blueprint of Alexander's Tomb</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146150" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146150" type="Folder">21</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1915/1915">1915</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref119">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Oversized items housed in OV 24</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref120" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Alexander Fund and Studio at MacDowell Colony</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146146" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                    </did>
                    <c03 id="ref121" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Reports</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146149" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146149" type="Folder">22</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1910/1926" type="inclusive">circa 1915-1926</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref122" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Images</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146148" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146148" type="Folder">23</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1905/1944" type="inclusive">circa 1910-1944</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref123" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Studio Book</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146147" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146147" type="Folder">24</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1920/1941" type="inclusive">circa 1925-1941</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref124" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Memorial Resolutions</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146145" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146145" type="Folder">25-29</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(5 folders; oversized items housed in OV 24)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1910/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1915</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref125" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Commemorative Lecture by Edwin Blashfield</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146144" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146144" type="Folder">30</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1917/1917">1917</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref126" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Award Certificates</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146143" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">24 (OV)</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1873/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1878-1915</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref127">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Items scanned with Box 2, f16</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref128" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Blueprint of Alexander's Tomb</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146142" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">24 (OV)</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1915/1915">1915</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref129">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Item scanned with Box 2, f21</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref130" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Memorial Resolution</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146141" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">24 (OV)</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1910/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1915</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref131">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Item scanned with Box 2, f25</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref134" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Artwork</unittitle>
                    <unitid>Series 7</unitid>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>1.5 Linear feet</extent>
                        <extent>Boxes 2-3, 14-16, OV 23</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1870/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1875-1915</unitdate>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref175">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>This series contains 13 sketchbooks, sketches and drawings on loose paper, and reproductions of John White Alexander's artwork in a variety of print media, including fine prints by various printmakers. An engraved portrait of Alexander by Arthur G. Learned is also found at the end of the series.</p>
                    <p>Sketchbooks contain drawings, sketches, cartoons, and illustrations in pencil, ink, wash, and gouache. A few are dated in the original. Others have been assigned dates during processing based on their content: cartoons and illustrations are dated to Alexander's main period of newspaper and magazine work (1873-1899), and sketches related to murals are dated to the murals' years of execution (Library of Congress, 1896; Carnegie Institute, 1905-1908). Additional notes on sketchbook content are found in the folder listing.</p>
                    <p>Loose sketches are filed by media, including charcoal, pencil, wash, and ink. Most of the pencil sketches are preliminary studies of allegorical figures and appear to relate to mural projects. Wash and ink drawings are more finished in appearance and were executed on Bristol board, and may have been published illustrations.</p>
                    <p>Reproductions of artwork consist of halftone prints, etchings, and engravings of Alexander's cartoons, paintings, murals, and illustrations. Reproductions are found on loose pages and in two oversized volumes. Many of the reproductions are fine prints and are signed by the printmaker. Names include George Bartle, John William Evans, Thomas Heard, William Fowler Hopson, Thomas Johnson, Frederick Juengling, W.H. Morse, Caroline A. Powell, Harry Elliott Sylvester, John H.E. Whitney, and Henry Wolf.</p>
                    <p>The second volume of reproductions also contains other types of materials, including six photographs of artwork, one sketched caricature of Alexander dated 1885, and five photographs picturing Alexander around 1903 to 1913. Among the loose reproductions are two large color prints are signed by Alexander, and installation views of the 1915 memorial exhibition at Arden Galleries.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <arrangement id="ref176">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>Additional sketches and illustrated letters are found in Correspondence and Notes and Writings series, and additional art reproductions are found in Scrapbooks and Photographs. This series has been scanned in its entirety.</p>
                </arrangement>
                <c02 id="ref135" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Sketchbooks</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146140" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">2</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146140" type="Folder">31-33</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(3 folders; oversized items housed in box 14)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1868/1899" type="inclusive">circa 1873-1899</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref136">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(sketchbooks contain primarily cartoons and illustrations and are dated to Alexander's main years of newspaper and magazine work)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref137" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Sketchbook</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146139" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146139" type="Folder">1</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1875/1881" type="inclusive">circa 1880-1881</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref138">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(inscribed July 1880; contains sketches from life; also contains sketches of illustrations depicting African Americans)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref139" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Sketchbook</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146138" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146138" type="Folder">2</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1884/1884">1884</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref140">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(travel sketchbook with dated sketches, one of which is labeled "Tangier")</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref141" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Sketchbook</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146137" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146137" type="Folder">3</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1886/1891" type="inclusive">circa 1891</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref142">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(cover reads "B. Alexander, 1891"; may have belonged to Elizabeth Alexander, who went by the name Betsy or Bessie; contains seascapes, figures and a page of text)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref143" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Sketchbooks</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146136" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146136" type="Folder">4-5</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(2 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1891/1896" type="inclusive">circa 1896</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref144">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(contain pencil sketches of figures, landscapes, and several lunettes that appear to be related to Alexander's Library of Congress murals, executed 1896)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref145" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Sketchbook</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146135" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146135" type="Folder">6</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1900/1908" type="inclusive">circa 1905-1908</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref146">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Oversized items housed in Box 14</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <scopecontent id="ref147">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(among the work in this volume are sketches from Alexander's murals at the Carnegie Institute, Pittsburgh, executed 1905-1908)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref148" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Sketchbooks</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146134" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146134" type="Folder">7-10</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(4 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref149">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(five undated volumes containing a variety of work in pencil, wash, gouache, and ink; two volumes were purchased in Europe.)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref150" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Charcoal Sketch</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146133" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146133" type="Folder">11</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref151" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Pencil Sketches</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146132" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146132" type="Folder">12-16</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(5 folders; oversized items housed in OV 23)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1891/1909" type="inclusive">circa 1896-1909</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref152">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(loose sketches in these folders are mainly of allegorical figures; many are recognizable from Alexander's murals at the Carnegie Institute, Pittsburgh, executed 1905-1908; a few cartoons are found; folders are dated to the period of Alexander's mural projects)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref153" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Wash and Ink Drawings</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146131" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146131" type="Folder">17</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1868/1899" type="inclusive">circa 1873-1899</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref154">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(contains a series of maritime scenes in wash and gouache on Bristol board, and a single figure in period costume; assuming these are illustrations, they are dated to Alexander's main period of illustration.)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref155" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Etchings, Engravings, and Reproductions of Artwork</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146126" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                    </did>
                    <c03 id="ref156" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Bound Volume 1</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146130" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146130" type="Folder">18</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1881/1894" type="inclusive">circa 1886-1894</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref157">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Oversized items housed in Box 15</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref158" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Items Removed from Bound Volume 1</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146129" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146129" type="Folder">19</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1881/1894" type="inclusive">circa 1886-1894</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref159" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Bound Volume 2</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146128" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146128" type="Folder">20</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1880/1996" type="inclusive">circa 1885-1996</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref160">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Oversized items housed in Box 16, sol</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref161" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Loose Items</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146127" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146127" type="Folder">21-24</container>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>(4 folders; oversized items housed in OV 23) </extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1881/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1886-1915</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref162" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Etched Portrait of John White Alexander by A.G. Learned</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146125" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146125" type="Folder">25</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref163">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Oversized items housed in OV 23</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref164" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Sketchbooks</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146124" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">14
                            (sol)</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(Items scanned with Box 2, folders 31-32 and Box 3, folder
                                6)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1868/1908" type="inclusive">circa 1873-1908</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref165" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Bound Volume 1 of Art Reproductions</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146123" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">15
                            (sol)</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1891/1909" type="inclusive">circa 1896-1909</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref166">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Items scanned with Box 3, folder 18</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref167" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Bound Volume 2 of Art Reproductions</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146122" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">16
                            (sol)</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1881/1894" type="inclusive">circa 1886-1894</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref168">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Items scanned with Box 3, folder 20</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref169" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Sketch</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146121" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">23
                            (OV)</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1880/1896" type="inclusive">circa 1885-1896</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref170">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Item scanned with box 3, f12</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref171" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Etchings, Engravings, and Reproductions of Artwork, Loose Items</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146120" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">23
                            (OV)</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1881/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1886-1915</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref172">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Items scanned with Box 3, folder 21</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref173" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Etched Portrait of Alexander by A.G. Learned</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146119" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">23
                            (OV)</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref174">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Item scanned with Box 3, f25</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref177" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Scrapbooks</unittitle>
                    <unitid>Series 8</unitid>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>1.8 Linear feet</extent>
                        <extent>Boxes 17-22</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1872/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1877-1915</unitdate>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref193">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>Eight scrapbooks date primarily from 1888 to 1915, with some earlier clippings in the first volume from Alexander's first trip to Europe in the late 1870s. Scrapbooks begin shortly after his marriage to Elizabeth Alexander and contain annotations that appear to be in her handwriting. Thus, the scrapbooks may have been created by her.</p>
                    <p>Most of the contents of the scrapbooks are newspaper and magazine clippings, with articles about Alexander's art activities and reproductions of his paintings. Also found are scattered letters from patrons and organizations announcing honors and thanking Alexander for commissioned portraits. Other types of items in the scrapbooks include exhibition invitations and catalogs, invitations to club events, programs for speaking engagements, and a few photographs.</p>
                    <p>Exhibition catalogs in the scrapbooks include Alexander's one-man show at Durand-Ruel Galleries (1901-1902), Pratt Institute (1905), the National Arts Club retrospective (1909), the Albright Knox gallery retrospective (1909), and the Art Institute of Chicago (1913). Other special contents of individual scrapbooks are noted in the folder listing.</p>
                    <p>Contents of scrapbooks are in loose chronological order, with each volume covering three to five years. Scattered items fall outside of the date ranges indicated for each volume. Additional volumes containing art reproductions, engravings, and photographs are found in the artwork series. Additional exhibition catalogs and clippings are found in the Printed Materials series.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <arrangement id="ref194">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>This series has been scanned in its entirety.</p>
                </arrangement>
                <c02 id="ref178" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Scrapbook</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146118" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">17
                            (sol)</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146118" type="Folder">1</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1872/1895" type="inclusive">circa 1877-1895</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref179">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(contains 1893 letter from Puvis de Chavannes re: membership in the Societe Nationale des Beaux-Arts, 1896 letter from Prince Eugene of Sweeden and Norway inviting Alexander to exhibit)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref180" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Scrapbook</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146117" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">17
                            (sol)</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146117" type="Folder">2</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1895/1900" type="inclusive">1895-1900</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref181" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Scrapbook</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146116" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">18
                            (sol)</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146116" type="Folder">1</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1900/1904" type="inclusive">1900-1904</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref182">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(contains photograph of the jury of Etchings and Engravings, Paris Exposition, 1900, on which Alexander served; 1901 letter from Emile Loubet, president of France, and a notice of the same year of his honor of Crois de Chevalier de L'Ordre Nationale de la Legion d'Honneur; 1904 letter from Edward Coates awarding him the Gold Medal of Honor by the Pennsylvania Academy)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref183" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Scrapbook</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146115" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">18
                            (sol)</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146115" type="Folder">2</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1904/1907" type="inclusive">1904-1907</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref184">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(contains letters from Henry van Dyke, V. van Syckel, Jane Potter Russell, Walter Gunnison, and K.M., possibly Katherine Mackay; also, telegram from JWA to EA informing her of the Carnegie mural contract for $175,000)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref185" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Scrapbook</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146114" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">19
                            (sol)</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146114" type="Folder">1</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1907/1909" type="inclusive">1907-1909</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref186">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Contains program for MacDowell club event with tableaux by Alexander; extensive publicity for the Carnegie Institute murals; and a 1908 note from H. W. Mabie)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref187" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Scrapbook</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146113" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">20
                            (sol)</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146113" type="Folder">1</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1909/1911" type="inclusive">1909-1911</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref188">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(contains letter from George A. Hearn; programs and publicity for Maude Adams productions of John of Arc and Chanticler)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref189" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Scrapbook</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146112" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">21
                            (sol)</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146112" type="Folder">1</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1910/1913" type="inclusive">1910-1913</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref190">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(contains note from Florence Levy re: honors from the School Art League; letter from Robert Underwood Johnson re: membership in the American Academy of Arts and Letters; 1912 photograph of the Pittsburgh International Jury, of which Alexander was a member; an invitation to a dinner honoring Alexander Drake, reproducing a cartoon by Alexander)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref191" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Scrapbook</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146111" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">22
                            (sol)</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146111" type="Folder">1</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1914/1915" type="inclusive">1914-1915</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref192">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(contains annotations related to publicity over Alexander's failure to complete the Carnegie murals)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref195" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Printed Materials</unittitle>
                    <unitid>Series 9</unitid>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>1.5 Linear feet</extent>
                        <extent>Boxes 3-4, OV 23</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1886/1945" type="inclusive">circa 1891-1945</unitdate>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref232">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>This series contains magazine and newspaper clippings, exhibition catalogs, circulars, bulletins, reports, books, pamphlets, and brochures.</p>
                    <p>Clippings in this series are often duplicated in Scrapbooks, especially those dating to Alexander's lifetime. Later clippings are unique to this series. The scope of subjects found in this series is also greater, including not only stories about Alexander's career, but also about other artists, family matters, and Elizabeth Alexander's career before and after her husband's death.</p>
                    <p>Exhibition catalogs are found for Alexander's solo exhibitions, before and after his death. Scattered catalogs for other artists' exhibitions are also found. The 1905 catalog of a Pratt Institute exhibition contains prices, and a 1915 catalog for his memorial exhibition is marked with scattered corrections and sales. Additional exhibition catalogs are found in Scrapbooks.</p>
                    <p>Circulars include an unsigned, printed letter of protest to the Metropolitan Museum of Art related to an exhibition of European modernists. Entire issues of a variety of magazines are found, several of which contain major articles related to Alexander and his artwork. See details in the folder listing. Bulletins and reports relate to organizations in which Alexander was involved or exhibited. Miscellaneous printed materials include calling cards, a magazine subscription, and a civil defense poster.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <arrangement id="ref233">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>Additional printed materials are found throughout the collection, especially in Artwork and Scrapbooks. See series descriptions for more details. The bulk of this series has been scanned. Items not scanned include newspaper and magazine clippings, and for some published items, only the covers have been scanned.</p>
                </arrangement>
                <c02 id="ref196" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Magazine Clippings</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146110" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146110" type="Folder">26-27</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(2 folders; oversized items housed in OV 23; not
                                scanned)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1891/1922" type="inclusive">circa 1896-1922</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref197" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Newspaper Clippings</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146109" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146109" type="Folder">28-30</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(3 folders; not scanned)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref198" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Newspaper Clippings</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146108" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146108" type="Folder">31-38</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(8 folders; not scanned)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1900/1914" type="inclusive">1900-1914</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref199" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Newspaper Clippings</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146107" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146107" type="Folder">39-48</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(10 folders; not scanned)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1915/1915">1915</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref200" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Newspaper Clippings</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146106" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">3</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146106" type="Folder">49-51</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(3 of 12 folders; not scanned)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1916/1916">1916</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref201" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Newspaper Clippings</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146105" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146105" type="Folder">1-9</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(9 of 12 folders; not scanned)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1916/1916">1916</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref202" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Newspaper Clippings</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146104" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146104" type="Folder">10-16</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(7 folders; not scanned)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1917/1918" type="inclusive">1917-1918</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref203" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Newspaper Clippings</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146103" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146103" type="Folder">17</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1924/1940" type="inclusive">1924-1940</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref204">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>not scanned</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref205" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Exhibition Catalogs</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146102" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146102" type="Folder">18</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1902/1905" type="inclusive">1902-1905</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref206" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Exhibition Catalogs</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146101" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146101" type="Folder">19-21</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(3 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1915/1918" type="inclusive">1915-1918</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref207" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Exhibition Catalogs</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146100" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146100" type="Folder">22-24</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(3 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1937/1945" type="inclusive">1937-1945</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref208" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Exhibition Poster and Wall Text</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146099" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146099" type="Folder">25</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref209">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Oversized items housed in OV 23</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref210" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Circulars</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146098" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146098" type="Folder">26</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1903/1903">circa 1908, 1921</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref211" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Memorial Essay by William Laurel Harris</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146097" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146097" type="Folder">27</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1910/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1915</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref212" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Magazines</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146096" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146096" type="Folder">28-33</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(6 folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1909/1933" type="inclusive">circa 1914-1933</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref213">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Articles include "A Visit to Mr. Alexander's Summer Studio," by Elbert F. Baldwin (page proof); "Is Our Art Distinctively American," by JWA in Century, various obituaries and memorials; "The JWA Murals" in Carnegie Magazine; "The Portrait Work of John W. Alexander" by John V. Sears)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref214" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Bulletins</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146095" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146095" type="Folder">34</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1913/1913">1913</unitdate>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1937/1937">1937</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref215">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(School Art League, Mint Museum of Art)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref216" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Reports</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146092" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                    </did>
                    <c03 id="ref217" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Société Royale Des Beaux-Arts (Brussels, Belgium)</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146094" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146094" type="Folder">35</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1908/1908">1908</unitdate>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1911/1911">1911</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref218" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>New York City Improvement Commission</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146093" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146093" type="Folder">36</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1907/1907">1907</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref219" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Books</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146088" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                    </did>
                    <c03 id="ref220" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Autobiography of Worthington Whittridge</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146091" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146091" type="Folder">37</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce">after 1941</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref221" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>American Academy of Arts and Letters 
                                <emph render="italic">Book of Record</emph></unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146090" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146090" type="Folder">38</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1922/1922">1922</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref222" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Smithsonian Institution National Gallery of Art</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146089" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146089" type="Folder">39</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1922/1922">1922</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref223" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Pamphlets, Brochures, and Mailings</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146087" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146087" type="Folder">40</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1926/1926">1926</unitdate>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref224" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Miscellaneous Printed Materials</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146086" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146086" type="Folder">41</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1886/1945" type="inclusive">circa 1891-1945</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref225">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Oversized item housed in OV 23</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref226" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Magazine Clippings</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146085" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">23
                            (OV)</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1891/1922" type="inclusive">circa 1896-1922</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref227">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>not scanned</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref228" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Exhibition Poster and Wall Text</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146084" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">23
                            (OV)</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref229">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Items scanned with Box 4, f25</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref230" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Miscellaneous Printed Materials</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146083" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">23
                            (OV)</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1886/1945" type="inclusive">circa 1891-1945</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref231">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Item scanned with Box 4, f41</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref234" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Photographs</unittitle>
                    <unitid>Series 10</unitid>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>4.2 Linear feet</extent>
                        <extent>Boxes 4-8, MGP 1-2, OV 25-43, RD 44-45</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1865/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1870-1915</unitdate>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref363">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>This series contains photographs of John White Alexander, friends and associates, family members, studios, places, exhibitions, and works of art.</p>
                    <p>Dozens of formal portraits are found depicting Alexander, many taken by notable photographers, including Zaida Ben-Yusuf, Aimé Dupont, Curtis Bell, Elizabeth Buehrmann, and several signed Miss Huggins, who may have been Estelle Huntington Huggins, a New York painter and photographer. Also found are photographs made in the well-known studios of Pach, Sarony, and George Rockwood. Portraits of others include Alexander's friends William Merritt Chase and Edward Austin Abbey.</p>
                    <p>Groups portraits depict Carnegie Founders' Day, the Metro Club, and the National Academy of Design. Juries include the Carnegie International Exhibition, the National Academy of Design, and one group identified as both the Academy jury and the last meeting of the Paris Society of American Artists.</p>
                    <p>Annotations are found throughout the series, in what appears to be either John White Alexander's or Elizabeth Alexander's handwriting. Mrs. Alexander's annotations in particular sometimes contradict information found in the photograph itself, or on other photographs of the same subjects. Contradictory annotations are particularly common among jury, studio, and personal photographs, and photographs of works of art.</p>
                    <p>Photographs of Alexander's studios include spaces in New York City; Paris; Sea Bright, New Jersey; and Onteora, New York; Alexander is pictured in some of the studios. Also found are photographs of the Alexander Memorial Studio built at the MacDowell Colony in New Hampshire after Alexander's death, several of which were taken by photographer Jesse Tarbox Beals. See Awards and Memorials for more images and documentation of the MacDowell studio.</p>
                    <p>Individuals identified in personal photographs include Alexander, Katherine Beatty, Ed Moran, Thomas S. Clarke, and Alexander's son, James. Also pictured here is Alexander with portraits painted at the Cowan residence in Scotland circa 1900, and Alexander in a mummy costume circa 1903-1904. Numerous photographs of unidentified children appear to have been taken in Alexander's Paris studio. Photographs of Polling, Bavaria show scenic views and architectural details.</p>
                    <p>Photographs of works of art span Alexander's career and are sometimes annotated with titles, dates of execution, and often owners. Note that annotations are sometimes contradictory. Photographs of paintings are arranged in broad chronological groups, with approximate dates noted in parentheses in the folder listing. These dates have not been verified, however, and many paintings are undated.</p>
                    <p>Original glass negatives are found for several personal photographs, photographs of studios, and photographs of works of art. Several of the negatives of works of art are retouched and numbered in the original. Recent prints have been made from the original negatives are filed along with vintage prints. Note that recent prints of paintings have been cropped to the picture frame and do not show the negative images in their entirety.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <arrangement id="ref364">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>Additional photographs are found in Awards and Memorials, Artwork, and Scrapbooks. The bulk of this series has been scanned. Items not scanned include photographs of artwork, and duplicate photographs. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.</p>
                </arrangement>
                <c02 id="ref235" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Portraits of John White Alexander</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146059" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                    </did>
                    <c03 id="ref236" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Curtis Bell</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146082" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146082" type="Folder">42</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1895/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1900-1915</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref237">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Oversized items housed in OV 25</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref238" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Curtis Bell, Copies</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146081" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146081" type="Folder">43</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1895/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1900-1915</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref239">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Not scanned</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref240" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Zaida Ben-Yusuf</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146080" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146080" type="Folder">44</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1895/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1900-1915</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref241">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Oversized items housed in OV 25</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref242" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Zaida Ben-Yusuf, Copies</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146079" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">4</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146079" type="Folder">45</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1895/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1900-1915</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref243">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Not scanned</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref244" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Bradley</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146078" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146078" type="Folder">1</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1908/1913" type="inclusive">circa 1913</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref245">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Oversized items housed in OV 25</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref246" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Elizabeth Buehrman</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146077" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146077" type="Folder">2</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1904/1912" type="inclusive">circa 1909-1912</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref247">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Oversized items housed in OV 25</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref248" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Elizabeth Buehrman, Copies</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146076" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146076" type="Folder">3</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1904/1912" type="inclusive">circa 1909-1912</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref249">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Not scanned</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref250" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photograph by Dana (Photography Studio; Brooklyn, NY)</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146075" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146075" type="Folder">4</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1865/1879" type="inclusive">circa 1870-1879</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref251" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Davis and Sanford</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146074" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146074" type="Folder">5</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1906/1911" type="inclusive">circa 1911</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref252">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Oversized items housed in OV 25</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref253" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Aimé Dupont</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146073" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146073" type="Folder">6</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1915/1915">1915</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref254">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Oversized items housed in OV 25</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref255" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Davis Garber</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146072" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146072" type="Folder">7</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref256" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Miss Huggins</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146071" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146071" type="Folder">8</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1898/1913" type="inclusive">circa 1903-1913</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref257">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Oversized items housed in OV 25</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref258" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Miss Huggins, Copies</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146070" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146070" type="Folder">9</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1898/1913" type="inclusive">circa 1903-1913</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref259">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Not scanned</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref260" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Chester Abbott Lawrence</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146069" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146069" type="Folder">10</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1899/1904" type="inclusive">circa 1904</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref261" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Pach (Photography Studio, New York)</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146068" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146068" type="Folder">11</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1907/1912" type="inclusive">circa 1912</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref262" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photograph by Otto Reitmayer (Photography Studio, Munich)</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146067" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146067" type="Folder">12</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1877/1877">1877</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref263" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Rockwood (Photography Studio, New York)</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146066" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146066" type="Folder">13</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1883/1896" type="inclusive">circa 1888-1896</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref264" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Sarony (Photography Studio, New York)</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146065" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146065" type="Folder">14</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1874/1885" type="inclusive">circa 1879-1885</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref265">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Oversized items housed in OV 25</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref266" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by Sarony (Photography Studio, New York), Copies</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146064" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146064" type="Folder">15</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1874/1885" type="inclusive">circa 1879-1885</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref267">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Not scanned</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref268" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs by E. Syms</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146063" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146063" type="Folder">16</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref269" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographer Unknown</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146062" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146062" type="Folder">17</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce">before 1880</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref270" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographer Unknown</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146061" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146061" type="Folder">18</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1885/1909" type="inclusive">circa 1890-1909</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref271">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>(1 glass plate negative housed in Box 7)</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref272" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographer Unknown</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146060" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146060" type="Folder">19</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1885/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1890-1915</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref273">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>(2 glass plate negatives housed in MGP 1)</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref274" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Portraits of Others</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146053" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                    </did>
                    <c03 id="ref275" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Edward Austin Abbey</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146058" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146058" type="Folder">20</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1875/1889" type="inclusive">circa 1880-1889</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref276" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>William Merritt Chase</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146057" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146057" type="Folder">21</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1865/1879" type="inclusive">circa 1870-1879</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref277">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Oversized items housed in OV 26</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref278" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Robert Louis Stevenson</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146056" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146056" type="Folder">22</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1875/1894" type="inclusive">circa 1880-1894</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref279" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Ruth McEnery Stuart</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146055" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146055" type="Folder">23</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref280" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Unidentified Sitters</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146054" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146054" type="Folder">24-25</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref281">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>(2 glass plate negatives housed in MGP 1-2)</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <scopecontent id="ref282">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>(Probably subjects of portrait paintings by JWA)</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref283" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Group Portraits and Juries</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146052" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146052" type="Folder">26</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1895/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1900-1915</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref284">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Oversized items housed in OV 26</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref285" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Studio, Alexander Memorial Studio at the MacDowell Colony</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146051" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146051" type="Folder">27-30</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(4 folders; oversized items housed in OV 27) </extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce">after 1915</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref286">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(includes photographs taken by Jesse Tarbox Beals and Favor Davis; additional photographs and images are found in Awards and Memorials)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref287" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Studio, New York City</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146050" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146050" type="Folder">31</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1893/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1898-1915</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref288">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(J.W. Alexander pictured)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <scopecontent id="ref381">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(Oversized items housed in OV 27; 3 glass plate negatives housed in Box 7)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref289" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Studio; Onteora, New York</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146049" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146049" type="Folder">32</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1908/1913" type="inclusive">circa 1913</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref290">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Oversized items housed in OV 27</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <scopecontent id="ref291">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(J.W. Alexander pictured)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref292" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Studio, Paris</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146048" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146048" type="Folder">33</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1887/1898" type="inclusive">circa 1892-1898</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref293">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Oversized items housed in OV 27</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <scopecontent id="ref294">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(J.W. Alexander pictured)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref295" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Studio; Sea Bright, New Jersey</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146047" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146047" type="Folder">34</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1883/1908" type="inclusive">circa 1888-1908</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref296" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Personal Photographs</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146046" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146046" type="Folder">35-37</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1877/1912" type="inclusive">circa 1882-1912</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref382">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(3 folders; oversized items housed in OV 27; 1 glass plate negative housed in MGP 2)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref297" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Personal Photographs, Copies</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146045" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146045" type="Folder">38</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1877/1912" type="inclusive">circa 1882-1912</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref298">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Not scanned</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref299" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Polling, Bavaria</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146044" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146044" type="Folder">39</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1873/1886" type="inclusive">circa 1878-1886</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref300">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>includes negatives</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref301" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Photographs of Works of Art</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146029" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                    </did>
                    <c03 id="ref302" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Installation Views, Art Institute of Chicago</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146043" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146043" type="Folder">40</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1898/1898">circa 1903, 1907</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref303">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Oversized items housed in OV 28</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref304" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Murals</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146036" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                        </did>
                        <c04 id="ref305" level="file">
                            <did>
                                <unittitle>Library of Congress Murals (1896)</unittitle>
                                <container id="cid3146042" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                                <container parent="cid3146042" type="Folder">41</container>
                                <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                            </did>
                            <scopecontent id="ref306">
                                <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                                <p>Not scanned</p>
                            </scopecontent>
                        </c04>
                        <c04 id="ref307" level="file">
                            <did>
                                <unittitle>Carnegie Institute Murals In Progress</unittitle>
                                <container id="cid3146041" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                                <container parent="cid3146041" type="Folder">42</container>
                                <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1900/1908" type="inclusive">circa 1905-1908</unitdate>
                            </did>
                            <scopecontent id="ref308">
                                <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                                <p>(snapshots with workers pictured)</p>
                            </scopecontent>
                        </c04>
                        <c04 id="ref309" level="file">
                            <did>
                                <unittitle>Carnegie Institute Murals, Preliminary Drawings</unittitle>
                                <container id="cid3146040" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                                <container parent="cid3146040" type="Folder">43</container>
                                <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1900/1908" type="inclusive">circa 1905-1908</unitdate>
                            </did>
                            <scopecontent id="ref310">
                                <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                                <p>Not scanned</p>
                            </scopecontent>
                        </c04>
                        <c04 id="ref311" level="file">
                            <did>
                                <unittitle>Carnegie Institute Murals (1905-1908)</unittitle>
                                <container id="cid3146039" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                                <container parent="cid3146039" type="Folder">44-47</container>
                                <physdesc>
                                    <extent>(4 folders; oversized items housed in OV 28-36; not
                                        scanned)</extent>
                                </physdesc>
                                <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                            </did>
                        </c04>
                        <c04 id="ref312" level="file">
                            <did>
                                <unittitle>Carnegie Institute Murals, Lantern Slides</unittitle>
                                <container id="cid3146038" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                                <container parent="cid3146038" type="Folder">48</container>
                                <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1903/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1908-1915</unitdate>
                            </did>
                            <scopecontent id="ref313">
                                <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                                <p>(8 lantern slides made by Charles Beseler of New York and identified in what appears to be JWA's handwriting)</p>
                            </scopecontent>
                            <scopecontent id="ref314">
                                <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                                <p>(8 lantern slides housed in Box 8; not scanned)</p>
                            </scopecontent>
                        </c04>
                        <c04 id="ref315" level="file">
                            <did>
                                <unittitle>Unidentified Mural</unittitle>
                                <container id="cid3146037" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                                <container parent="cid3146037" type="Folder">49</container>
                                <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                            </did>
                            <scopecontent id="ref316">
                                <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                                <p>Not scanned</p>
                            </scopecontent>
                        </c04>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref317" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Paintings (circa 1879-1899), Vintage Prints</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146035" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">5</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146035" type="Folder">50-59</container>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>(10 of 16 folders; not scanned)</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref318" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Paintings (circa 1879-1899), Vintage Prints</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146034" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">6</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146034" type="Folder">1-6</container>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>(6 of 16 folders; oversized items hosued in OV 37-39; not
                                    scanned)</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref319" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Paintings (circa 1900-1915), Vintage Prints</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146033" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">6</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146033" type="Folder">7-25</container>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>(19 folders; oversized items housed in OV 40-42; not
                                    scanned)</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1906/1906">1906</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref320" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Paintings (circa 1898-1904), Recent Prints from Glass Negatives</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146032" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">6</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146032" type="Folder">26</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref321">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>not scanned</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref322" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Poster, Sculpture, and Drawing (circa 1880-1915)</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146031" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">6</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146031" type="Folder">27</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref323">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>not scanned</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref324" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Photographs of Works of Art by Others (circa 1880-1899)</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid3146030" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">6</container>
                            <container parent="cid3146030" type="Folder">28</container>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>(Oversized items housed in OV 43, rolled documents 44-45;
                                    not scanned) </extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref325">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>(includes a portrait of John White Alexander by Frank Duveneck, a portrait of P.W. Bartlett by Charles Sprague Pearce, and around 20 rolled and fragile prints of Rodin sculptures with the note "Given to JWA and EA in Paris circa 1899")</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref326" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Photo Lab Envelopes</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146028" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">6</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146028" type="Folder">29</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1921/1921">1921</unitdate>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1910/1910">1910</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref327">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>not scanned</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref328" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Glass Plate Negatives, Portraits of John White Alexander</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid5788001" label="Negatives" type="Box">7</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1 Glass negatives</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref329">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Scanned with Box 5, f18-19</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref384" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Glass Plate Negatives, Portraits of John White Alexander</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid5788002" label="Negatives" type="Box">MGP 1</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>2 Glass negatives</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref385">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Scanned with Box 5, f18-19</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref330" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Glass Plate Negatives, Portraits of Unidentified Sitters</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid5788003" label="Negatives" type="Box">MGP 1</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1 Glass negatives</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref331">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Scanned with Box 5, f25</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref386" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Glass Plate Negatives, Portraits of Unidentified Sitters</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid5789001" label="Negatives" type="Box">MGP 2</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1 Glass negatives</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref387">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Scanned with Box 5, f25</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref332" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Glass Plate Negatives, New York City Studio</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid5789002" label="Negatives" type="Box">7</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>3 Glass negatives</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref333">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Scanned with Box 5, f31</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref334" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Glass Plate Negative, Personal Photographs</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid5789003" label="Negatives" type="Box">MGP 2</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1 Glass negatives</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref335">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Scanned with Box 5, f37</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref338" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Glass Plate Negatives, Paintings</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid5789004" label="Negatives" type="Box">7</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>41 Glass negatives</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1893/1904" type="inclusive">circa 1898-1904</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref339">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>not scanned</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref336" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Lantern Slides, Carnegie Institute Murals, Lantern Slides</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146023" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">8
                            (pam)</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref337">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>not scanned</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref340" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Portraits of John White Alexander by Curtis Bell, Zaida Ben-Yusuf, Bradley, Elizabeth Buehrman, Davis and Sanford, Aimé Dupont, Miss Huggins, and Sarony</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146021" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">25 (OV)</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref380">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Scanned with Box 4, f42 and 44, Box 5, f1, 2, 5, 6, 8, 14</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref341" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Portrait of William Merritt Chase</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146020" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">26 (OV)</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref342">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Scanned with Box 5, f21</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref343" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Group Portraits and Juries</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146019" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">26 (OV)</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref344">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Scanned with Box 5, f26</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref345" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Photographs of Studios</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146018" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">27 (OV)</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref346">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Scanned with Box 5, f28, 31-33</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref347" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Personal Photographs</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146017" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">27 (OV)</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref348">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Scanned with Box 5, f38</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref349" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Photographs of Works of Art, Installation Views</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146016" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">28 (OV)</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref350">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Scanned with Box 5, f40</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref351" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Photographs of Carnegie Institute Murals</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146015" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">28-36 (OV)</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref352">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>not scanned</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref353" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Photographs of Paintings, Vintage Prints</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146014" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">37-39 (OV)</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1874/1899" type="inclusive">circa 1879-1899</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref354">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>not scanned</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref355" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Photographs of Paintings, Vintage Prints</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146013" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">40-42 (OV)</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1895/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1900-1915</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref356">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>not scanned</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref357" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Photographs of Drawings and Poster</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146012" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">43 (OV)</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref358">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>not scanned</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref359" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oversized Photographs of Works of Art by Others</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146011" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">43 (OV)</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref360">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>not scanned</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref361" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Photographs of Rodin Sculptures</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146010" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">44-45 (RD)</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref362">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>not scanned</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref365" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Artifacts</unittitle>
                    <unitid>Series 11</unitid>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>0.4 Linear feet</extent>
                        <extent>Box 6 and artifact cabinet</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1894/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1899-1915</unitdate>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref379">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>This series contains a variety of objects found among Alexander's papers. The metal door plate reads "J.W. Alexander, Artist" and is signed J.C. Michel and Son. Printing plates are for an ex-libris engraving and two newspaper photographs. Souvenir pendants are from dedications of the Carnegie Institute in 1907 and the New York Public Library in 1911. Title plates from exhibited paintings include one for "Sunlight" and another for a portrait of Mercer Beasley, LLD.</p>
                    <p>The bulk of this series has been scanned.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <c02 id="ref366" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Door Plate</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146009" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">6</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146009" type="Folder">30</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref367" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Hand-sewn Book Cover</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146008" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">6</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146008" type="Folder">31</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref368" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Laurel Wreath</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146007" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">6</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146007" type="Folder">32</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref369">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(See Artifact Cabinet)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref370" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Palette</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146006" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">6</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146006" type="Folder">33</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref371">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(See Artifact Cabinet)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref372" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Printing Plates</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146005" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">6</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146005" type="Folder">34-36</container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>(3 folders; not scanned)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1910/1910">circa 1915, undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref373" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Relief Model for Pendant</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146004" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">6</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146004" type="Folder">37</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1775/1968" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref374" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Souvenir Engraving of Mark Twain Self-Portrait</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146003" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">6</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146003" type="Folder">38</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1902/1902">1902</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref375">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Not scanned</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref376" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Souvenir Pendants</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146002" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">6</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146002" type="Folder">39</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1907/1907">1907</unitdate>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1911/1911">1911</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref377">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>(made for School Art League award; see Awards and Memorials for Alexander's award medal dated 1911)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref378" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Title Plates from Paintings</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid3146001" label="Mixed Materials" type="Box">6</container>
                        <container parent="cid3146001" type="Folder">40</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1894/1911" type="inclusive">circa 1899-1911</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>