<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "/eadcb/shared/ead/ead.dtd">

<ead audience="external" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
<eadid mainagencycode="DSI-AAA" countrycode="us" url="http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/findingaids/xml/amerwate.xml">amerwate</eadid>

<filedesc>
	<titlestmt>
		<titleproper>American Watercolor Society</titleproper>
		<subtitle>A Finding Aid to the American Watercolor Society Records, <date type="inclusive">1867-1977</date> <date type="bulk">, bulk 1950-1970</date>, in the Archives of American Art</subtitle>
		<author>by Erin Corley</author>
		<sponsor>Funding for the processing of this collection was provided by the Terra Foundation for American Art.</sponsor>
	</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
	<publisher>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</publisher>
	<date type="publication">May 09, 2007</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Erin Corley on
<date>May 09, 2007</date>
</creation>
<langusage><language>English</language></langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>

<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory">
<did>
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
		<corpname>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</corpname>
	</repository>

	<origination label="Creator:">
		<corpname encodinganalog="110">American Watercolor Society</corpname>
	</origination>

	<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">American Watercolor Society records</unittitle>

	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f">1867-1977, bulk 1950-1970</unitdate>

	<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a">3.6 linear feet</physdesc>

	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">The records of the American Watercolor Society measure 3.6 linear feet and date from 1867 to 1977, with the bulk of the material dating from 1950 to 1970.  The collection provides scattered documentation of the operations and activities of one of the oldest continuously operating artists' organizations in the United States and includes records of its administration and history, membership, and exhibitions, as well as printed material and photographs.</abstract>

<!-- ONLY USE LANGMATERIAL TO NOTE LANGUAGES OTHER THAN OR IN ADDITION TO ENGLISH -->

	
</did>


<!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION GOES HERE: -->

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541" id="a19">
<head>Provenance</head>
<p>The American Watercolor Society loaned material for microfilming in 1968, and, in 1978, donated some of this material.  The bound volume of the record of works shown in annual exhibitions, 1897-1904, was microfilmed in 1972 and subsequently donated in 1978 by the American Antiquarian Society.</p>
</acqinfo>

<separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 0" id="a7">
<head>Separated Material</head>
<p>Originals of loaned material, including additional exhibition materials, correspondence, photographs, and administrative records were returned to the American Watercolor Society after microfilming.  Loaned material is available on reels N68-8 through N68-10, but is not described in the container listing of this  finding aid.</p>
</separatedmaterial>

<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 1" id="a6">
<head>Related Material</head>
<p>Additional records may be available by contacting the American Watercolor Society.</p>
</relatedmaterial>

<altformavail id="a17" encodinganalog="530">
<head>Alternative Forms Available</head>
<p>The bound volume of the record of works shown in annual exhibitions, 1897-1904, is available on 35 mm microfilm reel 497 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan.</p>
</altformavail>

<processinfo encodinganalog="583" id="a20">
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>The collection was initially received as a loan and microfilmed on reels N68-8 through N68-10. Portions of the loan were later donated and received preliminary processing.  The bound volume of the record of works shown in annual exhibitions was loaned and microfilmed on reel 497, and also later donated.  The entire collection was fully merged, processed, arranged, and described by Erin Corley in 2007 with funding provided by the Terra Foundation for American Art.</p>
</processinfo>

<prefercite encodinganalog="510" id="a18">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>American Watercolor Society records, 1867-1977, bulk 1950-1970. Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
</prefercite>

<accessrestrict id="a14" encodinganalog="506">
<head>Restrictions on Access</head>
<p>The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="a15">
<head>Ownership and Literary Rights</head>
<p>The American Watercolor Society records are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
</userestrict>


<!-- END ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->

<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GO HERE: -->



<bioghist altrender="biography" encodinganalog="545" id="a2">
<head>Historical Note</head>
<p>The American Watercolor Society still functions as an active artists' organization that was founded in New York City on December 5, 1866 as the American Society of Painters in Water Colors.  The first president was Samuel Colman.  Initially,  election to membership was very selective, consisting of active members and honorary members (those living outside of New York City).  From the beginning, the most important activity of the organization was its annual exhibition, open to both members and non-members, the first being held in the winter of 1867-1868. </p><p>The Society's first six annual exhibitions were held jointly with the National Academy of Design at the Academy's galleries.  Beginning with the seventh exhibition, the society initiated independent annual exhibitions until 1899.  The early exhibitions were very successful, and the society showed work from many prominent American and European artists such as Thomas Eakins, Abbott Thayer, Eugene Delacroix, and John Ruskin.  1888 marked the first year that the society awarded prizes to the best works.  By the early 1900s the society had developed a program for exhibitions that included a jury of selection and jury of awards.</p>
<p>In 1903 the society was officially incorporated as the American Water Color Society, to "advance the art of water color painting in this country."  Membership classifications changed slightly and artists were either classified as active (professional artists) or associate members.  By 1904 the society was struggling financially, and annual exhibitions were held at various spaces around New York City.  In 1905 the society established annual rotary (traveling) exhibitions.  From 1922 to 1931, the society combined exhibition venues with the New York Water Color Club (founded in 1890), and in January 1941 these two organizations merged under the name of the American Watercolor Society and created a new constitution.  This merger brought many female artists who were active in the New York Water Color Club to the society which had previously not recognized many women painters.  In 1941 the society established their headquarters in one room at the National Academy of Design's new building where they also held annual exhibitions in the galleries. </p>
<p>Frederic Whitaker, a painter and businessman, became president in 1949 and brought a renewed vigor to the society.  He reinstituted traveling exhibitions, created new committees, and increased the number of exhibition awards.  He also established an office in the Flatiron building and hired an Executive Secretary.  After he resigned in 1956, the society experienced a period of financial troubles that were immediately addressed when Mario Cooper became president in 1959.  Offices were moved back to the National Academy, several new officers were appointed, and after a period of fiscal austerity, a scholarship program and central awards fund were established. In 1967 the society had its 100th annual exhibition and also had an exhibition at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, entitled, "Two Hundred Years of Watercolor Painting In America, An Exhibition Commemorating The Centennial of the American Watercolor Society."  Over the next few years the society organized and exchanged exhibitions with other countries, including Canada, Mexico, England, and Australia.  Mario Cooper remained president until 1986, and the American Watercolor Society remains an active artists' organization today. </p>

</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520" id="a3">
<head>Scope and Content Note</head>
<p>The records of the American Watercolor Society measure 3.6 linear feet and date from 1867 to 1977, with the bulk of the material dating from 1950 to 1970.  The collection provides scattered documentation of the operations and activities of one of the oldest continuously operating artists' organizations in the United States and includes records of its administration and history, membership, and exhibitions
</p><p>
Records documenting the founding, history, and operations of the society are found in the administration and history series.  Included are written histories and material on the 1941 merger with the New York Water Color Club, including an updated Constitution and By-Laws.  Also found here are reports, committee documents, administrative correspondence, records of participation in national art events, and financial records.  
</p><p>
The membership records include a membership roster notebook, dating from 1953-1961, lists of members, member biographies, and correspondence regarding membership. The society's exhibition files include a bound volume of the record of works shown in the annual exhibition from 1897 to 1904, as well as files on a few other annual exhibitions and exchange exhibitions with other countries.  These files contain scattered correspondence, price lists, exhibition checklists and printed material.  
</p><p>
A small amount of printed material in the collection includes a booklet entitled, <emph render="italic">Water-Color Painting: Some Facts and Authorities in Relation to Its Durability</emph>, distributed by the society in 1868, as well as news clipping about events and exhibitions, newsletters, and other published items.  Photographs are of members, jurors, events, painting demonstrations, and artwork.   
</p>
<!-- add additional <p></p> tags as necessary -->
</scopecontent>


<!-- CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS GO HERE: -->


<controlaccess id="a12">
<head>Index Terms</head>
<p>This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms: </p>

<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects-Topical:</head>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Art -- Societies, etc. -- New York (State) -- New York</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Watercolor painting -- 19th century -- United States</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Watercolor painting -- 20th century -- United States</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Watercolor painting, American</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Watercolorists</subject>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Types of Materials:</head>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Photographs</genreform>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Names:</head>

<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh">New York Water Color Club</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh">American Water Color Society</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh">American Society of Painters in Water Colors</corpname>
</controlaccess>

</controlaccess>


<!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->

<!-- CONTINUE TOP-LEVEL METADATA HERE -->

<arrangement encodinganalog="351$b" id="a5">
<head>Arrangement</head>
<p>The collection is arranged into 5 series: </p>
<list>
<item>Series 1: Administration and History, 1891-1970 (Box 1-2; 1.1 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 2: Membership, 1941, 1951-1960s (Box 2; 0.7 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 3: Exhibition Files, 1867-1910, 1955-1975 (Box 2-3, BV02; 1.2 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 4: Printed Material, 1868, 1943-1972 (Box 3; 6 folders)</item>
<item>Series 5: Photographs, circa 1940-1977 (Box 3-4; 0.5 linear feet)</item>
</list>
</arrangement>



<!-- END TOP LEVEL METADATA -->


<!-- START DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->


<dsc type="combined" id="a23">
<head>Series Descriptions/Container Listing</head>

<!-- use this format if you have series only, no subseries -->
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 1: </unitid><unittitle>Administration and History, <unitdate>1891-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1-2; 1.1 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series consists of records documenting the administration and history of the American Watercolor Society.  Included is a draft of "A History of the American Watercolor Society: 1866-1950" and related notes, written by Frank Gervasi.  Gervasi was appointed the first Historian of the society in 1949.  Also found are documents about the American Watercolor Society Information Center which was established in the early 1950s to provide information about art and artists to the general public.  Other documents include leases for offices and exhibition space at the National Academy of Design, as well as legal documents, voting ballots, and recollections by J. Scott Williams regarding the society's merger with the New York Water Color Club. </p> <p>Additional records include the reports of Presidents Frederic Whitaker and Mario Cooper; records of the Gifts and Bequest Committee and Regional Committees; correspondence regarding publicity and other general administrative correspondence relating to board activities, events, the society's participation in national arts events, and other issues.  Also included are specific files on the society's participation in the Fine Arts Federation of New York and Artists for Victory, Inc., and a file of several lists of awards given by the American Watercolor Society.
</p><p>
Scattered financial records in this series include account books  and three general ledgers, monthly treasurer's reports, annual financial statements, other financial reports on matters such as catalog sales and exhibition expenses.  Also found are tax documents, records of paid bills, payments, and bank deposits, and correspondence regarding financial issues.  During the period covered by this documentation, Edgar A. Whitney and Cathy Altvater served as treasurer.  
</p> 
</scopecontent>

<arrangement> 
<p>Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.</p> 
</arrangement>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>History of the American Watercolor Society, <unitdate>1950-1952</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>American Watercolor Society Information Center, <unitdate>circa 1954</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Certificate of Incorporation (photocopy), <unitdate>1902-1903</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Constitution &amp; By-Laws, <unitdate>1940</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Lease Agreements with National Academy of Design, <unitdate>1950-1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>New York Water Color Club Merger Documents, <unitdate>1929-1942</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>"Comments on Water Color Club Merger", by J. Scott Williams, <unitdate>1952</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>Voting Ballots for New York Water Color Club Merger, <unitdate>1940</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>President's Reports to A. W. S. Members, <unitdate>circa 1950-1963</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle>Administrative Notebook (disbound), <unitdate>1950s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle>Gifts and Bequests Committee, <unitdate>1954-1956</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">12</container>
<unittitle>Regional Committees, <unitdate>1954-1956</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">13-14</container>
<unittitle>Publicity Correspondence, <unitdate>1955-1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">15</container>
<unittitle>General Administrative Correspondence, <unitdate>1937-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">16</container>
<unittitle>Press Releases, <unitdate>1955-1959</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">17</container>
<unittitle>Annual Meeting and Dinner, <unitdate>1954-1956</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">18</container>
<unittitle>Fine Arts Federation of New York, <unitdate>1962-1963</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">19</container>
<unittitle>Artists for Victory, Inc., <unitdate>1943</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">20</container>
<unittitle>Lists of Awards given by American Watercolor Society, <unitdate>1952-1960, 1966</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">21</container>
<unittitle>Corporate Resolutions, <unitdate>circa 1955-1963</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">22</container>
<unittitle>Ballots (blank), <unitdate>1954, 1963-1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Financial Files<unitdate></unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">23</container>
<unittitle>Record &amp; Account Book, <unitdate>1891-1898</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">24</container>
<unittitle>General Ledger, <unitdate>1960-1964</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">25</container>
<unittitle>General Ledger (disbound), <unitdate>1966-1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">26</container>
<unittitle>General Ledger (disbound), <unitdate>1967-1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">27-28</container>
<unittitle>Treasurer's Reports,  <unitdate>1957-1966</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">29</container>
<unittitle>Annual Financial Statements, <unitdate>1960-1966</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">30</container>
<unittitle>Various Financial Reports, <unitdate>1957-1966</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">31-32</container>
<unittitle>Tax Information, <unitdate>1958-1966</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">33-34</container>
<unittitle>Paid Bills, <unitdate>1961-1963, 1966</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">35-36</container>
<unittitle>Records of Payments, <unitdate>1957-1960</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Bank Deposit Lists, <unitdate>1956-1960</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1943, 1954-1966</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Notes, <unitdate>circa 1959-1960</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
</c02>


</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 2: </unitid><unittitle>Membership, <unitdate>1941, 1951-1960s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 2; 0.7 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Included in this series is a membership roster notebook (disbound) for the period of 1953 to 1961 which includes a notebook page for each artist, arranged alphabetically.  The information on each artist includes name, address, years that they paid membership dues, and the amount paid.  The notebook is arranged with active members listed first, followed by categories for artist's whose status had changed, including life members (who no longer had to pay dues), deceased members, dropped members, and resigned members.  Also found is a separate list of former members as of 1951 also listing the years that they were active, and lists of membership issues that had to be addressed by the board, such as new members and inactive or dropped members.  This series also contains many member biographies; questionnaires that members filled out for the American Watercolor Society Information Center.  Information on these forms includes name, address, family background, education, memberships, awards, etc.  Some artists also attached additional biographical materials such as news clippings and resumes.  Also found in this series are signed membership agreements after the merger with the New York Water Color Club in 1941, and correspondence regarding membership questions and status, payment of dues, and membership resignations.
</p> 
</scopecontent>

<arrangement> 
<p>Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.</p> 
</arrangement>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Membership Roster (disbound)<unitdate></unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">4-7</container>
<unittitle>Active Members, A-Z, <unitdate>1953-1961</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(4 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>Life Members, <unitdate>1953-1961</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>Deceased Members, <unitdate>1953-1961</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle>Dropped Members, <unitdate>1953-1961</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle>Resigned Members, <unitdate>1953-1961</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">12</container>
<unittitle>Lists of Former Members, <unitdate>1951</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">13</container>
<unittitle>Membership Lists for Board Action, <unitdate>1960s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">14-20</container>
<unittitle>Membership Biographies, A-Z, <unitdate>1950s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(7 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">21</container>
<unittitle>Signed Membership Agreements, <unitdate>1941</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">22</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence Regarding Membership and Dues, <unitdate>1954-1963</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 3: </unitid><unittitle>Exhibition Files, <unitdate>1867-1910, 1955-1975</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 2-3, BV02; 1.2 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series consists of files relating to exhibitions organized by the American Watercolor Society. Included is a large bound volume containing the record of works shown in the annual exhibitions from 1897 to 1904.  This record lists the registry and catalog number, title of work, name and address of the artist, the owner and price, agent, and shipping company.  A few loose letters, notes, and lists were also found within the pages of this book and have been placed in a separate folder.  Exhibition catalogs found here are for the society's annual exhibitions prior to 1910, including the catalog for the first exhibition, held in 1867-1868 as a joint exhibition with the National Academy of Design.  A few catalogs from this run are missing, and found here are catalogs from 1867-1869, 1875, 1878-1881, 1883-1897, 1899-1902, 1904, and 1907-1910. </p>  <p> Other files in this series are for various exhibitions held between 1955 and 1975, but do not document every exhibition held during this period.  Files are for both annual exhibitions and exchange exhibitions held with the Canadian Water Color Society, the Art Institute of Mexico, and others.  Files may contain correspondence about the exhibition, exhibition checklists, price lists, lists of award recipients and donors, receipts, exhibition announcements, clippings, and other printed material.  Traveling exhibitions are also covered here.  This series also contains exchange exhibition ballots (probably for the Australian exchange exhibition), jury selection records,   and miscellaneous items from other exhibitions. </p> 
</scopecontent>

<arrangement> 
<p>Items are arranged chronologically.</p> 
</arrangement>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">23</container>
<unittitle>Record of Works Shown in Annual Exhibitions (bound volume), <unitdate>1897-1904</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(See BV02)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">24</container>
<unittitle>Loose Items from Record of Works Shown in Annual Exhibitions, <unitdate>1897-1904</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">25-28</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Catalogs, Annual Exhibition, <unitdate>1867-1889</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(5 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">1-6</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Catalogs, Annual Exhibition, <unitdate>1890-1910</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(6 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>88th Annual Exhibition, <unitdate>1955</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>91st Annual Exhibition, <unitdate>1958</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>Royal Society Painters in Water-Colours and American Watercolor Society Exchange Exhibition, <unitdate>1961-1962</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle>92nd &amp; 93rd Annual Exhibitions, <unitdate>1958-1961</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle>94th Annual Exhibition, <unitdate>1961-1962</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">12</container>
<unittitle>95th Annual Exhibition, <unitdate>1962-1963</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">13</container>
<unittitle>96th Annual Exhibition, <unitdate>1963</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">14</container>
<unittitle>97th Annual Exhibition, <unitdate>1963-1964</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">15</container>
<unittitle>100th Annual Exhibition, "200 Years of Watercolor Painting in America", <unitdate>1964-1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">16-17</container>
<unittitle>Art Institute of Mexico and American Watercolor Society Exchange Exhibitions, <unitdate>1968-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">18</container>
<unittitle>Canadian and American Water Colors Societies Exhibition, <unitdate>1971-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">19</container>
<unittitle>Australian Exchange Exhibition, <unitdate>1974-1975</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">20</container>
<unittitle>Exchange Exhibition Ballots, <unitdate>1974</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">21</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Jury Selection, <unitdate>1965-1966</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">22</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Exhibition Documents, <unitdate>1956-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">BV02</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Record of Works Shown in Annual Exhibitions (bound volume), <unitdate>1897-1904</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(See also Box 2, F23)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 4: </unitid><unittitle>Printed Material, <unitdate>1868, 1943-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 3; 6 folders)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Scattered printed material includes a booklet entitled <emph render="italic">Water-Color Painting: Some Facts and Authorities in Relation to Its Durability</emph>, printed by the American Society of Painters in Water-Colors in New York in 1868.  This publication was co-edited by A. F. Bellows, William Hart, C. P. Cranch, John M. Falconer, and Gilbert Burling.  Also found in this series are news clippings about events, exhibitions, and featured members of the society, newsletters distributed to members, and two issues of <emph render="italic">American Artist</emph> which include several articles about watercolor painting.  There are also a few reproductions of artwork from an unidentified publication.  </p> 
</scopecontent>

<arrangement> 
<p>Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.</p> 
</arrangement>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">23</container>
<unittitle>Publication, <emph render="italic">Water-Color Painting</emph>, <unitdate>1868</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">24-25</container>
<unittitle>News Clippings, <unitdate>1943-1962</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">26</container>
<unittitle>Newsletters, <unitdate>1962-1965</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">27</container>
<unittitle><emph render="italic">American Artist</emph> Magazine, <unitdate>1970, 1972</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">28</container>
<unittitle>Reproductions of Artwork, <unitdate>circa 1950s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 5: </unitid><unittitle>Photographs, <unitdate>circa 1940-1977</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 3-4; 0.5 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Photographs are of events, members, exhibitions, and artwork.   Photographs of events include dinners, award presentations, and exhibition openings. None of the photographs of juries or events are labeled.  There are group photographs of jury members and photographs of members, both professional portraits and photographs of artists in their studio, arranged alphabetically by artist's last name.  Of note are photographs of Don Stone, Charles Hawes, and Tom Nicholas giving painting demonstrations at the annual exhibition in 1966.  This series also contains numerous photographs of watercolors exhibited in shows; almost all are labeled with the artist's name and any awards that were received for the painting on the back of the photograph.  Photographs of watercolors are arranged alphabetically by the artist's last name.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<arrangement> 
<p></p> 
</arrangement>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">29-30</container>
<unittitle>Photographs of Members, A-Z, <unitdate>circa 1940-1960</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4 (hol)</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Photographs of Juries, <unitdate>1950s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4 (hol)</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Photographs of Painting Demonstrations, <unitdate>1966</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4 (hol)</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Photographs of Events, <unitdate>circa 1950s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4 (hol)</container>
<container type="folder">4-9</container>
<unittitle>Photographs of Watercolors, <unitdate>circa 1955-1977</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(6 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4 (hol)</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle>Negatives of Photographs of Events, <unitdate>circa 1950s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4 (hol)</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle>Slides of Unidentified Exhibition, <unitdate>circa 1960</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

</c01>

</dsc>

<!-- END DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->

<!-- OPTIONAL DSC ELEMENTS -->

<!-- END OPTIONAL DSC ELEMENTS -->


</archdesc>
</ead>




