<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "/eadcb/shared/ead/ead.dtd">

<ead audience="external" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
<eadid mainagencycode="DSI-AAA" countrycode="us" url="http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/findingaids/xml/bearroma.xml">bearroma</eadid>

<filedesc>
	<titlestmt>
		<titleproper>Romare Bearden</titleproper>
		<subtitle>A Finding Aid to the Romare Bearden Papers, <date type="inclusive">1937-1982</date>, in the Archives of American Art</subtitle>
		<author>by Barbara Aikens</author>
<sponsor>Funding for the digitization of this collection was provided by the Terra Foundation for American Art</sponsor>
	</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
	<publisher>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</publisher>
	<date type="publication">November 20, 2003</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Barbara Aikens on
<date>November 20, 2003</date>
</creation>
<langusage><language>English</language></langusage>
</profiledesc>
<revisiondesc>
<change>
<date>January 2006</date>
<item>Finding aid updated from EAD v. 1.0 to v. 2002 by Stephanie Ashley</item>
</change>
</revisiondesc>
</eadheader>

<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory">
<did>
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
		<corpname>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</corpname>
	</repository>

	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100">Bearden, Romare</persname>
	</origination>

	<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Romare Bearden papers</unittitle>

	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f">1937-1982</unitdate>

	<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a">2 linear feet</physdesc>

	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">The papers of Romare Bearden measure two linear feet and date from 1937 to 1982.  The collection includes biographical information, correspondence, writings by and about Bearden, miscellaneous legal and financial material, photographs, drawings, and printed material.  Found are numerous letters referring to African-American arts movements of the 1960s and 1970s,  including exhibitions, publications, associations, and scattered letters of a more personal nature.</abstract>

</did>



<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GO HERE: -->


<bioghist altrender="biography" encodinganalog="545" id="a2">
<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>Born in Mecklenburg County, North Carolina, in 1914, Bearden's family relocated to  New York City when Bearden was a toddler.  Living in Harlem during the Harlem Renaissance of the 1920s, Bearden was exposed to such luminaries as writer Langston Hughes, painter Aaron Douglas, and musician Duke Ellington. While attending New York University, Bearden became interested in cartooning and became the art editor of the NYU Medley in his senior year.  He received his B.S. in mathematics in 1935, initially planning to pursue medical school.  Realizing that he had little interest in the other sciences however, Bearden began attending classes at the Art Students League in the evenings, studying under George Grosz. </p> 
<p>In the mid-1930s Bearden published numerous political cartoons in journals and newspapers, including the <emph render="italic">Afro-American</emph>, but by the end of the decade, he shifted his emphasis to painting. Bearden's first paintings, on large sheets of brown paper, recalled his early memories of the South.  After serving in the Army, Bearden began exhibiting more frequently, particularly in Washington, D.C. at the G Street Gallery and in New York with Samuel Kootz.</p>
<p>During a career lasting almost half a century, Bearden produced approximately two thousand works.  Although best known for the collages of urban and southern scenes that he first experimented with in the mid-1960s, Bearden also completed paintings, drawings, monotypes, edition prints, public murals, record album jackets, magazine and book illustrations, and costume and set designs for theater and ballet.   His work focused on religious subjects, African-American culture, jazz clubs and brothels, and history and literature. Not confining his abilities to the visual arts, Bearden also devoted attention to writing and song writing.  Several of his collaborations were published as sheet music, among the most famous of which is "Seabreeze," recorded by Billy Eckstine.  In addition, Bearden  coauthored three full-length books: <emph render="italic">The Painter's Mind: A Study of the Relations of Structure and Space in Painting</emph> (1969) with painter Carl Holty; <emph render="italic">Six Black Masters of American Art </emph>(1972); and <emph render="italic">A History of African-American Artists: From 1792 to the Present </emph>(posthumously, 1993), the latter two with journalist Harry Henderson. </p>
<p>Bearden was also active in the African-American arts movement of the period, serving as art director of the Harlem Cultural Council, a founding member of the Black Academy of Arts and Letters, and organizer of exhibitions, such as the Metropolitan Museum's "Harlem on My Mind" (1968).  Romare Bearden died in 1988.</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520" id="a3">
<head>Scope and Content Note</head>
<p>The papers of Romare Bearden measure two linear feet and date from 1937 to 1982.  The collection includes biographical information, correspondence, writings by and about Bearden, miscellaneous legal and financial material, photographs, drawings, and printed material.</p>

<p>Correspondence is with family, friends, artists, galleries, museums, publishers, universities, arts associations, and colleagues, primarily concerning gallery space, exhibitions, sales of artwork, publishing, and arts events. Also found are numerous letters referring to African-American art movements of the 1960s and 1970s, including exhibitions, publications, associations, and scattered letters of a more personal nature.   Many of the letters are illustrated with Bearden's doodlings and drawings.  Although most of the letters are from galleries, museums, publishers, and arts associations, scattered letters from Charles Alston, Jacob Lawrence, Ad Reinhardt, Carl Holty, and Sam Middleton are found.  In addition, there are letters from the Black Academy of Arts and Letters, and letters concerning its founding.</p>

<p>Writings by Bearden include lectures, speeches, talks, essays, and prose. Many are handwritten, annotated, and edited in Bearden's hand and several are illustrated with Bearden's doodlings and sketches.  Included are a memorial delivered upon artist Carl Holty's death, a tribute to Zell Ingram, autobiographical essays, essays on art, and African-American art, artists, and cultural life.  Also found are several handwritten examples of Bearden's prose and poetry.   There are also writings by others and one folder of fragments and notes assumed to be by Bearden.</p>

<p>The collection houses two folders of photographs and snapshots of Bearden, family members, other unidentified artists or friends, classes and/or lectures, and works of art. Also found are several undated ink drawings, sketches in pencil and ink, and a hand-drawn and colored map with overlay of Paris. Printed material includes examples of Bearden's commissioned artwork for publications, press releases, exhibition catalogs and announcements, invitations, newspaper and magazine clippings, and miscellaneous printed materials. Although much of the printed material concerns Bearden's work, a fair portion concerns African-American art, artists, and cultural movements.</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351$b" id="a5">
<head>Arrangement</head>
<p>The collection is arranged into seven series based on type of materials. Documents within each of the seven series have been arranged in chronological order, except for the writings which have been further subdivided by creator and are undated.  Printed materials have been arranged primarily according to form of material and are in rough chronological order.</p>
<list>
<item>Series 1: Biographical, 1977, undated (Box 1; 1 folder)</item>
 
 <item>Series 2: Correspondence, 1944-1981, undated (Box 1-2; 0.8 linear feet)</item>
 
 <item>Series 3: Writings By and About Bearden, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 3; 6 folders)</item>
 
 <item>Series 4:  Legal and Financial Material, 1970-1977 (Box 3; 3 folders)</item>
 
 <item>Series 5:  Photographs, undated (Box 3; 2 folders)</item>
 
 <item>Series 6:  Drawings, undated (Box 3, OV 6; 4 folders)</item>
 
 <item>Series 7:  Printed Material, 1937-1982 (Box 3-5; 1 linear foot)</item>
</list>
</arrangement>


<!-- END TOP LEVEL METADATA -->

<!-- CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS GO HERE: -->

<controlaccess id="a12">
<head>Index Terms</head>
<p>This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.</p>


<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects-Topical:</head>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">African American painters -- New York (State) --   New York</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">African American Artists</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Painting</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Painters -- New York (State) -- New York</subject>
</controlaccess>


<controlaccess>
<head>Types of Materials:</head>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Photographs</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Drawings</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Exhibition catalogs</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Works of art</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Maps -- Paris (France)</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Sketches</genreform>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Names:</head>

<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Alston, Charles Henry, 1907-1977</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Reinhardt, Ad, 1913-1967</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Holty, Carl, 1900-1973</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Lawrence, Jacob, 1917-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Middleton, Samuel M., 1927-</persname>
</controlaccess>

</controlaccess>


<!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->

<!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION GOES HERE: -->

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541" id="a19">
<head>Provenance</head>
<p>Romare Bearden donated his papers in several increments between 1977 and 1983.  In 1968, Bearden also loaned letters, a scrapbook, photographs, printed materials, and writings that were microfilmed and returned to Bearden.  He later donated some of this same material to AAA.</p>
</acqinfo>

<separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 0" id="a7">
<head>Separated Material</head>
<p>In 1968 Romare Bearden loaned a scrapbook, photographs, catalogs, clippings, and writings for microfilming on reels N/68-87.  These materials are not described in this finding aid.</p>
</separatedmaterial>

<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 1" id="a6">
<head>Related Material</head>
<p>Within the Archives holdings are two oral history interviews with Romare Bearden.  One was conducted in 1968 by Henri Ghent and another in 1980 by Avis Berman.  Both have been transcribed and the 1968 interview transcript is available on the Archives website and on microfilm.</p>
</relatedmaterial>

<accessrestrict id="a14" encodinganalog="506">
<head>Restrictions on Access</head>
<p>The bulk of the collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website. Use of material not digitized requires an appointment.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="a15">
<head>Ownership and Literary Rights</head>
<p>The Romare Bearden papers are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
</userestrict>

<altformavail id="a17" encodinganalog="530">
<head>Alternative Forms Available</head>
<p>The bulk of the collection was digitized in 2005 and is available online via AAA's website. </p>
</altformavail>

<prefercite encodinganalog="510" id="a18">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Romare Bearden papers, 1937-1982.  Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
</prefercite>

<processinfo encodinganalog="583" id="a20">
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>All accessions were merged and fully processed, arranged, and described in 2003 by Barbara Aikens.  A portion of an earlier loan that was microfilmed on reel N/68-87 was merged and processed with the later accessions. </p>
</processinfo>


<!-- END ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->


<!-- START DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->


<dsc type="combined" id="a23">
<head>Series Descriptions/Container Listing</head>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 1: </unitid><unittitle>Biographical, <unitdate>1977, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 1 folder)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>One folder of miscellaneous biographical information that includes awards, certificates, family history, resumes, and other miscellaneous documents.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Biographical Information, <unitdate>1977, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 2: </unitid><unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1944-1981</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Boxes 1-2; 0.8 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Letters to and from Bearden with family, friends, artists, galleries, museums, publishers, universities, arts associations, and colleagues primarily concerning gallery space, exhibitions, sales of artwork, publishing, and arts events. Also found are numerous letters referring to African-American art movements of the 1960s and 1970s, including exhibitions, publications, and associations, and scattered letters of a more personal nature. Many of the letters are illustrated with Bearden's doodlings and drawings.  

Although most of the letters are from galleries, museums, publishers, and arts associations, scattered letters from Charles Alston, Ad Reinhardt, Carl Holty, and Sam Middleton are found, as well as a 1946 letter from Samuel Kootz Gallery agreeing to be the sole representative of Bearden for a two year period.   There are a few letters from Jacob Lawrence, including a 1971 letter stating that Bearden's exhibition brings "back memories of 33 West 125th Street....which as is so offtimes true - turn out to be times we treasure greatly".  Lawrence is referring to a studio building on West 125th where Bearden also had a studio in the late 1930s and early 1940s. In addition, there are letters from the Black Academy of Arts and Letters, and letters concerning its founding.  There is also a 1970 Guggenheim award letter for a fellowship to develop and write "A History of Afro-American Artists". 
</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">3-21</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1944-September, 1972 </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(19 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">1-18</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>October, 1972-1981 </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(18 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 3: </unitid><unittitle>Writings By and About Bearden, <unitdate>circa 1950s-1980s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 3; 6 folders)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series houses writings, primarily in draft or manuscript version, by Bearden, such as lectures, speeches, talks, essays, and prose. Many are handwritten, annotated, and edited in Bearden's hand and several are illustrated with Bearden's doodlings and sketches.  Included are a memorial delivered upon artist Carl Holty's death, a tribute to Zell Ingram, autobiographical essays, essays on art, and African-American art, artists, and cultural life.  Also found are several handwritten examples of Bearden's prose and poetry.   One folder of writings by others includes an interview transcript edited by Bearden, a student paper, numerous essays about Bearden and his work, and one proposal for a film based on Bearden's life.  One folder of fragments and notes assumed to be by Bearden is also found and one folder of unidentified writings.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">1-2</container>
<unittitle>Writings By Bearden,<unitdate>circa 1950s-1980s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Writings By Bearden, Prose and Poetry, <unitdate>circa 1950s-1980s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Notes, <unitdate>circa 1950s-1980s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Writings About Bearden By Others, <unitdate>circa 1950s-1980s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>Unidentified Writings, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 4: </unitid><unittitle>Legal and Financial Material, <unitdate>1970-1977</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 3; 3 folders)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Scattered legal and financial material, including a 1977 agreement with Warner Brothers Records, Inc. for artwork for a Charlie Parker album cover.  Also found are miscellaneous financial receipts, invoices, and statements for sales and purchases of artwork, as well as loan and exhibition documentation. Scattered household receipts are also arranged in this series.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>Legal Agreements,<unitdate>1975, 1977</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Financial, Art-Related, <unitdate>1970-1977</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Financial, Non Art-Related, <unitdate>1974-1975</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 5: </unitid><unittitle>Photographs, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 3; 2 folders)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Two folders containing scattered photographs and snapshots of Bearden, family members, other unidentified artists or friends, classes and/or lectures, and works of art.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle>Photographs of Bearden, Family, Other Artists, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle>Photographs of Works of Art, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 6: </unitid><unittitle>Drawings,<unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 3, 6; 4 folders)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Undated ink drawings, sketches in pencil and ink, and a hand-drawn and colored map with overlay of Paris. </p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">12</container>
<unittitle>Ink Drawings, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">13</container>
<unittitle>Pencil and Ink Sketches, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(See also Box 6)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">14</container>
<unittitle>Hand-drawn Map of Paris with Overlay,<unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Oversized Sketch,<unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(See Box 3, F13)</physdesc>
</did></c02>



</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 7: </unitid><unittitle>Printed Material, <unitdate>1937-1982</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 3-5; 1 linear foot)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Printed material includes printed examples of Bearden's commissioned artwork for publications, press releases, exhibition catalogs and announcements, invitations, newspaper and magazine clippings, and miscellaneous printed materials, such as magazines and bulletins.  Also found is one folder of printed material concerning the 1973 Annual Conference of Artists and another folder housing materials concerning other artists.  Although much of the printed material concerns Bearden's work, a fair portion concerns African-American art,  artists, and cultural movements. </p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">15</container>
<unittitle>Examples of Artwork for Publications, <unitdate>circa 1970s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">16</container>
<unittitle>Press Releases, <unitdate>1971-1979, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">17</container>
<unittitle>Catalogs, <unitdate>1948-1971</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">1-4</container>
<unittitle>Catalogs (mostly Bearden), <unitdate>1972-1982</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(4 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Announcements, <unitdate>1964-1982, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>Invitations,<unitdate>1972-1975, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">7-8</container>
<unittitle>Newspaper Clippings, <unitdate>1937-1969</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders; partially scanned)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<container type="folder">1-6</container>
<unittitle>Newspaper Clippings,<unitdate>1970-1982, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(6 folders; partially scanned)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>Magazine Clippings, <unitdate>1933-1980, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Partially scanned)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>Magazines,<unitdate>1967-1969</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Not scanned)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<container type="folder">9-12</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Printed Material, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(4 folders; partially scanned)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<container type="folder">13</container>
<unittitle>National Conference of Artists, <unitdate>1972-1973</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<container type="folder">14</container>
<unittitle>Information on Other Artists, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Partially scanned)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>


</dsc>


<!-- END DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->
</archdesc>
</ead>





