<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "/eadcb/shared/ead/ead.dtd">

<ead audience="external" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
<eadid mainagencycode="DSI-AAA" countrycode="us" url="http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/findingaids/xml/borgcarl.xml">borgcarl</eadid>

<filedesc>
	<titlestmt>
		<titleproper>Carl Oscar Borg</titleproper>
		<subtitle>A Finding Aid to the Carl Oscar Borg Scrapbooks, <date type="inclusive">1903-1955</date>, in the Archives of American Art</subtitle>
		<author>by Rosa M. Fern&#x00E1;ndez</author>
	</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
	<publisher>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</publisher>
	<date type="publication">June 25, 2000</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Stephanie Ashley,
<date>August, 2002</date>
</creation>
<langusage><language>English</language></langusage>
</profiledesc>
<revisiondesc>
<change>
<date>October 2005</date>
<item>Finding aid updated from EAD v. 1.0 to v. 2002 by Stephanie Ashley
</item>
</change>
</revisiondesc>
</eadheader>

<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory">
<did>
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
		<corpname>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</corpname>
	</repository>

	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100">Carl Oscar Borg</persname>
	</origination>

	<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Carl Oscar Borg scrapbooks</unittitle>

	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f">1903-1955</unitdate>

	<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a">0.3 linear feet</physdesc>

	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">This collection consists of three scrapbooks dating from 1903 to 1955 containing mostly newspaper clippings  which document the career of California  artist Carl Oscar Borg, particularly his work as art director for Hollywood films.</abstract>

	<langmaterial>The records are in <language>English</language>.
	</langmaterial>
</did>



<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GO HERE: -->


<bioghist altrender="biography" encodinganalog="545" id="a2">
<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>Self taught Swedish-American artist Carl Oscar Borg (1879-1947)  began his career as a sign painter in New York. He emigrated to the United States from Stockholm, Sweden in 1901, settling in Los Angeles in 1903 where he became active in the emerging Los Angeles art community. He became the protog&#x00E9; of  Phoebe Apperson Hearst (mother of William Randolph Hearst) whose support and endorsement enabled him to study in Europe. He established himself as a serious artist after World War II working in the fields of print, film and painting, enabling him to secure a place among the Los Angeles artistic elite. Borg specialized in painting the Southwestern Hopi and Navajo Indians.  He also painted mariners and the seal hunting scenes which took place in Channel Island near Santa Barbara. He was a member of the National Academy of Design, the National Academy of Arts, the Soci&#x00E9;te Internationale des Beaux Arts (Paris) and the prestigious Salmagundi Club. He traveled to Sweden in 1939, remaining there until the end of World War II. Upon his return to California, he settled in Santa Barbara where he remained until his death in 1947.</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520" id="a3">
<head>Scope and Content Note</head>
<p>The collection consists of three scrapbooks compiled by Borg, and after his death by his widow, Lily Borg Elmberg. These contain newspaper clippings from the U.S. and Sweden, documenting Borg's lifelong career as a painter and printmaker since his arrival in Los Angeles in 1903. One scrapbook, 1925-1938, highlights  his role as supervising art director for the1926 silent film, The Black Pirate starring actor Douglas Fairbanks. Also included are articles about his years working in the silent movie industry (1925-1928) as the art director of films, Black Pirate, The Gaucho, The Night of Love, The Magic Flame, Two Lovers, and The Iron Mask.</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351$b" id="a5">
<head>Arrangement</head>
<p>Volumes are divided into three main categories: I. Los Angeles Years (1903-1935), II. Silent movies and trip to Sweden (1925-1938), and III. Sweden and Santa Barbara years (1935-1955). The dates of a number of the newspaper clippings and exhibition catalogs found in the scrapbooks  overlap. In addition, Scrapbook I, 1903-1935, is in fragile condition and should be handled with care.</p>
</arrangement>


<!-- END TOP LEVEL METADATA -->

<!-- CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS GO HERE: -->

<controlaccess id="a12">
<head>Index Terms</head>
<p>This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Names" when they are creators or contributors and under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents.</p>

<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects-Topical:</head> 
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Motion picture industry</subject> 
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Motion picture art directors -- California</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Painters -- California -- Los Angeles</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Painters -- California -- Santa Barbara</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Silent films</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Artists -- Sweden</subject>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>

<!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->

<!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION GOES HERE: -->

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541" id="a19">
<head>Provenance</head>
<p>The collection was donated in 1998 by Helen Laird, who received the papers from Borg's widow, Lily Borg Elmberg in preparation for a biography on Carl Oscar Borg.</p>
</acqinfo>

<accessrestrict id="a14" encodinganalog="506">
<head>Restrictions on Access</head>
<p>The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="a15">
<head>Ownership and Literary Rights</head>
<p>The Carl Oscar Borg scrapbooks are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
</userestrict>

<altformavail id="a17" encodinganalog="530">
<head>Alternative Forms Available</head>
<p>The collection is available on microfilm reel number 5671. The microfilm is available for interlibrary loan.</p>
</altformavail>

<prefercite encodinganalog="510" id="a18">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Carl Oscar Borg scrapbooks, 1903-1955. Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
</prefercite>

<processinfo encodinganalog="583" id="a20">
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>Processing of the collection was completed June 26, 2000 by Rosa M. Fern&#x00E1;ndez at the Archives of American Art, Washington, DC.</p>
</processinfo>


<!-- END ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->


<!-- START DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->


<dsc type="combined" id="a23">
<head>Series Descriptions/Container Listing</head>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 1: </unitid><unittitle>Scrapbooks, <unitdate>1903-1955</unitdate></unittitle><physdesc>(box 1, 0.3 linear ft.)</physdesc></did>
<c02><did><container type="box">1 (sol)</container>
<container type="reel">5671</container>
<unittitle>Scrapbook I:  The Los Angeles Years, <unitdate>1903-1935</unitdate></unittitle></did>    
</c02>
<c02><did><container type="box">1 (sol)</container>
<container type="reel">5671</container>
<unittitle>Scrapbook II: Silent Movies and Trip to Sweden, <unitdate>1925-1938</unitdate></unittitle></did>    
</c02>
<c02><did><container type="box">1 (sol)</container>
<container type="reel">5671</container>
<unittitle>Scrapbook III: Sweden and Santa Barbara Years, <unitdate>1935-1955</unitdate></unittitle></did>    
</c02></c01>


</dsc>


<!-- END DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->
</archdesc>
</ead>

