<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
    <eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" findaidstatus="Completed" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-DSI-AAA">chaswill.xml</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Finding Aid to the William Merritt Chase Papers, circa 1890-1964, in the Archives of American Art
                    <num>AAA.chaswill</num>
                </titleproper>
                <titleproper type="filing">Chase (William Merritt) papers</titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by Stephanie L. Ashley</author>
                <sponsor>Funding for the processing and digitization of this collection was provided by the Terra Foundation for American Art</sponsor>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Archives of American Art</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>750 9th Street, NW</addressline>
                    <addressline>Victor Building, Suite 2200</addressline>
                    <addressline>Washington, D.C., 20001</addressline>
                    <addressline>Phone: 202-633-7950</addressline>
                    <addressline>http://www.aaa.si.edu/askus</addressline>
                </address>
                <date>2014 May 3</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <notestmt>
                <note>
                    <p>This finding aid is associated with a MARC collection-level record.
                        <num type="siris_arc">209545</num></p>
                </note>
            </notestmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2015-03-12T09:31-0400</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>English</langusage>
            <descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>William Merritt Chase papers</unittitle>
            <unitid>AAA.chaswill</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>Archives of American Art</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>0.3 Linear feet</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1885/1964" type="inclusive">circa 1890-1964</unitdate>
            <langmaterial id="ref5" label="Language of Materials note">Collection is in English.</langmaterial>
            <abstract id="ref37" label="Abstract">The papers of New York painter and art instructor, William Merritt Chase, measure 0.3 linear feet and date from circa 1890 to 1964. Papers include a resolution of the Art Club of Philadelphia on Chase's death, letters, writings by Chase consisting of typescripts of lectures and lecture notes, blank postcards primarily depicting reproductions of artwork, a scrapbook, and photographs of Chase, his family, homes, and studios, and photographs of works of art.</abstract>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Chase, William Merritt, 1849-1916</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <arrangement id="ref1">
            <head>Arrangement note</head>
            <p>Due to the small size of the collection, the papers are arranged as 1 series.</p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>Series 1: William Merritt Chase Papers, circa 1890-1964 (0.3 linear feet.; Box 1, OV 2)</item>
            </list>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict id="ref2">
            <head>Conditions Governing Access note</head>
            <p>Use of original papers requires an appointment.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict id="ref3">
            <head>Conditions Governing Use note</head>
            <p>The William Merritt Chase papers are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
        </userestrict>
        <altformavail id="ref4">
            <head>Existence and Location of Copies note</head>
            <p>The collection was digitized in 2014 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="ref17">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>The papers of New York painter and art instructor, William Merritt Chase, measure 0.3 linear feet and date from circa 1890 to 1964. Papers include a resolution of the Art Club of Philadelphia on Chase's death, letters, writings by Chase consisting of typescripts of lectures and lecture notes, blank postcards primarily depicting reproductions of artwork, a scrapbook, and photographs of Chase, his family, homes, and studios, and photographs of works of art.</p>
            <p>Letters include a photocopy of a 1901 letter signed by 28 students of the Shinnecock Summer School thanking Chase for a painting; a 1903 postcard to Mr. Harold R. Shiffer from his aunt; a 1912 letter to Chase signed by 32 pupils of the Art Students League thanking him for his efforts on their behalf and acknowledging his "qualities of sympathy, interest, and an understanding of our individual needs;" a 1915 note from an unidentified writer; a 1920 letter to Chase's wife Alice, from Gertrude Abbey, wife of Edwin Austin Abbey, referencing a tile possibly created by Edwin Abbey that Mrs. Chase owns; a 1935 postcard to Chase's daughter Helen from an unidentified writer; and a 1964 letter to Helen Storm from Ala Story in which Story describes a Chase exhibition that he is organizing and apologizes for having given a sketchbook of drawings owned by Helen to the Morgan Library.</p>
            <p>Writings include 4 sets of lecture notes (one labeled as being notes for a lecture at Shinnecock), which are a combination of annotated typescripts and handwritten pages, and a typescript of a 1906 "Talk on the Old Masters by Mr. Chase" for the New York School of Art. Also found is a notebook with handwritten notes on a talk Chase gave to students in Philadelphia, presumably at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts.</p>
            <p>Writings by others consist of a six-page typescript entitled "Reminiscences of a Student," by F. Usher De Voll, describing his experiences of Chase as a teacher.</p>
            <p>Postcards (blank) include 3 reproductions of works of art by Chase, 8 reproductions of works of art by other artists, and 2 scenic views.</p>
            <p>A Chase family scrapbook consists of mounted prints, primarily cyanotypes, that document Chase's travels to Rome, Milan, Gibraltar and the Loire Valley, and visits to major monuments, and also includes images of Chase and his family at leisure during their travels, as well as five family portraits.</p>
            <p>Photographs of the Chase family include one of Chase with his son, Dana, and one of Chase with his wife, Alice, both undated. Other family members and friends are generally unidentified but do include Virginia Gerson and possibly Alice Gerson. Also found are four portraits of Chase, four photographs of Chase in his studio, a copy print of students at the Shinnecock Art School in circa 1895, and a copy print of an 1880 Tile Club trip up the Hudson River. In addition to circa 1960 copy prints, photographs include a variety of vintage prints such as albumen cabinet cards, silver gelatin prints, and a tintype.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <bioghist id="ref12">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>William Merritt Chase (1849-1916) was one of America's most prominent painters and art instructors in New York, New York and Shinnecock, Long Island, during the late 19th century. One of the first Impressionist landscape painters in the U. S, Chase was also a highly accomplished portrait and still life painter.</p>
            <p>Born in Indiana, Chase lived in New York and St. Louis, Missouri, before traveling to Europe and studying at the Royal Academy in Munich. After returning to New York in 1878, he taught at the Art Students League until 1896. His studio in the Tenth Street Studio building became an important gathering place for artists, students and patrons. Chase was also a member of the Tile Club whose members shared an interest in the decorative arts and sought to have their designs translated into ceramic tiles, from 1877-1887.</p>
            <p>Chase became one of the most important teachers of American artists around the turn of the century. He opened the Shinnecock Hills Summer Art School in 1891 and taught there until 1902, living in a house at Shinnecock designed by Stanford White. In 1896 he opened the Chase School of Art and also taught at the Brooklyn Art Association in 1887, and 1891-1896, and the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts from 1896-1909.</p>
            <p>Chase was a member of the National Academy of Design, and was president of the Society of American Artists from 1885 to 1895.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <separatedmaterial id="ref7">
            <head>Separated Materials note</head>
            <p>Also in the Archives are materials loaned for microfilming by Robert S. Chase and Chapellier Galleries in 1969, including an additional family scrapbook, undated, (reel N69-115) containing photographs of Chase, his wife and children, a notice of sale of the Chase house in Shinnecock Hills, N.Y. designed by Standord White, and photographs of the house. On reel N69-119 are circa 200 photographs of Chase at work, his wife, his studios in Philadelphia and on 5th Avenue and 10th Street New York City, and numerous snapshots of characters in a tableau vivent that include his family, friends, Mary S. Moore Cross, and others. Reel N69-137 contains letters from Chase to his wife during his travels abroad, one letter received from John Singer Sargent requesting the use of Chase's studio for the famous party Sargent gave for Isabella Stewart Gardner in 1890, and a six-page typescript, "Reminiscences of a Student. by F. Usher De Voll, and photographs of Chase's studio.</p>
            <p>Loaned material is available on N69-115, N69-119, and N69-137, but is not described in the Container Listing of this finding aid.</p>
        </separatedmaterial>
        <prefercite id="ref9">
            <head>Preferred Citation note</head>
            <p>William Merritt Chase papers, circa 1890-1964. Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <processinfo id="ref10">
            <head>Processing Information note</head>
            <p>The William Merritt Chase papers were donated in a series of accessions between 1969 and 2010, and some of the material was microfilmed at some point after receipt . All previously filmed and unfilmed accessions were merged, fully processed, arranged and described by Stephanie L. Ashley in 2014, and the collection was digitized in 2014, with funding provided by the Terra Foundation for American Art.</p>
        </processinfo>
        <acqinfo id="ref11">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>The papers were received in a series of accessions between 1969 and 2010: the lectures and speeches, a 1912 letter, and photocopies of a dinner menu and photos of artwork were donated by Roger Storm, widower of Chase's daughter Helen, in 1969; photographic copy prints of Chase's summer home, studio and art school were donated by Fred D. Bentley in 1986; and 2 letters, 2 postcards, the Chase family scrapbook, vintage photographs and blank postcards were donated in 2010 by D. Frederick Baker, author of the Chase catalogue raisonné. Baker received the material from Chase's estate via Chase's grandson, Jackson Case Storm.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <controlaccess>
            <corpname source="naf">Art Club of Philadelphia.</corpname>
            <corpname source="naf">Art Students League (New York, N.Y.).</corpname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">De Voll, F. Usher, 1873-1941</persname>
            <corpname rules="aacr" source="local">Shinnecock Summer School of Art. (Faculty)</corpname>
            <subject source="lcsh">Art teachers--New York (State)--New York</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Art, American</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Art--Study and teaching</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Artists' studios--New York (State)--New York--Photographs</subject>
            <subject source="aat">Painters--New York (State)--New York</subject>
            <genreform source="lcsh">Photographs</genreform>
            <genreform source="aat">Scrapbooks</genreform>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc>
            <c01 id="ref13" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>William Merritt Chase Papers</unittitle>
                    <unitid>Series 1</unitid>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>0.3 Linear feet</extent>
                        <extent>Box 1, OV 2</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1885/1964" type="inclusive">circa 1890-1964</unitdate>
                </did>
                <arrangement id="ref43">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>Papers are arranged by type and in chronological order (when known) thereafter. Circa 1960 dates indicate the estimated date of photocopies and copy prints.</p>
                </arrangement>
                <altformavail id="ref44">
                    <head>Existence and Location of Copies note</head>
                    <p>Series is scanned in entirety.</p>
                </altformavail>
                <c02 id="ref18" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Art Club of Philadelphia Resolution on Death of Chase</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid4599001" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid4599001" type="Folder">1</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1916/1916">1916</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref19" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Dinner Menu and Guest List (1897) Photocopy</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid4599002" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid4599002" type="Folder">2</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1955/1965" type="inclusive">circa 1960</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref14" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid4599003" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid4599003" type="Folder">3</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce">1901-1964</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref20" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Writings and Notes by Chase</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid4599004" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid4599004" type="Folder">4</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1885/1916" type="inclusive">circa 1890-circa 1911</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref21" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Writings and Notes by Chase</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid4599005" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid4599005" type="Folder">5</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1906/1906">1906</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref22" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Writings and Notes by Chase, Notebook</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid4599006" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid4599006" type="Folder">6</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1891/1914" type="inclusive">circa 1896-circa 1909</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref24" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Writings by Others</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid4599007" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid4599007" type="Folder">7</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1895/1905" type="inclusive">circa 1900</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref25" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Postcards (Blank)</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid4599008" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid4599008" type="Folder">8</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1875/1915" type="inclusive">circa 1890-circa 1910</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref26" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Scrapbook, Chase Family</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid4599009" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                        <container parent="cid4599009" type="Folder">9</container>
                        <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1895/1905" type="inclusive">circa 1900</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref38">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Oversized material housed in OV 2</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref27" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Photographs</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid4599010" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                    </did>
                    <c03 id="ref28" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Chase Family</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid4599011" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                            <container parent="cid4599011" type="Folder">10-11</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce">circa 1890-circa 1910</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref29" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Chase Home, Interior circa 1895</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid4599012" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                            <container parent="cid4599012" type="Folder">12</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1955/1965" type="inclusive">circa 1960</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref30" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Chase Portraits</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid4599013" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                            <container parent="cid4599013" type="Folder">13</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1895/1905" type="inclusive">circa 1900</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref31" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Chase Studio</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid4599014" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                            <container parent="cid4599014" type="Folder">14</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1890/1900" type="inclusive">circa 1895</unitdate>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1955/1965" type="inclusive">circa 1960</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref32" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Chase in Studio circa 1895</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid4599015" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                            <container parent="cid4599015" type="Folder">15</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1955/1965" type="inclusive">circa 1960</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref33" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Students at Shinnecock Art School circa 1895</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid4599016" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                            <container parent="cid4599016" type="Folder">16</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1955/1965" type="inclusive">circa 1960</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref34" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Tile Club Trip up the Hudson River in 1880</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid4599017" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                            <container parent="cid4599017" type="Folder">17</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1955/1965" type="inclusive">circa 1960</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref35" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Works of Art by Chase</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid4599018" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                            <container parent="cid4599018" type="Folder">18</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1955/1965" type="inclusive">circa 1960</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref36" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Works of Art (Photocopies)</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid4599019" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">1</container>
                            <container parent="cid4599019" type="Folder">19</container>
                            <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1955/1965" type="inclusive">circa 1960</unitdate>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref39" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Scrapbook, Chase Family (Oversized material scanned with Box 1, Folder 9)</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid4599020" label="Mixed materials" type="Box">OV 2</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>