<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "/eadcb/shared/ead/ead.dtd">

<ead audience="external" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
<eadid mainagencycode="DSI-AAA" countrycode="us" url="http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/findingaids/xml/cramkonr.xml">cramkonr</eadid>

<filedesc>
	<titlestmt>
		<titleproper>Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer</titleproper>
		<subtitle>A Finding Aid to the Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer Papers, <date type="inclusive">1897-1968</date>, in the Archives of American Art</subtitle>
		<author>by Megan McShea</author>
		<sponsor>Funding for the processing of this collection was provided by the Terra Foundation for American Art</sponsor>
	</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
	<publisher>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</publisher>
	<date type="publication">July 10, 2006</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Megan McShea on
<date>July 10, 2006</date>
</creation>
<langusage><language>English</language></langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>

<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory">
<did>
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
		<corpname>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</corpname>
	</repository>

	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100">Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer</persname>
	</origination>

	<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer papers</unittitle>

	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f">1897-1968</unitdate>

	<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a">8.5 linear feet</physdesc>

	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">The papers of painter, printmaker, and photographer Konrad Cramer and his wife, painter and printmaker Florence Ballin Cramer, measure 8.5 linear feet and date from 1897 to 1968.  Papers document both artists' personal and professional lives and are especially rich in documentation of the art community of Woodstock, NY, where Florence Ballin first attended art classes in 1906, and where the couple settled in 1911.  Records include biographical materials, correspondence, a Christmas card album, writings, business records, personal financial records, printed materials, photographs, and artwork.</abstract>

	<langmaterial>The records are in <language>English</language> and <language>German</language>.
	</langmaterial>
</did>



<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GO HERE: -->


<bioghist altrender="biography" encodinganalog="545" id="a2">
<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>Konrad Cramer was born in Wurtzburg, Germany, in 1888, and studied at the Karlsruhe Academy of Fine Arts from 1906 to 1908 with Ludwig Schmidt-Reutte and Ernest Schurth.  After a year in the German army, he returned to Karlsruhe to set up a studio, making frequent trips to Munich, where he was exposed to the experimental artists of the Blaue Reiter group, including Wassily Kandinsky and Franz Marc.</p>

<p>Florence Ballin was born in Brooklyn, NY, in 1884.  She studied at the Woodstock, New York, summer school of the Art Students League beginning in 1906 under Birge Harrison along with fellow students John Carlson, Grace Mott Johnson, and Andrew Dasburg.  She served as secretary for the League in 1906, and had a studio on 59th Street in Manhattan, where she held her first exhibition in 1909.  In 1911, she traveled to Europe and met Konrad Cramer in Munich and joined him on visits to exhibitions and studios of the vanguard artists.  The two married, moved to the United States, and settled permanently in Woodstock, NY.  </p>

<p>Konrad Cramer is often credited as being in important link between German and American modernism in art, and his experimentations with abstraction and expressionism during his first years in Woodstock would seem to bear this out.  In 1912 and 1913, he painted a series he called "Improvisations" (after Kandinsky) which was shown in a group exhibition at the MacDowell Club in 1913 along with Andrew Dasburg, Oliver Chaffee, and Paul Rohland.  Cramer was photographed by Alfred Stieglitz and wrote an essay about the 291 Gallery for Stieglitz's magazine, <emph render="italic">Camera Work</emph>, in 1914.     </p>

<p>The Cramers had two daughters, in 1914 and 1917, and Konrad Cramer became an American citizen in 1917.  For income, he began designing textiles for department stores using stencils and batiks around 1918.  In his painting, he turned from abstract experiments to the traditional subjects of landscape, still life, and figure in a more representational style that blended modern and regional influences.  Florence Ballin Cramer opened a gallery on 57th Street in 1919, encouraged by the sculptor Elie Nadelman.  The mission of the Florence Gallery, as it was called, was to exhibit and sell the work of living artists.  Although it only survived the season, it was the first gallery to show work by Yasuo Kuniyoshi, Alexander Brook, Ernest Fiene, and Stefan Hirsch, and generated important sales for several young artists in her circle.  </p>

<p>Konrad Cramer returned to Europe in 1920 on a Rockefeller grant to study educational methods for craftsmen in Germany and France, and on his return he taught at the Woodstock School of Painting and Allied Arts.  Cramer also studied lithography with Bolton Brown in Woodstock around this time, and both Cramers took up printmaking and began publishing prints in local arts magazines.  The Cramers were deeply immersed in Woodstock life, participating in the annual Maverick festivals, the Woodstock Artists Association, the Historical Society, and other organizations, hosting meetings and serving as officers of many committees and organizations that presented and supported artwork in their community.  They enjoyed a rich social life there among fellow artists at frequent parties and festivals, where Konrad provided entertainment with his fiddle and both Cramers memorialized events in countless photographs.</p>

<p>Konrad Cramer exhibited at the Whitney Studio Club in 1924, and taught at the Children's University School (now the Dalton School), where he painted a mural in 1929.  The 1930s were busy years in both Cramers' professional lives.  Konrad's exhibitions included the Carnegie International (1929 and 1933), and a two-man show at the Dudensing Gallery (1930), where Cramer and Adolph Gottlieb had been selected the most deserving unknown American painters of the year.  He was also included in the exhibit <emph render="italic">Abstract Painting in America</emph> at the Whitney Museum (1935).  Florence Ballin Cramer exhibited at Marie Harriman Gallery (1931 and 1933), Macy Galleries (1933), at the Pennsylvania Academy (1934 and 1936), and the Corcoran (1935 and 1937).  Both Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer were included in a traveling exhibition of Woodstock artists organized by the College Art Association (1931), the first and second Whitney Biennials (1933 and 1935), and the Wanamaker Regional Art Exhibition of Contemporary American Painting (1934).   </p>

<p>In 1934, the Cramers traveled to Mexico, where they produced many paintings and drawings.  Konrad Cramer joined the Federal Art Project briefly in 1935, administering the regional program in Woodstock with Judson Smith.  It was around this time that he began to learn photography.  He became a sort of community photographer, taking photographs of friends' artwork and commissioned portraits, as well as informal photographs of friends.  Cramer experimented with photographic techniques such as solarization and collage, using prisms, panes of glass, or composite printing.  He first exhibited photographs in 1936 at the Albany Institute, and established the Woodstock School of Miniature Photography (the "miniature" referring to the then-new format of 35mm film) in 1937.  He also taught courses in photography at Bard College in the 1940s, and his photographs and articles about photography were published in national magazines.</p>

<p>For the remainder of his life, Cramer continued to teach, write, and produce photographs, occasionally returning to painting, drawing, and printmaking, creating gouaches, wax resist drawings, and stencils of landscapes and figures, with an increasing interest in abstract styles and automatic techniques.  Three of his early paintings were included in the 1946 Whitney Museum exhibition <emph render="italic">Pioneers of Modern Art in America</emph>, and the same year, he exhibited abstract photographs at the Woodstock Artists Association.  In the late 1940s, he built an automatic drawing machine which he called the sympalmagraph, which rendered precise, geometric forms.  In the late 1950s, he collaborated on a traveling exhibition and book of abstract photographs with Manuel Komroff and Nathan Resnik called <emph render="italic">The Third Eye</emph>.  </p>

<p>Florence Ballin Cramer held her last exhibitions at the Woodstock Town House gallery (1953) and at Long Island University (1957).  She died in 1962.  Konrad Cramer died the following year.  Both were memorialized in an exhibition at the Woodstock Artists Association Gallery in 1968.</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520" id="a3">
<head>Scope and Content Note</head>
<p>The papers of painter, printmaker, and photographer Konrad Cramer and his wife, painter and printmaker Florence Ballin Cramer, measure 8.5 linear feet and date from 1897 to 1968.  Papers document both artists' personal and professional lives and are especially rich in documentation of the art community of Woodstock, NY, from 1906, when Florence first attended art classes there, and where the couple resided until their deaths in the 1960s.  Records include biographical materials, correspondence, a Christmas card album, business records, writings, personal financial records, printed materials, photographs, and artwork.</p>

<p>Correspondence is between the Cramers and other artists, curators, gallery staff, editors, writers, and personal friends and family.  Many drafts and carbons of outgoing letters are also present.  The Christmas card album brings together original cards made by their artist friends in the 1920s and early 1930s.  Writings include diaries of both artists, mostly from 1949 onward, with notes and excerpts from earlier diaries present; technical and biographical essays by Konrad Cramer, and autobiographical and historical essays by Florence Ballin Cramer; notebooks and notes related to art, travel, photography, and other subjects.  Personal Business Records include price lists, receipts, and gallery correspondence with dealers and exhibitors; correspondence, accounting records, and writings related to Florence Ballin Cramer's Florence Gallery in New York City (1919-1920); records related to Woodstock arts and civic organizations in which the Cramers were involved; and personal financial records.</p>

<p>Printed Materials include publicity materials related to the Cramers' various endeavors and the activities of Woodstock arts and civic organizations, as well as dozens of books, little magazines, and journals by and about members of the Woodstock artist's colony.  Photographs depict the Cramers and their friends, including early Art Students League Classes and the annual Maverick festival in the 1920s.  Also found are a small number of photo-collages and experiments with color photography, and a series of early twentieth century photographs in the pictorialist style.  Artwork includes early sketchbooks of both artists; loose sketches, drawings, and designs; textile designs by Konrad Cramer; and prints and printing blocks.
</p>
<!-- add additional <p></p> tags as necessary -->
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351$b" id="a5">
<head>Arrangement</head>
<p>The collection is arranged into 8 series: </p>
<list>
<item>Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1898-1955 (Box 1; 1 folder)</item>
<item>Series 2: Correspondence, 1900-1964 (Boxes 1-3, 9; 2.2 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 3: Christmas Card Album, 1921-1961 (Box 3, 0.8 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 4: Writings, 1897-1962 (Boxes 4-5, 11; 1.7 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 5: Personal Business Records, 1918-1962 (Boxes 5, 10; 0.3 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 6: Printed Materials, 1906-1968 (Boxes 6-7, 11; 1.8 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 7: Photographs, 1906-1960 (Box 7; 0.5 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 8: Artwork, 1897-1954 (Boxes 8-11; 1.2 linear feet)</item>
</list>
</arrangement>


<separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 0" id="a7">
<head>Separated Material</head>
<p>Originals of loaned material, including diaries (Florence Ballin Cramer, 1917-1920; Konrad Cramer, 1918-1921), sketches, and photographs, were returned to Aileen Cramer after microfilming.  Loaned material is available for viewing on microfilm reels D170-D171 and 1027, but is not described in the container listing of this finding aid.</p>
</separatedmaterial>


<!-- use odd for appendixes -->
<odd encodinganalog="500" id="a11">
<head>Index to Selected Correspondence in Series 2</head>
<p>This index to Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer's Correspondence in Series 2 includes selected artists, curators, dealers, patrons, neighbors, and other significant correspondents.  Illustrated letters and significant enclosures are indicated in parentheses.  This index is not comprehensive.  </p>

<p><list><item>
Apple, Marianne: 1942-1943
</item><item>Bacon, Peggy: 1922-1924, 1930, 1940, 1942, undated
</item><item>Barkin, Maeluise; 1950, 1962
</item><item>Barrère, George: 1932
</item><item>Barrère, Jean: 1950
</item><item>Bartlett, Mabel: 1957-1958
</item><item>Berkowitz, Sidney: 1954
</item><item>Bieber, Alfred: 1952, 1958, 1963, undated
</item><item>Blashfield, Edwin Howland: 1906
</item><item>Bloch, Julius: 1937, undated
</item><item>Boch, Alfred: 1961
</item><item>Boissevain Nusbaum, Anne: 1942, 1950, 1960, 1962
</item><item>Bourgeois, Stephan: 1924
</item><item>Braun, Alfred: 1957, 1959-1960, 1962-1963
</item><item>Bridgeman, George: 1906
</item><item>Brook, Alexander: 1924-1927, 1930
</item><item>Bullard, Marion: 1939, 1949
</item><item>Cahill, Holger: 1934
</item><item>Campbell, Blanche: 1948-1950, 1957, 1960
</item><item>Carlson, John: 1909-1911, 1913
</item><item>Carlson, Margaret (Mrs. John): 1962-1963
</item><item>Chambers, Faith: undated
</item><item>Chase, Barbara: 1947
</item><item>Chase, Cathy: 1947
</item><item>Cohn, Hilda: 1949
</item><item>Cowell, Sidney: 1962
</item><item>Cox, Kenyon: 1906
</item><item>Cramer, Belle: 1954
</item><item>Dasburg, Andrew: 1909, 1921, 1924-1927, 1931, 1945, 1955, 1959, undated
</item><item>Davenport, John: 1951-1953, 1955, 1963
</item><item>Delden, Gisela van: 1911, 1927, 1938-1939, 1952, 1954, 1956-1960
</item><item>DeLiagre, Alfred, Ally, and Delly: 1935, 1937, 1942-1943, 1948-1949, 1952, 1958, 1960, undated
</item><item>Dexter, Lindsay: 1939-1940
</item><item>Dickens, Elsa: 1962
</item><item>Dudensing, Leroy: undated
</item><item>Dudensing, Richard: 1932
</item><item>DuFrène, Mary: undated
</item><item>DuMond, Frank Vincent: 1906
</item><item>Dunbar, Henry: 1962
</item><item>Dunn, R. Loring; 1935-1937
</item><item>Eidlitz, Dorothy Meigs: 1945-1951, 1959-1960, 1962
</item><item>Evans, Grace: 1924, 1930 (photos enclosed), 1932, 1940, 1942, 1956, undated
</item><item>Ficke, Evelyn: undated
</item><item>Fischer, Anton Otto: 1943
</item><item>Force, Juliana: 1921, 1932-1934, 1936
</item><item>Fortess, Karl: 1935, 1940, 1945-1947, 1954, 1962
</item><item>Fortess, Lillian: 1934-1935, 1958
</item><item>Franklin, George: 1933
</item><item>Ganso, Emil: 1940-1941
</item><item>Ganso, Fanny: 1941-1947, 1949, 1951, undated
</item><item>George, Rowland: undated
</item><item>George, Thomas: 1963
</item><item>Gershoy (Gottlieb), Eugenie: 1927, 1937
</item><item>Gise, Margaret: 1934
</item><item>Gittis, Archie: 1929, 1939, undated
</item><item>Goldberg, Rube: 1937 (illustrated)
</item><item>Goodrich, Lloyd: 1962-1963
</item><item>Grant, Stuart: 1945
</item><item>Grosz, George: 1933, 1939
</item><item>Guggenheim, Mrs. Jules: 1959
</item><item>Guinzburg, Liu: 1941, undated
</item><item>Gurewitsch, Arno D.: 1936-1937, undated
</item><item>Harrison, Birge: 1910
</item><item>Hartman, Gusta and Bertram: 1928
</item><item>Haz, Hicholas: 1941
</item><item>Henderson, Alice: 1947
</item><item>Hermann, Norbert: 1962
</item><item>Hervey, Wilna: 1931, 1934-1938, 1940-1941, 1951(illustrated), 1956 (illustrated), 1962, undated (photos enclosed)
</item><item>Johnson, Grace Mott: 1910, 1911, 1916-1918, 1921, 1947
</item><item>Jones, Jane (Mrs. Wendell): 1956
</item><item>Karasz, Ilonka: undated (original print)
</item><item>Kass, Marie: 1957-1959
</item><item>Kessel, Therese Woodleaf: 1957
</item><item>Kleinert, Hermine "Mousie": 1911, 1919-1924, 1931-1934, 1936-1941, undated </item><item>Klitgaard, Georgia: 1911, 1913-1914, 1946, undated
</item><item>Komroff, Manuel: 1945-1946, 1949-1952, 1956-1957, 1959-1961, 1963, undated
</item><item>Krom, Alice: 1935, 1943-1944, 1957
</item><item>Kuniyoshi, Katherine: 1956
</item><item>Kuniyoshi, Sara: 1954
</item><item>Labrot, Elanor: 1935
</item><item>Langner, Lawrence: 1920
</item><item>Lathrop, Charles: 1937, undated
</item><item>Lester, Henry: 1945, 1952-1956, undated
</item><item>Lester, Janka: 1940, 1942-1944, 1946, 1949, 1951, 1955-1956, 1958, 1963
</item><item>Lindin, Greg: 1944-1945, undated
</item><item>Lindin, Carl Eric: 1934
</item><item>Lindin, Louise: 1962
</item><item>Marsh, Fred Dana: 1944, 1948-1949, 1953, 1956
</item><item>Marshall, James: 1953, 1955-1956
</item><item>Marshall, Lenore: 1941, 1953, 1955-1958, 1963
</item><item>Mason, Nan: see Wilna Hervey
</item><item>Mayer, Grace: 1959-1960
</item><item>Mayers, Martha: 1934, 1945, 1950, 1953
</item><item>McFee, Aileen: 1917, 1919, 1921, 1928, 1930-1937, 1941, undated 
</item><item>McFee, Henry Lee: 1921-1922, 1930-1931, 1935, 1951, undated 
</item><item>Meadows, Harriet: 1962
</item><item>Mearns, Bill Hughes and Fagley: 1935, 1938-1939, 1941, 1949, 1956
</item><item>Mecklem, Austin "Meck" and Marianne: 1950, 1959
</item><item>Michelson, Nancy: 1959-1960
</item><item>Miles, Florence: 1949
</item><item>More, Herman; 1935, 1944
</item><item>Nadelman, Elie: 1914, undated
</item><item>Nadelman, Viola: 1925-1927, 1942, 1948-1949, undated
</item><item>Nelson, Doris Starr: undated (poems enclosed)
</item><item>Neuman, Janet: 1933-1935, 1956, 1960, 1962
</item><item>Neuman, Robert: 1959
</item><item>Niggli, Josefina and G. Morgan: 1935, 1938-1939, 1942, 1948
</item><item>Nusbaum, Dorothy: 1943, undated
</item><item>Obendorf, C.P.: 1945, 1952
</item><item>Oberferst, Norman: 1955
</item><item>Oertel, Curt: 1953
</item><item>Offner, Phillipa Whiting: 1942
</item><item>Ostes, Camela: 1934-1935, 1938
</item><item>Ottenberg, Irving: 1908, 1959, undated
</item><item>Ottenberg, Reuben: 1917, 1934, 1939, 1942-1945, 1948-1949, 1951, 1953, 1957, 1959, undated (photo enclosed) 
</item><item>Pachner, Bill and Lorraine: 1945-1946, 1950, 1956, 1959, undated
</item><item>Parkhurst, Helen: 1933
</item><item>Penning, Tom: 1943-1944
</item><item>Pittman, Hobson: 1931, 1934, 1940
</item><item>Polansky, Ed: 1958-1959
</item><item>Pollard, William; 1954
</item><item>Ransohoff, Danny: 1943-1947, 1949-1953
</item><item>Reilly, Mary: 1911, 1921
</item><item>Resnick, Nat: 1957, 1962, 1963, undated 
</item><item>Riesberg, Sid: undated
</item><item>Riley, Charlotte: 1923, undated
</item><item>Rohland, Caroline Speare: 1932-1933, 1942-1944, 1947, 1949, 1952, 1954, 1959, 1963, undated 
</item><item>Rohland, Paul: undated
</item><item>Rollo, Jo: 1928-1930
</item><item>Saint-Gaudens, Carlota: 1911, undated
</item><item>Saint-Gaudens, Homer: 1923, 1919, 1933, 1937
</item><item>Segal, Bill: 1953
</item><item>Shermund, Barbara: 1939, 1942, undated
</item><item>Schultz, Andi: 1931-1933, undated
</item><item>Siegel, Adrian and Sophie: 1943-1944, 1953, undated
</item><item>Simonson, Lee: 1921, 1932-1933, undated
</item><item>Sluizer, Esther: 1951, 1962
</item><item>Slusser, Jean Paul: 1933
</item><item>Smith, Frank Leon: 1931, 1958, 1962-1963
</item><item>Smith, Judson: 1934-1935
</item><item>Sortwell, Frances: 1948
</item><item>Speicher, Gene: 1927, 1929 (photo enclosed), undated
</item><item>Sprinchorn, Carl: undated
</item><item>Stieglitz, Alfred: 1916, 1921
</item><item>Streibel, J.H.: 1956 (illustrated)
</item><item>Summers, Dudley: 1950-1953, 1955
</item><item>Trafton, Howard: 1926-1927
</item><item>Uhlenhutt, Edward "Uhli": 1918, 1919, 1921, 1927, 1935, 1937-1938, 1940-1942, 1945, 1947-1952, 1954-1959
</item><item>Varian, Dorothy: 1944
</item><item>Vaughn, Hilda: 1940, undated
</item><item>Walters, Carl: 1948
</item><item>Wangler, Albert: 1962
</item><item>Watson, Forbes: 1938-1939
</item><item>Watson, Thomas Jr.: 1958
</item><item>Webster, Ben: undated
</item><item>Wehle, Harry B.: 1921-1922, 1944
</item><item>Weyhe, E.: 1927
</item><item>White, Hervey: undated
</item><item>Wilson, Marty and Dave: 1952, 1957, 1959-1960, 1962
</item><item>Wingate, Bill and Maxine: 1962
</item><item>Wolfman, Gus: 1959-1960
</item><item>Zimm, Louise: 1962
</item></list>
</p>
</odd>




<!-- END TOP LEVEL METADATA -->

<!-- CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS GO HERE: -->

<controlaccess id="a12">
<head>Index Terms</head>
<p>This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.</p>

<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Woodstock Artists Association (Woodstock, N.Y.)</corpname>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects-Topical:</head>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Artist colonies -- New York (State) -- Woodstock</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Festivals</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Painters -- New York (State) -- Woodstock</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Photographers -- New York (State)</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Printmakers -- New York (State) -- Woodstock</subject>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Types of Materials:</head>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Christmas cards</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Photographs</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Diaries</genreform>

</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Names:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Cramer, Florence Ballin, 1884-1962</persname>
</controlaccess>

</controlaccess>







<!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->

<!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION GOES HERE: -->

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541" id="a19">
<head>Provenance</head>
<p>A portion of the papers in this collection were loaned to the Archives of American Art for microfilming in 1964 by Aileen Cramer and Margot Cramer Taylor, daughters of Florence and Konrad Cramer.  Selected diaries, sketches, and photographs were returned to Aileen Cramer at that time.  Some, but not all, of the original loan was subsequently donated, along with additional materials, in 1975.  Materials returned to the donor can be viewed on microfilm. </p>
</acqinfo>

<accessrestrict id="a14" encodinganalog="506">
<head>Restrictions on Access</head>
<p>The collection is open for research.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="a15">
<head>Ownership and Literary Rights</head>
<p>The Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer papers are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
</userestrict>

<altformavail id="a17" encodinganalog="530">
<head>Alternative Forms Available</head>
<p>Microfilm of much of the collection is available on microfilm reels D170-D171, 1027, 1203-1204, 2751-2757 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan.  Researchers should note that the arrangement of the collection described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm.  </p>
</altformavail>


<prefercite encodinganalog="510" id="a18">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer papers, 1897-1964. Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
</prefercite>

<processinfo encodinganalog="583" id="a20">
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>A portion of the papers in this collection were loaned to the Archives of American Art for microfilming in 1964 and are available for viewing on reels D170-171 and 1027.  Most of the loaned materials were donated in 1975, along with additional materials that were microfilmed on reels 1203-1204 and reels 2751-2757. A small portion of material, consisting mostly of duplicates and photographs of works of art, was never microfilmed.  Previously microfilmed and unmicrofilmed portions were merged, arranged, and described as a whole by Megan McShea in 2006 with funding provided by the Terra Foundation for American Art. The current archival arrangement does not match the arrangement of the materials on microfilm. </p>
</processinfo>


<!-- END ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->


<!-- START DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->


<dsc type="combined" id="a23">
<head>Series Descriptions/Container Listing</head>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 1: </unitid><unittitle>Biographical Materials, <unitdate>1898-1955, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 1 folder)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Biographical materials include a birth certificate for Konrad Cramer; picture postcards showing views of Konrad Cramer's neighborhood in Karlsruhe, Germany; the calling card of the man who introduced Konrad and Florence; the Cramers' wedding announcement; a biographical essay about Konrad Cramer; an informal will written by Florence Ballin Cramer; and other personal certificates and documents.</p> 
<p>Items in this series were previously scattered throughout the collection.  Most can be viewed on reels 2751, 2755, and 2756.</p>
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Biographical Materials, <unitdate>1898-1955, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 2: </unitid><unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1900-1964, undated </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Boxes 1-3, 9; 2.2 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series consists of Florence Ballin Cramer and Konrad Cramer's correspondence, including outgoing drafts and carbons of letters written by the Cramers.  Correspondence is arranged chronologically, with undated letters and drafts of letters filed alphabetically at the end of the series.  Before 1911 correspondence is entirely that of Florence Ballin, and the letters of 1911 are dominated by a large volume of letters between Florence Ballin and Konrad Cramer during the months of their courtship, many of which are in German.  Letters and notes between the two are found throughout the series.  Also found are letters to Florence's brother Irving Ballin, and letters to and from the Cramer's children, Margot and Aileen.  An increasing number of outgoing drafts of letters written by Konrad Cramer are found beginning in the 1950s.
</p><p>
Correspondents include artists, curators, gallery staff, editors, writers, and personal friends and family.  Artists represented here include John Carlson, Birge Harrison, Peggy Bacon, Alexander Brook, Andrew Dasburg, Alfred Stieglitz, Julius Bloch, Grace Mott Johnson, George Franklin, Hermine Kleinert, Holger Cahill, Grace Evans, Emil Ganso, George Grosz, Carl Eric Lindin, Fred Dana Marsh, Henry Lee McFee, Elie Nadelman, Homer Saint-Gaudens, Lee Simonson, Gene Speicher, Carl Sprinchorn, Alfred Stieglitz, Dorothy Varian.  Artwork found in the correspondence includes a hand-painted card from Peggy Bacon and Alexander Brook (1923), a Rube Goldberg cartoon (1937), and an illustrated letter from Konrad to Florence Cramer (1957).  See the index to correspondence for additional illustrated letters, and the Christmas Card album in Series 3 for additional hand-made cards.  
</p><p>
The correspondence files include fragments of letters, especially  drafts of outgoing letters, and enclosures such as receipts, photographs, and clippings. These include early photographs of Konrad Cramer in the 1911 letters, and a photograph of Eugene Speicher from 1929.  Notes made retrospectively by Florence Ballin Cramer are sometimes found with letters or on accompanying envelopes.  
</p><p>
Correspondence in this series is from two separate accessions which were previously microfilmed on reels D170-171 and 2751-2753, and which are now merged into a single chronological sequence.  Materials that relate to galleries and exhibitions, which were formerly arranged and microfilmed with general correspondence on reels D170-171, have been moved to Personal Business Records.  Scattered papers which are not correspondence, but which were interfiled with letters in the microfilm arrangement, have been relocated to their appropriate series, such as Writings, Photographs, and Printed Materials.</p>

<p>Additional correspondence can be found in Personal Business Records, and drafts of outgoing letters are found in Notebooks in the Writings series.  See also the Christmas Card Album for additional notes and cards.  See the index to correspondence for names and dates of selected correspondants in this series.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">2-54</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1900-1941</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(53 folders; see also Box 9, sol)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">2</container>
	<container type="folder">1-36</container>
	<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1942-1964</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(36 folders; see also Box 9, sol)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">2</container>
	<container type="folder">37</container>
	<unittitle>Correspondence; Cramer, Aileen, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">2</container>
	<container type="folder">38</container>
	<unittitle>Correspondence; Cramer, Florence Ballin, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">2</container>
	<container type="folder">39-40</container>
	<unittitle>Correspondence; Cramer, Konrad, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders; see also Box 9, sol)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>


<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">2</container>
	<container type="folder">41-44</container>
	<unittitle>Correspondence; A-W, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(4 folders)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">2</container>
	<container type="folder">45</container>
	<unittitle>Correspondence; First Names Only or Illegible, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">3</container>
	<container type="folder">1-5</container>
	<unittitle>Correspondence, Envelopes, <unitdate>1909-1963, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(5 folders)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">9 (sol)</container>
	<container type="folder"></container>
	<unittitle>Oversized Correspondence<unitdate></unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(See Box 1, f22; Box 2, f22, 25, 26, 31, and 40)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>

</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 3: </unitid><unittitle>Christmas Card Album, <unitdate>1921-1931, 1940, 1961, undated </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 3; 0.8 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>The Cramers' Christmas card album is a large scrapbook containing handmade cards, wrapping papers, and a collection of postcards and clippings depicting animals.  Most of the Christmas cards were received between 1921 and 1931, and many bear original works of art.  Artists represented in the album include Peggy Bacon, Austin Mecklem, Frank Chase, Nan Mason, Hermine Kleinert, Harry Gottlieb, Felix Payant, E. Weyhe, Cecil Chichester, Henry Lee McFee, Arthur Young, Rudolph Wetterau, Sam Wylie, Wanda Gág, Will Shuster, Judson Smith, Elsa Milius, Louise Hellstrom, Jok Billings, Henry Billings, Emil Ganso, Marisha Karasz, Lee Simonson, Jo Cantine, Carl Lindin, Orville Peets, Paul and Caroline Rohland, C. Bertram Hartman, and Peter Juley.  Photographs include a portrait of Aileen and Henry Lee McFee and several photographs of friends' homes.
</p><p>
Loose items found in the album which do not appear to have been pasted in originally have been removed to a separate folder.  Items which were pasted in and have since become unglued have been kept in the album between the pages of what appears to be their original location.
</p><p>
Additional hand-made cards are scattered throughout the Correspondence series.  A small portion of cards in the album have been microfilmed on reel 2753.    
</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container><container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>Christmas Card Album, <unitdate>1921-1931, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">3</container>
	<container type="folder">7</container>
	<unittitle>Items Found In Christmas Card Album, <unitdate>1926, 1931, 1940, 1961, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>

</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 4: </unitid><unittitle>Writings, <unitdate>1897-1962, undated </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Boxes 4-5, 11; 1.7 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series includes the notes and writings of Florence Ballin Cramer and Konrad Cramer, along with scattered notes and writings by others.  Types of material include an address book; appointment books; diaries, notes and excerpts from diaries, and items found in diaries; essays; notebooks; poems; a movie scenario; and notes.  Some of the notebooks include drafts of outgoing correspondence. </p>

<p>Diaries include twelve volumes kept by Konrad Cramer from 1945 to 1962, and two volumes and some loose pages by Florence Ballin Cramer, as well as notes and excerpts from diaries that are not part of the collection. Konrad Cramer's diary entries are sporadic, recording his farming activities, weather conditions, and personal activities.  The volume for 1949 also contains notes from Florence Ballin Cramer's lengthy hospital stay and his contacts in New York during that time.  Florence Ballin Cramer's diaries date from her school days and travels to Europe, when she met Konrad Cramer, and contain many sketches.  A later volume documents her hospital stay, and also contains sketches.  Also found are detailed notes and excerpts from diaries not found in the collection, possibly loaned for microfilming and returned to the Cramers.  In addition, loose items removed from several diaries, including those found within the collection and those removed from the collection, are filed here and include photographs of Florence, unidentified friends, a costume ball, and the area around Woodstock; early exhibition documentation; clippings; a sketch; and writings by Florence and Irving Ballin. </p>

<p>Konrad Cramer's essays mostly concern technical aspects of painting, drawing, printmaking, and photography, with a few essays on broad concepts such as modernism and design.  Also found are numerous drafts of informal essays about people known to Cramer, including people from the Woodstock community such as Hervey White, founder of the Maverick artist's colony.  Florence Ballin Cramer's essays include a lengthy autobiographical essay about her earliest visits to Woodstock as a student of the Art Student's League summer classes, essays on Ameican crafts and Mexican artists, and other subjects.</p>

<p>Konrad Cramer's earliest notebook contains recipes gathered from his peers for paints and varnishes.  Other notebooks contain essays, technical notes, drafts of outgoing letters, and some notes from meetings of Woodstock organizations.  Volumes given titles by Cramer are listed by title, and titled essays within volumes are noted in the folder contents list.  Florence Ballin Cramer's notebooks include two volumes from her adolescence containing notes and drawings.</p>

<p>Notes include travel notes and an annotated map from a 1938 trip West and notes written by Florence Ballin Cramer and Konrad Cramer including technical photo notes, recipes, quotes from published sources, contact information, and other miscellany.  Collection notes, probably written by Florence Ballin Cramer, describe materials in the Cramer papers that have become separated from the items they describe.  Miscellaneous notes include a student's poem, a list of books about Greenwich Village, and a brief note from a friend.</p>

<p>Additional notes and writings are found in Biographical Materials and Personal Business Records.  Picture books by the Cramers are found in Artwork.  </p>

<p>Most of the papers in this series were previously microfilmed on reels 2753-2755, unless otherwise noted in the folder heading.
</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container><container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Address Book, Florence Ballin Cramer, <unitdate>circa 1910s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">4</container>
	<container type="folder">2</container>
	<unittitle>Appointment Books, Florence Ballin (Cramer), <unitdate>1908, 1910</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">4</container>
	<unittitle>Diaries</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">4</container>
	<container type="folder">3-13</container>
	<unittitle>Konrad Cramer, <unitdate>1945-1950, 1957-1962</unitdate></unittitle>
  <physdesc>(12 volumes in 11 folders)</physdesc>  </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">4</container>
	<unittitle>Florence Ballin Cramer</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">4</container>
	<container type="folder">14</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>1911, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">4</container>
	<container type="folder">15</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>1949-1951</unitdate></unittitle>
	    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">4</container>
	<container type="folder">16</container>
	<unittitle>Notes (1906-1907, 1926-1943), <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">4</container>
	<container type="folder">17</container>
	<unittitle>Excerpts from Removed Diaries, <unitdate>1916-1917, 1934, 1955, 1958-1962</unitdate></unittitle>
	    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">4</container>
	<container type="folder">18</container>
	<unittitle>Loose Items Removed from 1908-1910 Diary, <unitdate>1907-1913, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">4</container>
	<container type="folder">19</container>
	<unittitle>Items Removed from 1911 Diary, <unitdate>1940, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">4</container>
	<container type="folder">20</container>
	<unittitle>Excerpts and Items Removed from Unspecified Diary, <unitdate>1909, 1917, 1920, 1925, 1935, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c04>
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<unittitle>Essays</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<unittitle>Konrad Cramer</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">1</container>
	<unittitle>"The Painter's Handbook", <unitdate>1932</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">2</container>
	<unittitle>"The Good Painter's Handbook", <unitdate>1933</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">3</container>
	<unittitle>"The Artist in the Darkroom", <unitdate>circa 1937</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">4</container>
	<unittitle>"The Tools for Drawing", <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">5</container>
	<unittitle>"The Artist and His Craft", <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	<scopecontent><p>(Includes sections by unidentified authors)</p></scopecontent>
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">6</container>
	<unittitle>"How to Display the Modern Photograph", <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">7</container>
	<unittitle>"Modern Tendencies in Art", <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">8</container>
	<unittitle>"The Origin of Design", <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">9</container>
	<unittitle>"The What and How of Photography", <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">10</container>
	<unittitle>"The Why and How of the Art Department", <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">11</container>
	<unittitle>"Memo for the Art Room" (Dalton School), <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">12</container>
	<unittitle>People and Woodstock History, <unitdate>1937-1962, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also OV 11)</physdesc>	
    </did>	<scopecontent><p>(Amalie Cramer; Harold Reynolds; Hervey White and the Maverick Story; Rosie Magee; J. Albert of Munich and Albertypes; Sidney Berkowitz; Carl Olaf Eric Lindin)</p></scopecontent>
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">13</container>
	<unittitle>Miscellaneous Essays and Notes about Art, <unitdate>1934, 1960, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">14</container>
	<unittitle>Miscellaneous Essays, Non-Art Subjects, <unitdate>1957-1958, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">15</container>
	<unittitle>(Copies), <unitdate>1953, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<unittitle>Florence Ballin Cramer</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">16</container>
	<unittitle>Autobiographical Sketch about Woodstock circa 1906-1910, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">17</container>
	<unittitle>"The Artists in Mexico", <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">18</container>
	<unittitle>"Craftwork In America", <unitdate>circa 1928-1931</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">19</container>
	<unittitle>Miscellaneous Non-Art Subjects, <unitdate>1938, 1950, 1959, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">20</container>
	<unittitle>(Copies), <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">21</container>
	<unittitle>Unknown Author, "The Kindergarten - What It Is", <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<unittitle>Notebooks</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<unittitle>Konrad Cramer (see also Artwork, sketchbook with notes on printmaking)</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">22</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>1929-1930</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	<scopecontent><p>(Contains recipes from various artists for paint, varnish, and other media; and technical notes)</p></scopecontent>
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">23</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>1944-1945</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	<scopecontent><p>(Contains the essay "A Practical Handbook of Drawing", with editor's comments)</p></scopecontent>
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">24</container>
	<unittitle>"Handbook of Drawing, Volume 1", <unitdate>1945</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	<scopecontent><p>(Also contains drafts of outgoing letters)</p></scopecontent>
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">25-26</container>
	<unittitle>"Volume 2", <unitdate>1945</unitdate></unittitle>
	<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>    
</did>	
<scopecontent><p>(Contains "Handbook of Drawing, Volume 2")</p></scopecontent>
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">27</container>
	<unittitle>"Notes on Stieglitz", <unitdate>1946</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	<scopecontent><p>(Also contains meeting notes of the Woodstock Foundation, and an essay about Thanksgiving at Rivington Hospital)</p></scopecontent>
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">28</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>1957</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	<scopecontent><p>(Contains the essay "Developing 35mm Film by Inspection," also drafts of outgoing letters and notes regarding the Kleinert Wing of the Woodstock Foundation)</p></scopecontent>
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">29</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>1952, 1958</unitdate></unittitle>
	    </did>	<scopecontent><p>(Contains drafts of outgoing letters and technical notes)</p></scopecontent>
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">30</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>circa 1958</unitdate></unittitle>
	    </did>	<scopecontent><p>(Contains fragment of essay "Restoring Oil Paintings" and drafts of outgoing letters)</p></scopecontent>
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">31</container>
	<unittitle>"Notes on Lectures for Painting Materials", <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">32</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	<scopecontent><p>(Contains essays related to photography and notes on Mozart's letters)</p></scopecontent>
</c04>
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<unittitle>Florence Ballin Cramer</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">33-34</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>1897-1898</unitdate></unittitle>
	<physdesc>(2 volumes in 2 folders)</physdesc>
    </did>	
</c04>
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<unittitle>Unknown Author</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">35</container>
	<unittitle>Recipes in German, <unitdate>1800s</unitdate></unittitle>
	    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">36</container>
	<unittitle>Forecast of Futures of Woodstock Children, <unitdate>1935</unitdate></unittitle>
	    </did>	
</c04>
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<unittitle>Poetry</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<unittitle>Florence Ballin Cramer</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">37</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>1924-1929, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">38</container>
	<unittitle>Poems for Children, <unitdate>1920s</unitdate></unittitle>
	
    </did>	
</c04>
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">39</container>
	<unittitle>Irving Ballin, <unitdate>1908-1912</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">40</container>
	<unittitle>Movie Scenario by Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer, <unitdate>circa 1912, 1938</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<unittitle>Notes</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">41</container>
	<unittitle>Travel Notes and Map (see also Reel 2756), <unitdate>1938, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">42</container>
	<unittitle>Miscellaneous Notes by Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">43</container>
	<unittitle>Notes by Manuel Komroff, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">44</container>
	<unittitle>Notes from Oral Histories of the Cramers and Hermine Kleinert by Sam Eskin, <unitdate>1962, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">45</container>
	<unittitle>Collection Notes (not microfilmed), <unitdate>1958-1959, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">46</container>
	<unittitle>Excerpts from Correspondence (1937), <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">47</container>
	<unittitle>Contacts, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">48</container>
	<unittitle>Miscellaneous Notes, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
</c02>

<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">11 (OV)</container>
	<unittitle>Oversized Writings</unittitle>
<physdesc>(See Box 5, f12)</physdesc>    </did>	
</c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 5: </unitid><unittitle>Personal Business Records, <unitdate>1918-1962, undated </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Boxes 5, 10; 0.3 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series contains records of Florence Ballin Cramer's and Konrad Cramer's respective artistic careers, other business and civic pursuits, and personal finances.</p>

<p>Artwork and exhibit records of Konrad Cramer include correspondence with the Dudensing Gallery, the Whitney Museum, John Graham and Sons, the Woodstock Artists Association and other exhibitors and dealers.  Also found are receipts and price lists, some of which are illustrated with rough sketches.  Florence Ballin Cramer's artwork and exhibit records include price lists, receipts, a guest book, and mailing lists, most of which refer to her 1953 exhibition at the Woodstock Town House gallery.  Documents from her exhibitions at the Marie Harriman Gallery and Long Island University are also found. Additional materials related to exhibitions can be found in Printed Materials.</p>

<p>Records of the Florence Ballin Cramer's 57th Street gallery, the Florence Gallery, include photographs of Florence in the gallery, her contract with H. Kevorkian for the use of the space, clippings, catalogs, price lists, and letters from artists and subscribers to the gallery, including Andrew Dasburg, Gene Speicher, Stefan Hirsch, Elie Nadelman, Christine Chaplin, Paul Rohland, Caroline Speare, John Everts Bates, and Forbes Watson.  Also found are drafts of letters and other writings by Florence promoting the gallery and its mission, and a small card file recording sales, income and expenses, and contact information.</p>

<p>Records of Florence Cramer's shop in Woodstock consist mostly of accounting and inventory records.  Correspondence related to this venture can be found in the correspondence series, especially for the years 1925 to 1927.</p>

<p>Records of Woodstock craft organizations include legal contracts, by-laws, letters, notes, press releases, and other records related to the Woodstock Guild of Craftsmen and the Crafts' Foundation of Woodstock.  Included are drafts of letters and speeches related to the opening of the Kleinert Wing of the Woodstock Guild of Craftsmen's building in 1958.  See Correspondence, Writings, and Printed Materials for additional materials related to these groups.  </p>

<p>Konrad Cramer's employment contracts with the Children's University School (now the Dalton School) and an advertising firm are also found.  For materials related to his various teaching endeavors, see Writings and Printed Materials.</p>

<p>Materials in this series were previously scattered among the various accessions.  Microfilm reels on which most of the documents in this series can be viewed are indicated in parentheses by the folder heading.  Researchers should note that the order of documents on microfilm does not reflect the current physical arrangement.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<unittitle>Artwork and Exhibit Records</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">49-52</container>
	<unittitle>Konrad Cramer (Reels D170-D171, 2755), <unitdate>1929-1936, 1952-1962, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(4 folders)</physdesc>    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">53</container>
	<unittitle>Florence Ballin Cramer (Reels D171, 2755), <unitdate>1933, 1936, 1953, 1957, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 <physdesc>(See also OV 10)</physdesc>   </did>	
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">54</container>
	<unittitle>Art Students League By-Law Amendments (Reel D170), <unitdate>1906</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">55-58</container>
	<unittitle>Florence Gallery Records (Reel D170), <unitdate>1918-1923, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(4 folders)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">59-61</container>
	<unittitle>Florence Ballin Cramer's Woodstock Shop Records (Reel 2755), <unitdate>1922-1944, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(3 folders)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">62-63</container>
	<unittitle>Records of Woodstock Craft Organizations (Reel 2755 and 2756), <unitdate>1948-1959, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders; see also OV 10)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">64</container>
	<unittitle>Records of Other Woodstock Organizations (Reel 2757), <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	<scopecontent><p>(Woodstock Town House, Maverick Summer Concerts)</p></scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">65</container>
	<unittitle>Konrad Cramer Patent on Camera Accessory (Reel 2755), <unitdate>1939</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">66</container>
	<unittitle>Konrad Cramer's Employment Contracts (Reel 2755), <unitdate>1926, 1929</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<unittitle>Personal Financial Records</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">67-68</container>
	<unittitle>Account Books (Reel 2755), <unitdate>1955-1959</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>    </did>	<scopecontent><p>(Contain sketches)</p></scopecontent>
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">69</container>
	<unittitle>Assets (Reel 2755), <unitdate>1928, 1930, 1954-1960</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">70</container>
	<unittitle>Bank and Stock Records (Reel 2755 and unfilmed), <unitdate>1932, 1955-1962, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">71</container>
	<unittitle>Bills and Receipts (Reel 2755 and unfilmed), <unitdate>1919-1961, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">5</container>
	<container type="folder">72</container>
	<unittitle>Property Improvements (Reel 2755), <unitdate>1924, 1961</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">10 (OV)</container>
	<unittitle>Oversized Personal Business Records (See Box 5, f53 and 62)</unittitle>
    </did>	
</c02>
</c01>


<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 6: </unitid><unittitle>Printed Materials, <unitdate>1906-1968, undated </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Boxes 6-7, 9, 11; 1.8 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series includes clippings, exhibition catalogs, press releases, printed ephemera related to Woodstock organizations and events, and over a dozen periodicals and books by and about Woodstock artists and writers.  Other materials include letterhead, business cards, brochures, posters, maps, postcards, and other publicity pieces.</p>

<p>Exhibition announcements, catalogs, and invitations are for Florence Ballin Cramer's and Konrad Cramer's group and solo shows as well as shows of other artists.  Clippings are mostly from New York City and Woodstock-area papers and include notices and reviews of exhibitions, art news and features, articles about friends and neighbors, and other miscellany.  Some clippings have been pasted to other types of documents, such as contracts or correspondence related to one of the Cramers' exhibitions, and appear to have been cut from a scrapbook.  A number of newspapers saved in their entirety feature coverage of significant local events in Woodstock. </p>

<p>Brochures and letterhead are found for Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer's various professional endeavors, including the Konrad Cramer's School for Miniature Photography as well as his auto mechanic service, Florence Ballin Cramer's antique shop, and other entities, many of which appear to be made with a manual letter-press and decorated with relief prints.  Prints by other artists are filed separately and include a large engraved map of Woodstock created by Marg and Rudolph Wetterau.  Additional prints are found in the Artwork series.</p>

<p>Woodstock organizations and events are documented here with brochures, posters, announcements, catalogs, programs, directories, and newsletters, many of which refer to Konrad or Florence Ballin Cramer's involvement in the organization.  Woodstock publications include thirteen titles of books, little magazines, and journals featuring prints, drawings, stencils, and writings of the Cramers and other Woodstock-area artists and writers such as Hervey White, Paul Rohland, Peggy Bacon, Alexander Brook, John Carroll, Andrew Dasburg, John Evert Bates, Jean Paul Slusser, Grace Mott Johnson, Judson Smith, Rudolph and Marg Wetterau, Arnold Blanch, and many others.  The largest run in the series is for the satirical arts paper Hue and Cry, which includes several complete volumes for its early years as well as two annuals with original relief prints on rice paper and many art reproductions.  Issues of both The Wasp and The Overlook contain lengthy essays about Konrad Cramer.  Woodstock Gargoyles features articles by many mainstays of the Woodstock community including Konrad Cramer, and is the first and only issue of that publication.</p>

<p>Additional scattered printed materials are filed with Biographical Materials, Correspondence, Writings (Items found in diaries), and Personal Business Records.  See series descriptions for more details.</p>

<p>Printed materials in this series were part of two separate accessions previously arranged and microfilmed on reels D171 and 2755-2757, unless otherwise noted. 
</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">6</container><container type="folder">1-8</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, and Invitations, <unitdate>1909-1968, undated </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(8 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">9-21</container>
	<unittitle>Clippings, <unitdate>1908-1962, 1965, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(13 folders)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">22-24</container>
	<unittitle>Magazines, Journals, and Other Articles, <unitdate>1906-1958, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(3 folders)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">25-27</container>
	<unittitle>Newspapers (not microfilmed), <unitdate>1925-1955</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(3 folders)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">28</container>
	<unittitle>Press Releases and Advertisements, <unitdate>1951-1962</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">29</container>
	<unittitle>Reproductions of Artwork, <unitdate>1937, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">30</container>
	<unittitle>Business Cards, <unitdate>1920, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">31</container>
	<unittitle>Cramers' Brochures and Letterhead, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<unittitle>Woodstock Organizations and Events</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">32</container>
	<unittitle>Woodstock Artists Association, <unitdate>1933, 1947-1948, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">33</container>
	<unittitle>Woodstock Guild of Craftsmen, <unitdate>1948-1951</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">34</container>
	<unittitle>Woodstock School of Painting, <unitdate>1920, 1934-1935</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">35</container>
	<unittitle>Woodstock School of Miniature Photography, <unitdate>1937-1946</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">36</container>
	<unittitle>Miscellaneous Woodstock Schools and Workshops, <unitdate>1952-1958, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">37</container>
	<unittitle>"The First Art Film Festival in America", <unitdate>1951</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">38</container>
	<unittitle>The Woodstock Festival, <unitdate>1959-1960, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">39</container>
	<unittitle>Programs for Cultural Events in Woodstock, <unitdate>1931-1960, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also OV 11)</physdesc>    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">40</container>
	<unittitle>Woodstock Civic Organizations, <unitdate>1933-1959, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<unittitle>Woodstock Publications</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">41-42</container>
	<unittitle><emph render="italic">The Plowshare</emph>, <unitdate>1917-1919</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">43</container>
	<unittitle><emph render="italic">Woodstock, an Essay by Richard Le Gallienne, with Reproductions of Work by Woodstock Artists</emph>, <unitdate>1923</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">44</container>
	<unittitle><emph render="italic">Woodstock Almanac</emph>, <unitdate>1924</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">6</container>
	<container type="folder">45</container>
	<unittitle><emph render="italic">The Maverick Hoot</emph>, <unitdate>1927</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">1-8</container>
	<unittitle><emph render="italic">Hue and Cry</emph>, <unitdate>1923-1926, 1929, 1933, 1945</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(8 folders; see also Box 9, sol)</physdesc>    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">9</container>
	<unittitle><emph render="italic">The Woodstock Bulletin</emph>, <unitdate>1929-1930</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">10-11</container>
	<unittitle><emph render="italic">The Overlook</emph>, <unitdate>1931-1932</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">12</container>
	<unittitle><emph render="italic">Art Notes</emph>, Vol. 11, No. 10, <unitdate>1932</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">13-15</container>
	<unittitle><emph render="italic">Publications of the Woodstock Historical Society</emph>, <unitdate>1930-1939</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(3 folders)</physdesc>    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">16</container>
	<unittitle><emph render="italic">Fallen Leaves</emph> by Carl Eric Lindin, <unitdate>1941</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">17</container>
	<unittitle><emph render="italic">Woodstock Gargoyles</emph>, <unitdate>1949</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">18</container>
	<unittitle><emph render="italic">The Wasp</emph>, <unitdate>1952, 1954</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">19</container>
	<unittitle><emph render="italic">The Bulletin</emph>, <unitdate>1960-1961</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<unittitle>Other Brochures, Mailings, and Posters</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">20</container>
	<unittitle>Art Students League, <unitdate>1948-1950, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(See also OV 11)</physdesc>    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">21</container>
	<unittitle>Clubs, <unitdate>1950, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	<scopecontent><p>(United World Federalists, Circle of Confusion)</p></scopecontent>
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">22</container>
	<unittitle>Camera Equipment, <unitdate>1947-1958, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">23</container>
	<unittitle>Mexico, <unitdate>1934, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">24</container>
	<unittitle>Miscellaneous Brochures and Mailings, <unitdate>1947-1951, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">25</container>
	<unittitle>Blank Cards and Postcards, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">26</container>
	<unittitle>Relief Prints and Engravings Including Map of Woodstock (partially microfilmed), <unitdate>1912, 1927, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(See also OV 11)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>

<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">9 (sol)</container>
	<unittitle>Oversized Issues of <emph render="italic">Hue and Cry</emph> (See Box 7, f1, 3-6, 8)</unittitle>
    </did>	
</c02>

<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">11 (OV)</container>
	<unittitle>Oversized Programs for Cultural Events in Woodstock (See Box 6, f39)</unittitle>
    </did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">11 (OV)</container>
	<unittitle>Oversized Art Students League Posters (See Box 7, f20)</unittitle>
    </did>	
</c02>

<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">11 (OV)</container>
	<unittitle>Oversized Relief Prints and Engravings Including Map of Woodstock (See Box 7, f26)</unittitle>
    </did>	
</c02>
</c01>


<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 7: </unitid><unittitle>Photographs, <unitdate>1906-1960, undated </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 7; 0.5 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series includes snapshots, photo postcards, fine prints, and negatives depicting Florence Ballin Cramer, Konrad Cramer, their friends, schools, studios, Woodstock parties, the Maverick Festival, scenic views of Woodstock, and photographs of works of art.</p>

<p>A series of early photographs in the pictorialist style appear to have been made on printing-out paper and are filed under the heading "Early Woodstock Views and Figures."  Their photographer is unknown, but the female figure depicted is most likely Florence Ballin.  A few examples of photo experiments with color and collage, probably by Konrad Cramer, are also found.  Photographs filed under the heading "Portraits of Friends" include formal portraits, snapshots, and a series of posed photographs Konrad Cramer took of friends with family members in their homes.</p>

<p>Many of the photographs in this series were probably taken by Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer, although many are uncredited.  Wherever possible, photographs that appear to have been taken together have been filed together.  Except for very early photographs, many of the individuals pictured have been identified on the photographs themselves, and names of those identified are noted in the folder listing.</p>

<p>Additional photographs are found in Correspondence, Personal Business Records (Florence Gallery records), and Writings (Items found in diaries).  Writings and notes related to Konrad Cramer's work with photography are found in the Writings series, and manuals for cameras are filed with Printed Materials.</p>

<p>Except for photographs of works of art, which were not microfilmed, photographs in this series were microfilmed in an earlier arrangement on reels 1203 and 1204, unless otherwise noted.
</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">7</container><container type="folder">27</container>
<unittitle>Early Florence Ballin, Irving Ballin, and Friends, <unitdate>1906, 1919, 1928, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did><scopecontent><p>(Also pictured are Homer and Carlota Saint-Gaudens and Henry Lee McFee, with note from McFee)</p></scopecontent></c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">28</container>
	<unittitle>Early Konrad Cramer and Friends (one image on Reel 2756), <unitdate>circa 1909, 1915</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">29</container>
	<unittitle>Konrad Cramer's Studio, <unitdate>1952, 1958, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">30</container>
	<unittitle>Florence Ballin's Studio, <unitdate>circa 1900s</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">31</container>
	<unittitle>Florence Ballin Cramer and Konrad Cramer, <unitdate>1930s-1951, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">32</container>
	<unittitle>Florence Ballin Cramer's Exhibit Opening, Woodstock, <unitdate>circa 1950s</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<unittitle>Portraits of Friends</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">33</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>1908, 1923, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	<scopecontent><p>(pictured are Carlota Saint-Gaudens, Louise Hellstrom, Henry Lee McFee (Reel 1817 and digitized), Arnold Blanch (Reel 439 and digitized), Karl Fortess, Carl Walters, Sara Kuniyoshi, Marion Greenwood, Barbara Shermund, John Striebel, John Carlson)</p></scopecontent>
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">34-37</container>
	<unittitle>Gene and Elsie Speicher (One photo on Reel 440 and digitized), <unitdate>1930s, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(4 folders, including duplicates and copy print)</physdesc>    </did>	</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">38</container>
	<unittitle>Frank Chase and Son Dennis, <unitdate>circa 1930s</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">39</container>
	<unittitle>Neil Ives and Daughter Peggy Cole, <unitdate>1930s</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">40</container>
	<unittitle>Henry Billings, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">41</container>
	<unittitle>Hervey White, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">42</container>
	<unittitle>Merril (Pixie) and Fritz Mueller, <unitdate>1960</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">43-44</container>
	<unittitle>Judson and Mary Smith, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
  <physdesc>(2 folders, including copy print)</physdesc>  </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">45-46</container>
	<unittitle>Yasuo Kuniyoshi (One photo on Reel 439 and digitized), <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders, including copy negative)</physdesc>    </did>	
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">47-48</container>
	<unittitle>Art Classes, Group and Candid Shots, <unitdate>1904-1909, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders, including copy negatives and prints)</physdesc>	</did>	<scopecontent><p>(includes Art Students League classes, picturing Edith Morrell, Remington Schuyler, R. Nisbet, John Carlson, Florence Ballin, Grace Johnson, Mollie Bannister, Mary Reilly, Pop Goltz, Birge Harrison, Andrew Dasburg, among others)</p></scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">49-50</container>
	<unittitle>Maverick Festival, <unitdate>1922, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders, including copy print)</physdesc>	</did>	<scopecontent><p>(pictured are Ernest Brace, Florence Ballin Cramer, Reeves Brace, Konrad Cramer, Helen Walters, Eugenie Gershoy, Harry Gottlieb, and Marjorie Barnes)</p></scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">51</container>
	<unittitle>Woodstock People, <unitdate>circa 1909-1938, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	<scopecontent><p>(pictured are Gene Speicher, John Carlson, Andrew Dasburg, Harry Hopkins, Came and Ella Lasher, Charles Rosen, Clarence Bolton, and others unidentified)</p></scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">52</container>
	<unittitle>Woodstock Parties, <unitdate>1946-1957, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	<scopecontent><p>(pictured are Alexander Brook, Joe Pollett, Tom Penning, Helen Estes, Elsa Kimball, Sid Berkowitz, Dick Burlingame, Herman Cherry, Charles Rosen, John Striebel, Sigmund Menkes, Zombie Pachner, Sam Eskin, Florine Walkowitz, Kaj Klitgaard, Marianne Mecklin, Jay Allen, Odillon, Gene Speicher, Arnold Blanch, Edward L. Chase, Henry Mattson, Fanny Ganso, Yasuo Kuniyoshi, Karl Fortess, and many others)</p></scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">53-54</container>
	<unittitle>Woodstock Views, <unitdate>circa 1909, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders, including copy print)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">55</container>
	<unittitle>Early Woodstock Views and Figures, <unitdate>circa 1900s</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	<scopecontent><p>(figure may be Florence Ballin)</p></scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">56</container>
	<unittitle>Color and College Experiments by Konrad Cramer, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">57</container>
	<unittitle>Travel Snapshots, <unitdate>1934, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">58</container>
	<unittitle>Photo Postcards, <unitdate>circa 1934</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">59</container>
	<unittitle>Miscellaneous Photographs, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<unittitle>Works of Art (unfilmed)</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">60</container>
	<unittitle>Installation Views, <unitdate>1931-1953, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">61</container>
	<unittitle>Konrad Cramer (1915-1957, undated), <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">62-63</container>
	<unittitle>Florence Ballin Cramer (1929-1944, undated), <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">7</container>
	<container type="folder">64</container>
	<unittitle>Other Artists, <unitdate>1935, 1958, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
</c02>
</c01>


<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 8: </unitid><unittitle>Artwork, <unitdate>1897-1954, undated </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Boxes 8-11; 1.2 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series contains sketchbooks, loose sketches and drawings, original illustrations for children's picture books, textile designs, graphic designs, woodblock and linoleum block prints, printing blocks, examples of textile prints and batik, calligraphy, and an autograph book kept by Florence Ballin as a child containing artwork, poems, and music by its signers.  Most of the artwork is by Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer.  Artwork by others is filed separately.  Artwork is in pencil, graphite, watercolor, gouache, pastel.</p>

<p>Additional sketches by Florence Ballin Cramer can be found in the Writings series.  Examples of  woodblock and linoleum prints and engravings by the Cramers and others in their circle can be found in Printed Materials.  Other sketches are found in the account books in Personal Business Records.  See series descriptions for more details.</p>

<p>Most of the artwork in this series was previously microfilmed in an earlier arrangement on reel 2755.
</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<unittitle>Sketchbooks</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<unittitle>Konrad Cramer</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">1</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>circa 1906-1908</unitdate></unittitle>
	    </did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">2</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>circa 1907</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">3</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>circa 1909</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">4</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>after 1912</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">5</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>1916, 1921</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">6-8</container>
	<unittitle>Dismantled Design Sketchbook, <unitdate>circa 1918, 1920, 1924</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(3 folders)</physdesc>	</did>	<scopecontent><p>(Original Collation)</p></scopecontent>
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">9</container>
	<unittitle>Sketchbook with Notes on Printmaking, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c04>
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">10-11</container>
	<unittitle>Florence Ballin Cramer, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 volumes in 2 folders)</physdesc>    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">12</container>
	<unittitle>Aileen Cramer (daughter), <unitdate>1942</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">13</container>
	<unittitle>Unsigned, <unitdate>1909, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<unittitle>Sketches and Drawings</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<unittitle>Konrad Cramer</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">14</container>
	<unittitle><unitdate>1921, 1923, 1954, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">15-16</container>
	<unittitle>Blackface Cartoons, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c04>
<c04>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">17</container>
	<unittitle>Erotic Drawings, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c04>
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">18</container>
	<unittitle>Florence Ballin Cramer, <unitdate>1925, 1938, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">19-20</container>
	<unittitle>Childhood Drawings of Aileen and Margot Cramer, <unitdate>1924, 1926, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">21</container>
	<unittitle>Caricature of Mayor Goltz of Woodstock by Aimé Titus, <unitdate>1908</unitdate></unittitle>
    </did>	
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<unittitle>Children's Books by Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer</unittitle>
    </did>	
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">22-23</container>
	<unittitle><emph render="italic">Thoughts and Pictures</emph>, <unitdate>1925</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c03>
<c03>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">24</container>
	<unittitle><emph render="italic">A Book for Very Small Children</emph>, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">25-28</container>
	<unittitle>Textile Designs, <unitdate>circa 1918</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(4 folders; see also Box 9 and OV 11)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">29</container>
	<unittitle>Designs for <emph render="italic">Hue and Cry</emph>, <unitdate>1923, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(See OV 10)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">30-31</container>
	<unittitle>Wood and Linoleum Block Prints by the Cramers, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders, including duplicates)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">32-33</container>
	<unittitle>Printing Blocks by the Cramers, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>	</did>	<scopecontent><p>(see also Konrad Cramer's 1916, 1921 Sketchbook for 2 original bookplate printing blocks)</p></scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">34</container>
	<unittitle>Woodblock Prints by Children, <unitdate>1920-1921</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">35</container>
	<unittitle>Textile Samples Designed by Konrad Cramer, <unitdate>circa 1915-1916</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">36</container>
	<unittitle>Undyed Batik made by Konrad Cramer, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also OV 11)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">37</container>
	<unittitle>Calligraphy, <unitdate>1923, 1925, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">38</container>
	<unittitle>Miscellaneous Designs, Sketches, and Prints, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(See also OV 10)</physdesc>	</did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">8</container>
	<container type="folder">39</container>
	<unittitle>Autograph Book of Florence Ballin Cramer, <unitdate>1897-1899</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>	<scopecontent><p>(Contains paintings, drawings, poems, and music by signers)</p></scopecontent>
</c02>

<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">9 (sol)</container>
	<unittitle>Oversized Textile Designs (See Box 8, f28)</unittitle>
    </did>	
</c02>
<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">10 (OV)</container>
	<unittitle>Oversized Artwork (see Box 8, f29 and 38)</unittitle>
    </did>	
</c02>

<c02>
   <did>
	<container type="box">11 (OV)</container>
	<unittitle>Oversized Artwork (See Box 8, f28 and 36) </unittitle>
    </did>	
</c02>

</c01>

</dsc>


<!-- END DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->
</archdesc>
</ead>


