<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "/eadcb/shared/ead/ead.dtd">

<ead audience="external" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
<eadid mainagencycode="DSI-AAA" countrycode="us" url="http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/findingaids/xml/disumarc.xml">disumarc</eadid>

<filedesc>
	<titlestmt>
		<titleproper>Mark di Suvero and di Suvero Family</titleproper>
		<subtitle>A Finding Aid to the Mark di Suvero and di Suvero Family Papers, <date type="inclusive">1934-2005</date>, in the Archives of American Art</subtitle>
		<author>by Jean Fitzgerald</author>
	</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
	<publisher>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</publisher>
	<date type="publication">October 2005</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Stephanie Ashley on
<date>January 07, 2006</date>
</creation>
<langusage><language>English</language></langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>

<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory">
<did>
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
		<corpname>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</corpname>
	</repository>

	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100">Mark di Suvero and di Suvero family</persname>
	</origination>

	<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Mark di Suvero and di Suvero family papers</unittitle>

	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f">1934-2005</unitdate>

	<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a">6.7 linear feet</physdesc>

	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">The collection measures 6.7 linear feet, dates from 1934 to 2005, and documents the career of sculptor Mark di Suvero and family relationships. Found within the papers are biographical material; letters to and from di Suvero family members; scattered writings by di Suvero and Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero, the artist's sister, about Mark di Suvero; drawings; a file on the Socrates Sculpture Park; a file on artist Helen Lessick, an acquaintance of Mark di Suvero; exhibition files; printed material; photographs of the artist, artwork, and members of the di Suvero family; audio and video recordings of interviews with di Suvero; and promotional Tee Shirts.  A portion of this collection is sealed. </abstract>

	<langmaterial>The records are in <language>English</language>.
	</langmaterial>
</did>



<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GO HERE: -->


<bioghist altrender="biography" encodinganalog="545" id="a2">
<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>Mark di Suvero was born September 18, 1933, in Shanghai, China, the son of Matilde Millo di Suvero and Victor E. di Suvero, an Italian diplomat.  He was one of four children:  Victor M., the eldest, Marie Louise, Mark, and the youngest son Henry.  With the outbreak of World War II, the family immigrated to San Francisco, California, in 1941.</p>  
<p>Mark di Suvero studied fine arts and philosophy at the San Francisco City College from 1953 to 1954, and attended the University of California, Santa Barbara, from 1954-1955, where he began creating sculpture.  In 1956, he received a B.A. in Philosophy from the University of California, Berkeley.  The following year, di Suvero moved to New York City to establish a career as a sculptor.</p>
<p>Shortly before his first solo exhibition at the Green Gallery in 1960, di Suvero suffered severe spinal injuries when he was pinned against an elevator shaft in a construction accident.  Initially confined to a wheelchair for two years, di Suvero persevered in overcoming his injuries and continuing his work.</p>  
<p>In protest of the Vietnam War, di Suvero left the United States in 1971, and exhibited his sculpture in Holland and Germany.   A year later, he established a painting and drawing studio in Venice, where he also taught at the Università Internazionale dell'Arte, and, in 1973, he moved to France.  Also during this time, di Suvero married Maria Teresa Capparotta, an architect, whom he later divorced.</p>
<p>The Whitney Museum of American Art honored Mark di Suvero in 1975 with the first retrospective and first American city-wide exhibition of his work, in New York City.  At this time, di Suvero began working with a team in assembling his sculpture, first with Lowell McKegney, and later joined by his nephews Enrico and Matteo Martignoni.</p>

<p>In 1977, di Suvero founded the Athena Foundation to award grants to artists.  In 1986, in conjunction with the Athena Foundation and with Enrico Martignoni, he created the Socrates Sculpture Park in Long Island City, New York, an outdoor space where sculptors are invited to create and exhibit their work. With Marcel Evrard in 1988, di Suvero created a foundation entitled La Vie des Formes (The Life of Forms) in the shipyards at Chalon-sur-Saône, France.  Based upon the model of Socrates Sculpture Park, this organization hosted artists in studio and exhibition spaces at the shipyard and on di Suvero's converted canal barge <emph render="italic">Rêve des Signes</emph>, that was moored alongside. </p>

<p>Included in most major international gallery collections, Mark di Suvero's art work has also been the focus of major solo exhibitions including two at Storm King, and international city-wide exhibitions in Duisberg and Stuttgart in Germany, Chalon-sur-Saône, Paris, Valence, and Nice in France, and Valencia in Spain.  During the summer of 1995, di Suvero was honored with a major installation of seven pieces along the Grand Canal to coincide with the Venice Biennale's 100th anniversary.</p> 

<p>In 1993, Mark di Suvero married Kate Levin, Ph.D., a professor at the City University of New York and Commissioner of the New York Department of Cultural Affairs.  Di Suvero and Levin have a daughter named Veri.  At present, di Suvero maintains studios in Petaluma, California, Long Island City, New York, and Chalon-sur-Saône, France.</p>

</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520" id="a3">
<head>Scope and Content Note</head>
<p>The collection measures 6.7 linear feet (including sealed portions of the collection), dates from 1934 to 2005, and documents the career of sculptor Mark di Suvero and the importance of his family relationships.   Found within the papers are biographical material; letters to and from di Suvero family members; scattered writings by di Suvero and Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero, the artist's sister, about Mark di Suvero; drawings; a file on the Socrates Sculpture Park; a file on artist Helen Lessick, a friend of Mark di Suvero; exhibition files; printed material; photographs of the artist, artwork, and members of the di Suvero family; audio and video recordings of interviews with di Suvero; and promotional Tee Shirts.  

57 folders of Mark di Suvero's letters to his brother Henry are sealed, as are 3 folders of letters to his sister Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero. Also sealed are a typescript for a book by di Suvero, a play script by Henry di Suvero, and family photographs, per the donor's request. All series contain annotations by the donor, Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero.</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351$b" id="a5">
<head>Arrangement</head>
<p>The collection has been arranged into 11 series: </p>
<list>
<item>Series 1:  Biographical Material, 1941-2004 (Box 1; 4 folders)</item>
<item>Series 2:  Letters, 1956-2005, undated (Box 1, 7, and <emph render="bold">Sealed Box 6, 8, OV 10;</emph> 1.6 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 3:  Notes and Writings, 1961-2005, undated (Box 1, and <emph render="bold">Sealed Box 6</emph>;  15 folders)</item>
<item>Series 4:  Drawings, 1983, undated (Box 1; 1 folder)</item>
<item>Series 5:  Socrates Sculpture Park File, 1985-2004, undated (Box 1-2, 7; 0.6 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 6:  Helen Lessick File, 1986-2004 (Box 2, 7; 6 folders)</item>
<item>Series 7:  Exhibition Files, 1975-2003 (Box 2-3, 7; 1.4 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 8:  Printed Material, 1958-2004, undated (Box 3-4, 7, OV 9; 1.4 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 9:  Photographs, 1934-2004, undated (Box 4-5, <emph render="bold">Sealed Box 6;</emph> 37 folders)</item>
<item>Series 10:  Audio and Video Recordings, 1982-1994, undated (Box 5; 7 folders)</item>
<item>Series 11:  Promotional Tee Shirts, 1978-2001 (Box 7; 2 folders)</item>
</list>
<p>All series have been arranged chronologically.  Unrestricted material is housed in Boxes 1-5, 7 (Sol), and OV 9.  <emph render="bold">Sealed material is housed in Boxes 6, 8 (Sol), and OV 10.  </emph>
</p>

</arrangement>


<!-- END TOP LEVEL METADATA -->

<!-- CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS GO HERE: -->

<controlaccess id="a12">
<head>Index Terms</head>
<p>This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.</p>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Lessick, Helen</persname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Socrates Sculpture Park</corpname>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects-Topical:</head>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York</subject>
</controlaccess>


<controlaccess>
<head>Types of Materials:</head>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Photographs</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Sound recordings</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Slides (photographs)</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Video recordings</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Works of art</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Drawings</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Interviews</genreform>
</controlaccess>

</controlaccess>


<!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->

<!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION GOES HERE: -->

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541" id="a19">
<head>Provenance</head>
<p>The Mark di Suvero and di Suvero family papers were donated in 2004 and 2005 by Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero, the artist's sister. After donation, the donor requested that a portion of the papers be sealed (no access) until 2033. The sealed portion includes family letters, a typescript for a book, a play script, and family photographs.  </p>
</acqinfo>

<accessrestrict id="a14" encodinganalog="506">
<head>Restrictions on Access</head>
<p>A portion of the the collection is open for research, Boxes 1-5, 7, and OV 9. Use requires an appointment. <emph render="bold">A portion of the collection (Boxes 6, 8, OV 10) is SEALED and unavailable for research. </emph></p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="a15">
<head>Ownership and Literary Rights</head>
<p>The Mark di Suvero and di Suvero family papers are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.  Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship.  The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite encodinganalog="510" id="a18">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Mark di Suvero and di Suvero family papers, 1934-2005.  Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
</prefercite>

<processinfo encodinganalog="583" id="a20">
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>The papers were processed by Jean Fitzgerald in October 2005.  After processing, the donor requested that a portion of the collection be sealed, thus the sealed boxes have box numbers integrated with the rest of the boxes. </p>
</processinfo>


<!-- END ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->


<!-- START DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->


<dsc type="combined" id="a23">
<head>Series Descriptions/Container Listing</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 1: </unitid><unittitle>Biographical Material, <unitdate>1941-2004</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 4 folders)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series consists of biographical accounts for various members of the di Suvero family and school records for Mark di Suvero.  The curricula vitae were written by Mark di Suvero. </p> 
</scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Biographical Accounts for di Suvero Family Members, <unitdate>1993-2004</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Curriculum Vitae Written by Mark di Suvero, <unitdate>1984-1997</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Report Cards for Mark di Suvero, <unitdate>1941-1948</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>School Attendance Certificate for Mark di Suvero, <unitdate>1944</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 2: </unitid><unittitle>Letters, <unitdate>1956-2005, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1, 7, and <emph render="bold">Sealed Box 6, 8, OV 10;</emph> 1.6 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>The majority of the letters are from Mark di Suvero to his brother Henry and sister Marie Louise, including 60 SEALED folders of letters and several SEALED oversized letters. There are also some scattered letters to friends and colleagues including a letter containing a printed description of di Suvero's New York Court of Appeals case concerning his accident. Several of these letters are illustrated with drawings of ideas for sculpture.  Other letters are those written by members of the di Suvero family to each other, and letters received from various friends and colleagues. </p> 
</scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Letters from di Suvero Family Members (see also Box 7), 
<unitdate>1966-2005, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(27 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">6 SEALED</container>
<unittitle>SEALED Letters from Mark di Suvero to Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero (see also SEALED Box 8 ),  <unitdate>1960-1964</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(3 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">6 SEALED</container>
<unittitle>SEALED Letters from Mark di Suvero to Henry di Suvero (see also SEALED Box 8, OV 10), <unitdate>1956-2001</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(57 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">7 (sol)</container>
<unittitle>Oversized letter from Mark di Suvero to Marie Louise Martignoni
di Suvero, <unitdate>1987-1988</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">8 (sol)SEALED </container>
<unittitle>SEALED Oversized letter from Mark di Suvero to Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero, <unitdate>1961</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">8 (sol) SEALED</container>
<unittitle>SEALED Oversized letters from Mark di Suvero to Henry di Suvero, <unitdate>1958-1999,
undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">OV 10 SEALED</container>
<unittitle>SEALED Oversized letters from Mark di Suvero to Henry di Suvero, <unitdate>1972, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 3: </unitid><unittitle>Notes and Writings, <unitdate>1961-2005, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1, <emph render="bold">Sealed Box 6</emph>; 15 folders)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series primarily consists of Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero's notes and writings.   The files containing notes for her  lecture at the University of New Mexico include 2 photographs and 80 slides of Mark di Suvero's art work.  There are also writings by Mark, Henry, and Victor di Suvero.</p> 
</scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Poems by Mark di Suvero, <unitdate>1961, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Typescripts of Poems Written from 1938 to 1953 by Victor di Suvero, <unitdate>1998</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Notes and Writings by Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero, <unitdate>1982-2005</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Draft Press Release for the Portland Museum, <unitdate>1982</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Notes for Lecture at University of New Mexico,  <unitdate>1989</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Proposal to Cast in Bronze Gutzon Borglum's Bust
of Adolph Bandelier, <unitdate>1991-1993</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Notes Concerning Mark di Suvero Art Work Executed
Between 1954 and 2004, <unitdate>2005</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Notes Concerning Decades of Family Events,
<unitdate>2004</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(6 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">6 SEALED</container>
<unittitle>SEALED Typescript Draft for a Proposed Book by Mark di Suvero, <unitdate>circa 1998</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">6 SEALED</container>
<unittitle>SEALED Play Script, <emph render="italic">The Ballad of Rachel Corrie</emph>, by Henry di Suvero, <unitdate>2003</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 4: </unitid><unittitle>Drawings, <unitdate>1983, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 1 folder)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Three small ink sketches by Mark di Suvero are designs for sculpture.</p> 
</scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Ink Sketches, <unitdate>1983, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 5: </unitid><unittitle>Socrates Sculpture Park File, <unitdate>1985-2004, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1-2, 7; 0.6 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series contains material concerning the Socrates Sculpture Park, an outdoor space where sculptors are invited to create and exhibit their work, created through the Athena Foundation. The photographs include one showing New York Mayor Koch presenting co-founder Enrico Martignoni with an award for the Park.  Artifacts include two matchbooks and a tee shirt advertising the Park.</p> 
</scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Letters, <unitdate>1985-1996</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Typescript of the Proposal, <unitdate>1988</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Inventory and Analysis Report, <unitdate>1988</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Notes and Writings, <unitdate>1986-2001, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Clippings, <unitdate>1985-2001</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Press Packet, <unitdate>1985-1986</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Press Releases, <unitdate>1986-2003</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs (see also Box 7),
<unitdate>1986-2004</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(9 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Brochure for the Athena Foundation, <unitdate>1986</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Brochures for Socrates Sculpture Park, <unitdate>1990-1992</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Printed Material, <unitdate>1986-2004</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Photographs, <unitdate>1986-1990</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<unittitle>Videotape <emph render="italic">Socrates Sculpture Park</emph>, <unitdate>1986</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<unittitle>Artifacts (see Also Box 7), <unitdate>2003, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">7 (sol)</container>
<unittitle>Oversized Exhibition Announcement from the Socrates Sculpture Park
File, <unitdate>1987</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">7 (sol)</container>
<unittitle>Socrates Sculpture Park tee shirt, <unitdate>2003</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 6: </unitid><unittitle>Helen Lessick File,  <unitdate>1986-2004</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 2, 7; 6 folders)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series contains miscellaneous material relating to artist Helen Lessick, an Athena grant-funded artist and friend of Mark di Suvero and the Martignoni family, who exhibited her work at the Socrates Sculpture Park in its early days, and at Chalon-sur-Saône's <emph render="italic">La Vie des Formes.</emph></p> 
</scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<unittitle>Letters (see also Box 7), <unitdate>1990-2003</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, <unitdate>1987-2004</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Printed Material, <unitdate>1986-2003</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<unittitle>Baseball Cards Created by Helen Lessick, <unitdate>1999</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<unittitle>Bookmarks Created by Helen Lessick, <unitdate>2003</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">7 (sol)</container>
<unittitle>Oversized Illustrated Letter from Helen Lessick File, <unitdate>1990</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 7: </unitid><unittitle>Exhibition Files, <unitdate>1975-2003</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 2-3, 7; 1.4 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>The exhibition files contain miscellaneous material relating to specific exhibitions or installations by Mark di Suvero.  Most files contain printed materials, catalogs, announcements, notes, a few essays, letters, and photographs.   Two of the exhibition files also contain video recordings:  La Biennale di Venezia, XLCI International Art Exhibition, Venice, Italy, 1994-1996; Storm King Art Center, Mountainville, New York, 1995-1996.</p> 
</scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<unittitle>Whitney Museum of American Art, New York, <unitdate>1975-1976</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(7 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<unittitle>Storm King Art Center, Mountainville, New York,  <unitdate>1985</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(7 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<unittitle>Württembergischer Kunstverein, Stuttgart, Germany,  <unitdate>1988</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(5 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<unittitle>Musée des Beaux-Arts, Valence, France, <unitdate>1989-1991</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(10 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<unittitle>Musée d'Art Moderne et d'Art Contemporain, Nice, France, 
<unitdate>1991</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(4 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<unittitle>Unveiling of <emph render="italic">L'Illume (Erleuchtung)</emph>, Parliament Building, Bonn, Germany, <unitdate>1992</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(5 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<unittitle>Centre Julio González, Valencian Institute of Modern Art (IVAM),
Valencia, Spain, <unitdate>1994-1995</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<unittitle>La Biennale di Venezia, XLCI International Art Exhibition,
Venice, Italy, <unitdate>1994-1996</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(7 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<unittitle>Dedication of <emph render="italic">Sea Change</emph>, South Beach Park, San Francisco, California,
<unitdate>1995</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(7 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<unittitle>Storm King Art Center, Mountainville, New York, <unitdate>1995-1996</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(8 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<unittitle>Mark di Suvero in Paris Exhibition, Paris, France, <unitdate>1997-1998</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(7 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<unittitle>Unveiling of <emph render="italic">Tyne Anew</emph>,  <unitdate>1999</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<unittitle>Works from a Private Collection, Danese Gallery, New York, New York,
<unitdate>2000</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(4 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<unittitle>Installation of <emph render="italic">Beppe</emph>, University of Missouri at St. Louis and Laumeier Sculpture Park, St. Louis, Missouri, <unitdate>2003</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(5 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">7 (sol)</container>
<unittitle>Oversized Letter from Mark di Suvero to Henry di Suvero, from the
La Biennale di Venezia Exhibition File, <unitdate>1994</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">7 (sol)</container>
<unittitle>Oversized Posters from a Press Packet in Exhibition File for
Mark di Suvero in Paris, <unitdate>1997</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 8: </unitid><unittitle>Printed Material, <unitdate>1958-2004, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 3-4, 7, OV 9; 1.4 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series consists of printed material that does not directly relate to specific exhibitions.  Exhibition announcements include a poster for di Suvero's first solo exhibition at the Green Gallery in 1960.  Exhibition catalogs for <emph render="italic">The Hands</emph>, 1996-1997, and for the  Orange County Museum of Art solo exhibition, 1998, are autographed.</p> 
</scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<unittitle>Clippings (see also Box 7), <unitdate>1960-2004, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(33 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<unittitle>Press Releases, <unitdate>1966-2000</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Mark di Suvero (see also OV 9), 
<unitdate>1958-1986</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(9 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Mark di Suvero, 
<unitdate>1987-2004</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(18 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others (see also Box 7), 
<unitdate>1976-1995</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(3 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<unittitle>Lecture Announcements, <unitdate>2000-2001</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<unittitle>Brochures for Miscellaneous Art Galleries, <unitdate>1973-2004, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(4 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<unittitle>Brochures for the Sale of Art Work, <unitdate>1973-1993</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<unittitle>Travel Brochures, <unitdate>1990-1995, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Brochures, <unitdate>1991-2001</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<unittitle>Note Cards with Photographs of Art Work by Mark di Suvero,
<unitdate>1996-2001, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<unittitle>Postcards with Photographs of Art Work by Mark di Suvero, <unitdate>1998, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Picture Postcards, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<unittitle>Booklet <emph render="italic">Summer War Haiku</emph> by Jack Crimmins, <unitdate>2002</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<unittitle>Book <emph render="italic">New York Painting and Sculpture: 1940-1970</emph> by Henry Geldzahler,
<unitdate>1969</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Printed Material, <unitdate>1993-2000, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">7 (sol)</container>
<unittitle>Oversized Clippings, <unitdate>1964-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">7 (sol)</container>
<unittitle>Oversized Exhibition Announcement for Others, <unitdate>1988</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">OV 9</container>
<unittitle>Oversized Exhibition Announcements for Mark di Suvero, <unitdate>1960-1986</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 9: </unitid><unittitle>Photographs, <unitdate>1934-2004, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 4-5, <emph render="bold">Sealed Box 6;</emph> 37 folders)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Photographs are of Mark di Suvero, members of the di Suvero family, di Suvero's studios and art work.  Many of the photographs depict a combination of all these elements, so they have been organized into one chronology in order to maintain the sense of each occasion. The CD-ROM of slides and the slides of di Suvero's work belonged to friend and dealer Richard Bellamy.</p> 
</scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<unittitle>Photographs of the di Suvero Family and Mark di Suvero's Art Work,
<unitdate>1934-2004</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(14 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<unittitle>CD-ROM of Mark di Suvero's Art Work Executed from the 1960s to
1990s, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<unittitle>Slides of Mark di Suvero's Art Work Executed from the 1960s to 1990s, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">6 SEALED</container>
<unittitle>SEALED Photographs of the di Suvero Family and Mark di Suvero's Art Work, <unitdate>1963-1998, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(19 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">6 SEALED</container>
<unittitle>SEALED Miscellaneous Negatives, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 10: </unitid><unittitle>Audio and Video Recordings, <unitdate>1982-1994, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 5; 7 folders)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series presents aural and visual insights into Mark di Suvero's work.  With the exception of <emph render="italic">La Vie des Formes</emph>, all videotapes contain interviews of Mark di Suvero.</p> 
</scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<unittitle>Audio-Cassette Lecture by Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero Speaking
about Mark di Suvero, Portland Museum of Art, Oregon <unitdate>1982</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<unittitle>	Videotape <emph render="italic">Mark di Suvero: Rêve des Signes (Dream of Signs)</emph>, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<unittitle>Videotape <emph render="italic">Storm King</emph>, <unitdate>1987</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<unittitle>Videotape <emph render="italic">La Vie des Formes</emph> by Dominique Evrard, <unitdate>1988-1989</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<unittitle>Videotape <emph render="italic">In the Steel: A Portrait of Mark di Suvero</emph>, <unitdate>1991</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<unittitle>Videotape <emph render="italic">Sculptors at Storm King</emph>, <unitdate>1992</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<unittitle>Videotape <emph render="italic">Echt Wahr Träume (Genuinely True Dreams)</emph> by Nina Hagar, <unitdate>1994</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 11: </unitid><unittitle>Promotional Tee Shirts, <unitdate>1978-2001</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 7; 2 folders)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>These Tee Shirts are promotional items from an unveiling event for Mark di Suvero's sculpture Potowatami, and from a charity event.</p> 
</scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">7 (sol)</container>
<unittitle>Tee Shirt from the Unveiling of <emph render="italic">Potowatami</emph>, <unitdate>1978</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">7 (sol)</container>
<unittitle>Tee Shirt from the Art Walk 2001 for the Venice Family Clinic, <unitdate>2001</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

</dsc>


<!-- END DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->
</archdesc>
</ead>

