<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "/eadcb/shared/ead/ead.dtd">

<ead audience="external" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
<eadid mainagencycode="DSI-AAA" countrycode="us" url="http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/findingaids/xml/.xml"></eadid>

<filedesc>
	<titlestmt>
		<titleproper>La Vern Frank-Rush papers regarding the WPA Art Center in Sioux City, Iowa</titleproper>
		<subtitle>A Finding Aid to the La Vern Frank-Rush papers regarding the WPA Art Center in Sioux City, Iowa, <date type="inclusive">1936-2007,</date> <date type="bulk"> bulk 1936-1942</date>, in the Archives of American Art</subtitle>
		<author>by Jivan Kaur Soverall</author>
		<sponsor></sponsor>
	</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
	<publisher>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</publisher>
	<date type="publication">June 18, 2009</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Jivan Kaur Soverall on
<date>June 18, 2009</date>
</creation>
<langusage><language>English</language></langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>

<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory">
<did>
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
		<corpname>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</corpname>
	</repository>

	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100">Frank-Rush, La Vern</persname>
	</origination>

	<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">La Vern Frank-Rush papers</unittitle>

	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f">1936-2007, bulk 1936-1942</unitdate>

	<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a">0.2 linear feet</physdesc>

	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">The La Vern Frank-Rush papers regarding the WPA Art Center in Sioux City, Iowa, measure 0.2 linear feet and date from 1936 to 2007 with the bulk dated 1936 to 1942. Two scrapbooks compiled by Frank-Rush between 1936 and 1942 contain introductory and concluding statements added by her in 2006. A memoir, circa 2007, documents activities, achievements, staff, and participants of the WPA Art Center in Sioux City, Iowa. Also included is a CD-ROM with images of the scrapbooks and memoir, along with seven images of Frank-Rush's artwork.</abstract>

<!-- ONLY USE LANGMATERIAL TO NOTE LANGUAGES OTHER THAN OR IN ADDITION TO ENGLISH -->
	
	<langmaterial label="Language of Materials:"><language>English</language>
	</langmaterial>
</did>



<!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION GOES HERE: -->

<acqinfo encodinganalog="561" id="a19">
<head>Provenance</head>
<p>The La Vern Frank-Rush papers regarding the WPA Art Center in Sioux City, Iowa, were donated by La Vern Frank-Rush in 2007.</p>
</acqinfo>

<separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 0" id="a7">
<head></head>
<p></p>
</separatedmaterial>

<originalsloc encodinganalog="535" id="a24">
<head></head>
<p></p>
</originalsloc>

<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 1" id="a6">
<head>Related Material</head>
<p>The Archives of American Art houses microfilm copies of selected official WPA records of interest to art historians. The following microfilm, available at AAA ofices and through interlibrary loan, contain additional documentation of the WPA Art Center in Sioux city, Iowa: </p> 

<p>Records of the WPA, General Correspondence files include selected documents pertaining to the Federal Art Project in Iowa. (Reel DC 76, frames 317-2309)</p>

<p>WPA Photograph Collection contains 18 photographs of the Sioux City Art Center, classes, projects, puppet workshops, exhibitions, and marionettes. (Reel 1178, frames 0011-0044)</p>

<p>Iowa Community Art Centers, 1938-1939, features 13 photographs of the Sioux City Art Center. (Reel NDA 16, frames 290-317)</p>
</relatedmaterial>

<altformavail id="a17" encodinganalog="530">
<head></head>
<p></p>
</altformavail>

<processinfo encodinganalog="583" id="a20">
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>The collection was processed by Jivan Kaur Soverall in June 2009.</p>
</processinfo>

<prefercite encodinganalog="510" id="a18">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>La Vern Frank-Rush papers regarding the WPA Art Center in Sioux City, Iowa, 1936-2007. Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
</prefercite>

<accessrestrict id="a14" encodinganalog="506">
<head>Restrictions on Access.</head>
<p>Use of original material requires an appointment.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="a15">
<head>Ownership and Literary Rights</head>
<p>The La Vern Frank-Rush papers regarding the WPA Art Center in Sioux City, Iowa, are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
</userestrict>

<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="a22">
<head></head>
<p></p>
</accruals>


<!-- END ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->

<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GO HERE: -->



<bioghist altrender="biography" encodinganalog="545" id="a2">
<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>La Vern Frank-Rush (b. 1918) worked at the WPA Art Center in Sioux City, Iowa, from its opening in 1938 until 1941, first as a volunteer and then as an employee. During this time she compiled two scrapbooks about the Art Center. Circa 2007, she wrote a memoir that focused on the Art Center. </p>

<p>After finishing junior high school, La Vern Frank-Rush won a contest that enabled her to attend free summer art classes at the Sioux City Public Library. The instructor, Roy Langley, had a lasting influence on the aspiring artist. </p>

<p>The WPA Art Center in Sioux City, Iowa, offered free exhibits, lectures, and art classes to a community which otherwise would not have had such opportunities. The Art Center organized plays, marionette shows, and exhibitions. It also provided classes in ceramics, puppetry, and watercolors; hundreds of children and adults were enrolled, and the weekly schedule include 32 different offerings. Performances were always well received, and record crowds gathered to view exhibits.</p>

<p>Frank-Rush started working as a volunteer at the WPA Art Center in Sioux City, Iowa, soon after it opened in 1938, and began compiling a scrapbook about the Art Center. She studied painting and printmaking with the various artists who taught there. Eventually, Frank-Rush became an employee and served as an instructor, art teacher, and librarian for the Art Center through 1942.</p>

<p>La Vern Frank and George Rush, who also worked at the Art Center, married in 1943. Three days after their marriage, Rush was assigned to the Engineer Corps at Fort Belvoir, Virginia.  Frank-Rush served in the Civil Service War Department in Washington, D.C., but soon was able to transfer to Fort Belvoir. In 1953, the couple moved to Lincoln, Nebraska, where she taught art at the University of Nebraska from 1956 through 1966. Frank-Rush was certified to teach the care and raising of houseplants, helped organize the Nebraska Herbal Society, and presented herbal and plant demonstrations at South East Community College in Lincoln. Since retiring in 1980, she has lived quietly in Oregon. </p>
<!-- add additional <p></p> tags as necessary -->
<chronlist>
<listhead>
<head01></head01>
<head02></head02>
</listhead>

<chronitem>
<date></date>
<event></event>
</chronitem>
</chronlist>
<!-- Delete the above, beginning with <chronlist> and ending with </chronlist> if the bioghist is text only: -->
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520" id="a3">
<head>Scope and Content Note</head>

<p>The La Vern Frank-Rush papers regarding the WPA Art Center in Sioux City, Iowa, measure 0.2 linear feet and date from 1936 to 2007 with the bulk dated 1936 to 1942. Two scrapbooks compiled by Frank-Rush between 1936 and 1942 contain introductory and concluding statements added by her in 2006. A memoir, circa 2007, documents activities, achievements, staff, and participants of the WPA Art Center in Sioux City, Iowa. Also included is a CD-ROM with images of the scrapbooks and memoir.  </p>

<p>Two scrapbooks document the Sioux City Art Center's founding by the WPA in 1938, its activities, and programs. The Center, which still exists today, is one of four WPA art centers in Iowa to survive without interruption. Photographs record exhibits, staff members, students, and work produced at the Art Center and also depict Frank-Rush's personal life. </p>

<p>The CD-ROM  is a digitized version of the collection. Images on the CD-ROM do not completely reproduce the scrapbooks. For instance, although scrapbook volume 2 contains the complete script for <emph render="italic">The Shoe Bears</emph>, the entire play does not appear on the CD-ROM.</p>

<p>Frank-Rush's memoir and scrapbooks provide insight into how the WPA Art Center impacted her  as well as the larger community. In her own words, the collection "reveals the personality of the Sioux City Art Center." A small selection of her artwork, preserved on CD-ROM, lends a view into the late 1930s. </p>
<!-- add additional <p></p> tags as necessary -->

<!-- If you have a non-series-related index provide a link to the index here: 

<note><p><ref target="index1"></ref></p></note>  

-->

</scopecontent>

<arrangement encodinganalog="351$b" id="a5">
<head>Arrangement</head>
<p>The collection is organized into 3 series:</p>
<list>
<item>Series 1: Scrapbooks, 1936-2007 (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)</item>
<item>Series 2: Memoir, circa 2007 (Box 1; 1 folder)</item>
<item>Series 3: CD-ROM, circa 2007 (Box 1; 1 folder)</item>
</list>
</arrangement>


<!-- END TOP LEVEL METADATA -->

<!-- CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS GO HERE: -->


<controlaccess id="a12">
<head>Names and Subject Terms</head>
<p>This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:</p>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>

<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh"></persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh"></persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh"></persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh"></persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh"></persname>

<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">United States.--Works Projects Administration</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">United States.--Works Progress Administration</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh"></corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh"></corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh"></corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="611" source="lcsh"></corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="611" source="lcsh"></corpname>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects-Topical:</head>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Art centers--Iowa--Sioux City</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh"></subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh"></subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh"></subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh"></subject>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects-Geographical:</head>
<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh"></geogname>
<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh"></geogname>
<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh"></geogname>
<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh"></geogname>
<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh"></geogname>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Types of Materials:</head>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">CD-ROMs</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Memoirs</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Photographs</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Scrapbooks</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh"></genreform>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Names:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh"></persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh"></persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh"></persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh"></persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh"></persname>

<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh"></corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh"></corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh"></corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh"></corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh"></corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="711" source="lcsh"></corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="711" source="lcsh"></corpname>
</controlaccess>

</controlaccess>


<!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->

<!-- START DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->


<dsc type="combined" id="a23">
<head>Series Descriptions/Container Listing</head>

<!-- use this format if you have series only, no subseries -->
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 1: </unitid><unittitle>Scrapbooks,<unitdate>1936-2007, undated.</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>The scrapbooks contain a variety of material: newspaper articles and publicity clippings, black and white photographs, recital and exhibition programs, correspondence, original art work by Art Center students, pamphlets, class and workshop schedules, personal comments, bulletins, flyers, surveys of activities, invitations, lists of artists in Sioux City and vicinity, and Christmas and thank you cards. Also found are the script and program for a three-act play, <emph render="italic">The Shoe Bears</emph>, and the program for a performance of <emph render="italic">Uncle Tom's Cabin</emph>.</p>

<p>Frank-Rush collected articles from two newspapers in order to make the scrapbooks. This was her personal copy; duplicates were presented to the Central Library in Sioux City and to the regional WPA office. Items pre-dating the Art Center concern Frank-Rush's participation in an art contest for a scholarship.</p>

<arrangement>
<p>Both scrapbooks appear on a CD-ROM (Series 3).</p>
</arrangement></scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">1-2</container>
<unittitle>Scrapbook Volume 1,<unitdate>1936-2007</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders; removed from 3-ring binder)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">3-4</container>
<unittitle>Scrapbook Volume 2,<unitdate>1936-circa 2007</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders; removed from 3-ring binder)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 2:</unitid><unittitle>Memoir,<unitdate>circa 2007</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 1 folder)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p></p>

<p>La Vern Frank-Rush's well narrated 47-page memoir centers on her experiences and activities at the Art Center in Sioux City, Iowa. Her various jobs and salaries, Art Center instructors and friends are mentioned, and she recalls the Great Depression, Dust Bowl phenomenon, World War II, and difficulties in paying for food, shelter, and tuition.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<arrangement>
<p>The memoir is available on CD-ROM (Series 3).</p>
</arrangement>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>How the WPA Art Center shaped my life between two wars,<unitdate>circa 2007</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(1 folder)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 3:</unitid><unittitle>CD-ROM,<unitdate>circa 2007</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 1 folder)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 

<p>The CD-ROM contains scans of both scrapbooks and the memoir. Also included are images of 5 paintings by La Vern Frank-Rush (<emph render="italic">Downtown</emph>, undated; <emph render="italic">Grocery Orders</emph>, 1942; <emph render="italic">Downtown Rooftops</emph>, undated; <emph render="italic">Railroad</emph>, circa 1938, and <emph render="italic">Midwest Factory</emph>, 1941); a watercolor (<emph render="italic">Old Houses (from a Sioux City Alley)</emph>, 1939); and a lithograph (<emph render="italic">Window Shopping</emph>, 1942). The original artwork is not a part of the collection. </p> 

<p>The CD-ROM  is a digitized version of the collection, produced by Phyllis Wrynn, director of the Park Slope Art Gallery in Brooklyn, New York, which specialises in the art of the WPA Federal Art Project and American mid-century art and design.  Images on the CD-ROM do not completely reproduce the scrapbooks.  For instance, although the complete script for <emph render="italic">The Shoe Bears</emph> is found in volume 2, the entire play does not appear on the CD-ROM.</p></scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>LaVern Frank-Rush: Sioux City WPA Art Center Scrapbook, Memoir, and Images,<unitdate>circa 2007</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(1 folder; 1 CD-ROM)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>
</dsc>

</archdesc>
</ead>

