<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "/eadcb/shared/ead/ead.dtd">

<ead audience="external" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
<eadid mainagencycode="DSI-AAA" countrycode="us" url="http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/findingaids/xml/garfmoll.xml">garfmoll</eadid>

<filedesc>
	<titlestmt>
		<titleproper>Mollie Garfield</titleproper>
		<subtitle>A Finding Aid to the Mollie Garfield papers regarding President James Garfield, <date type="inclusive">1874-1883</date>, in the Archives of American Art</subtitle>
		<author>by Erin Corley</author>
		<sponsor>Funding for the processing and digitization of this collection was provided by the Terra Foundation for American Art. </sponsor>
	</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
	<publisher>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</publisher>
	<date type="publication">August 28, 2007</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Erin Corley on
<date>August 28, 2007</date>
</creation>
<langusage><language>English</language></langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>

<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory">
<did>
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
		<corpname>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</corpname>
	</repository>

	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100">Garfield, Mollie</persname>
	</origination>

	<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Mollie Garfield papers regarding President James Garfield</unittitle>

	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f">1874-1883</unitdate>

	<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a">19 items </physdesc>

	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">The Mollie Garfield papers regarding her father President James Garfield date from 1874 to 1883 and consist primarily of an illustrated memorial album presented to Mollie after the assassination of her father in 1881.  The album contains 26 signed pencil sketches, ink drawings, and watercolors of various subjects by American painters and illustrators, including James Carter Beard, Harry Fenn, William Henry Holmes, Joseph Pennell, and others.  Also found are a few items of correspondence and notes regarding the album and the artists, and a few scattered miscellaneous documents from the 1870s.  </abstract>

<!-- ONLY USE LANGMATERIAL TO NOTE LANGUAGES OTHER THAN OR IN ADDITION TO ENGLISH -->
</did>



<!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION GOES HERE: -->

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541" id="a19">
<head>Provenance</head>
<p>The collection was donated in 1970 by Mrs. Herbert (Ruth) Feis, daughter of Mollie Garfield.</p>
</acqinfo>

<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 1" id="a6">
<head>Related Material</head>
<p>The Mary Garfield Stanley-Brown papers, 1881-1967, are located at the Western Reserve Historical Society, Cleveland, Ohio.</p>
</relatedmaterial>

<altformavail id="a17" encodinganalog="530">
<head>Alternative Forms Available</head>
<p>The collection was digitized in 2007 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website.</p>
</altformavail>

<processinfo encodinganalog="583" id="a20">
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>The Mollie Garfield papers regarding President James Garfield were microfilmed on reel 865, and the album was conserved in 1989. The collection was fully processed by Erin Corley and digitized in 2007 with funding provided by the Terra Foundation for American Art.</p>
</processinfo>

<prefercite encodinganalog="510" id="a18">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Mollie Garfield papers regarding President James Garfield, 1874-1883. Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
</prefercite>

<accessrestrict id="a14" encodinganalog="506">
<head>Restrictions on Access</head>
<p>The collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="a15">
<head>Ownership and Literary Rights</head>
<p>The Mollie Garfield papers regarding President James Garfield is owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
</userestrict>


<!-- END ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->

<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GO HERE: -->

<bioghist altrender="biography" encodinganalog="545" id="a2">
<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>Mary "Mollie" Garfield (1867-1947) was born in Washington, D.C. to James A. Garfield and Lucretia Rudolph Garfield.  She was 14 when her father became President of the United States in January, 1881.  On July 2, James Garfield was shot at Union Station in Washington, D.C. and Mollie and her mother were present when he died of his wounds on September 19.  Mollie Garfield's education included Miss Mittleberger's School in Cleveland, Ohio and one semester at Miss Porter's Finishing School in Farmington, Connecticut.  She lived with her mother at the Garfield family home, Lawnfield, in Mentor, Ohio until her marriage in 1888 to Joseph Stanley-Brown, who had been her father's private secretary.  She died in Pasadena, California at the age of 80.</p>
<!-- add additional <p></p> tags as necessary -->

<!-- Delete the above, beginning with <chronlist> and ending with </chronlist> if the bioghist is text only: -->
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520" id="a3"> 
<head>Scope and Content Note</head>
<p>The Mollie Garfield papers regarding her father President James Garfield date from 1874 to 1883 and consist primarily of an illustrated memorial album presented to Mollie after the assassination of her father in 1881.  The album contains 26 signed pencil sketches, ink drawings, and watercolors of various subjects by American artists.  Also found are a few items of correspondence and notes regarding the album and the artists, and a few scattered miscellaneous documents from the 1870s. </p>    
<!-- add additional <p></p> tags as necessary -->
</scopecontent>

<arrangement encodinganalog="351$b" id="a5">
<head>Arrangement</head>
<p>Due to the small size of this collection, there is only one series consisting of five folders of 19 items. Items are arranged chronologically.</p>
</arrangement>



<!-- END TOP LEVEL METADATA -->

<!-- CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS GO HERE: -->


<controlaccess id="a12">
<head>Names and Subject Terms</head>
<p>This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms: </p>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>

<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Garfield, James A. (James Abram), 1831-1881</persname>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Types of Materials:</head>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Works of art</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Presentation albums</genreform>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Names:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Fenn, Harry, 1838-1911</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Holmes, William Henry, 1846-1933</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Pennell, Joseph, 1857-1926</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Beard, James Carter, 1837-1913</persname>

</controlaccess>

</controlaccess>


<!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->

<!-- START DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->


<dsc type="combined" id="a23">
<head>Series Descriptions/Container Listing</head>

<!-- use this format if you have series only, no subseries -->
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 1: </unitid><unittitle>Mollie Garfield papers regarding President James Garfield, <unitdate>1874-1883 </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 19 items)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>An illustrated memorial album presented to Mollie Garfield after the assassination of her father President James Garfield in 1881.  The album contains 26 signed pencil sketches, ink drawings, and watercolors of various subjects by American artists.  Among the painters and illustrators contributing to the album were James Carter Beard, Daniel Beard, Francis Lathrop, Frederick Dielman, Michael Woolf, W. H. Drake, William Hamilton Gibson, William Henry Holmes, Walter Shirlaw, Henry Sandham, Joseph Pennell, Harry Fenn, Allen Redwood, M. J. Burns, W. Taber, J. M. Nugent, Alfred Brennan, and others.</p>  <p> Also found are a few letters regarding the album, including a letter from Robert U. Johnson of Century Magazine to Colonel Rockwell, a friend of President Garfield, discussing how the album is being circulated to artists and apologizing for being slow to return it.  Johnson also enclosed several autographs to present to Miss Garfield.  Other correspondence includes a letter to Colonel Rockwell from A. W. Drake about one of the contributing artists, Allen Redwood, and Redwood's letter to Drake about the album.  Other items include an unidentified person's handwritten notes on each of the contributing artists, and four earlier letters and four poems from the 1870s which were probably kept within the pages of the album as autograph items. </p>    
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Illustrated Memorial Album, <unitdate>1882-1883</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Photographs of Album Pages (done by AAA), <unitdate>undated  </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Not scanned)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence Regarding Memorial Album, <unitdate>1883</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Notes on Artists, circa <unitdate>1883</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Letters and Poems, <unitdate>1874, circa 1870s-1883</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
<!-- use this format if you have series and subseries -->

<!-- use this format if you have series, subseries and sub-subseries -->


<!-- END DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->

<!-- OPTIONAL ARCHDESC ELEMENTS -->

<!-- use odd for indexes -->
<!-- END OPTIONAL ARCHDESC ELEMENTS -->


</archdesc>
</ead>





