<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "/eadcb/shared/ead/ead.dtd">

<ead audience="external" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
<eadid mainagencycode="DSI-AAA" countrycode="us" url="http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/findingaids/xml/holtcarl.xml">holtcarl</eadid>

<filedesc>
	<titlestmt>
		<titleproper>Carl Holty</titleproper>
		<subtitle>A Finding Aid to the Carl Holty Papers, <date type="inclusive">circa 1860s-1972</date> <date type="bulk"> (bulk 1940-1967)</date>, in the Archives of American Art</subtitle>
		<author>by Catherine S. Gaines</author>
	</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
	<publisher>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</publisher>
	<date type="publication">2007</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Stephanie Ashley on
<date>May 31, 2007</date>
</creation>
<langusage><language>English</language></langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>

<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory">
<did>
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
		<corpname>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</corpname>
	</repository>

	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100">Holty, Carl</persname>
	</origination>

	<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Carl Holty papers</unittitle>

	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f">circa 1860s-1972 (bulk 1940-1967)</unitdate>

	<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a">1.8 linear feet</physdesc>

	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">The Carl Holty papers are dated circa 1860s-1972 (bulk 1940-1967), measure 1.8 linear feet and contain correspondence, writings, printed material and photographs documenting Holty's career as an abstract painter and painting teacher.</abstract>
</did>



<!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION GOES HERE: -->

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541" id="a19">
<head>Provenance</head>
<p>The Carl Holty papers were donated in increments between 1972 and 2006. The bulk of the papers were originally loaned in 1968, and later donated by Holty in 1972.  Charles Byrne, a friend of Holty, donated a small amount of correspondence, printed material, and photographs in 1976-1977; family photographs were given by Holty’s biographer, Virginia Liles, in 2006.</p>
</acqinfo>

<separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 0" id="a7">
<head>Separated Material</head>
<p>Loaned material that was not later donated by Holty was returned to Holty after microfilming.  This includes Holty's letters to his wife, Elizabeth, and daughter, Antonia, letters to Zoe Dusanne, letters from Ulfert Wilkie and Erwin Breithaupt, a small amount of general correspondence, and a typescript copy of Holty's journal. Loaned material is available on microfilm reels N68-93 and N68-105, but is not described in the container listing of this finding aid.</p>
</separatedmaterial>

<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 1" id="a6">
<head>Related Material</head>
<p>Six interviews with Carl Holty (in addition to the one described in this finding aid) are available at the Archives of American Art.  Three are oral histories conducted by the Archives of American Art, 1964-1968.   The others are parts of interview collections accessioned by the Archives:  Interviews relating to American Abstract Artists (Ruth Bowman), Anne Bowen Parsons collection of Interviews on Art, and Collette Roberts Interviews with Artists.</p>

<p>In addition, substantial correspondence with Carl Holty is included among the Hilaire Hiler papers and Romare Bearden papers owned by the Archives of American Art.</p>
</relatedmaterial>

<altformavail id="a17" encodinganalog="530">
<head>Alternative Forms Available</head>
<p>The bulk of the collection is available on microfilm reels reels 439, 670, 1625, N68-93, and N68-105, at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the collection as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm.  When known, references to reel numbers have been added to folder headings. </p>
</altformavail>

<processinfo encodinganalog="583" id="a20">
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>The bulk of the collection was microfilmed in several installments in the order in which it was received and/or loaned on reels N68-93, N68-105, 439, 670, and 1625. The entire collection was merged and re-processed, arranged and described by Catherine S. Gaines in 2007.</p>
</processinfo>

<prefercite encodinganalog="510" id="a18">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Carl Holty papers, circa 1860s-1972 (bulk 1940-1967). Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
</prefercite>

<accessrestrict id="a14" encodinganalog="506">
<head>Restrictions on Access</head>
<p>The collection is open for research.  Use requires an appointment.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="a15">
<head>Ownership and Literary Rights</head>
<p>The Carl Holty papers are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
</userestrict>

<!-- END ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->

<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GO HERE: -->

<bioghist altrender="biography" encodinganalog="545" id="a2">
<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>Carl Holty was born in 1900 to American parents in Freiburg, Germany, where his father was studying medicine.  Carl was still an infant when the family returned to Milwaukee, Wisconsin, where they lived with his grandparents in a traditional German neighborhood.  It was Carl’s grandfather who first introduced him to art through visits to a small local commercial gallery.</p>

<p>After showing an interest in being an artist at around age 12, Holty began taking lessons with a local painter.  As a teenager he began drawing cartoons and soon set his sights on becoming a poster artist.  With that in mind, Holty enrolled at the Art Institute of Chicago in 1919.  He soon headed to New York and took courses at the Parsons School of Design and then at the National Academy of Design.  In 1923 he returned to Milwaukee and opened a portrait painting studio.</p>  

<p>Holty married in 1925 and took his bride to Europe, remaining abroad for the next decade.  He entered Hans Hofmann’s school in Munich in 1926, and exposure to Hofmann’s ideas about color, space, and form greatly influenced and transformed his work.  In 1927, the Holtys relocated to Switzerland in search of treatment for Mrs. Holty’s tuberculosis.  Holty and Hofmann remained in touch, and while in Switzerland, Holty increasingly incorporated Hofmann’s teachings into his paintings as they grew more abstract in style.</p>  

<p>After his wife’s death in 1930, Holty moved to Paris for five years where he participated in several exhibitions and his work was well-received.  Robert Delaunay invited him to join <emph render="italic">Abstration-Création</emph>, and the group published some of Holty’s work in its magazine.</p>  

<p>Upon returning to the United States in 1935, Holty settled in New York City where he eventually remarried and had a daughter.  He renewed friendships with Hans Hofmann, Vaclav Vytlacil, and Stuart Davis, whom he had known in Paris.  A figure in vanguard art circles, Holty was involved in meetings that resulted in the formation of the American Abstract Artists, and in 1938 he served as the group’s chairman.</p>  	

<p>Holty taught drawing and paining at Brooklyn College from 1950 until his retirement in 1970, when he was designated Professor Emeritus.  His years at Brooklyn College were punctuated by brief stints as a visiting instructor at the Art Students League, Washington University (St. Louis), and University of Louisville; he served as artist-in-residence at the universities of Georgia, Florida, California (Berkeley), and Wisconsin, and the Corcoran School of Art.</p> 

<p>He exhibited widely at major museums throughout the United States including: the San Francisco Art Museum, Seattle Art Museum, Whitney Museum of American Art, Carnegie Institute, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Museum of Modern Art, and the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum.  Holty’s work was shown at major New York galleries such as J. B. Neumann, Samuel Kootz Gallery, and Graham Gallery, and is in the permanent collections of many museums including:  Addison Gallery of American Art, Brooklyn Museum, Butler Institute of Art, Carnegie Institute, Smithsonian American Art Museum, and the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum.</p>

<p>Carl Holty died March 22, 1973 in New York City, after a short illness.</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520" id="a3">
<head>Scope and Content Note</head>
<p>The papers of Carl Holty are dated circa 1860s-1972 (bulk 1940-1967), measure 1.8 linear feet and consist of correspondence, writings, printed material and photographs documenting Holty's career as an abstract painter and painting teacher.</p>

<p>Correspondence with Romare Bearden, Charles Byrne and Hilaire Hiler concerns art, exhibitions and reviews, education, and news of mutual friends.  Holty’s writings include articles, autobiographical writings, unpublished manuscripts of a monograph, <emph render="italic">Art In America</emph>, and an untitled novel.  Also found among his writings is a journal which contains his reminiscences of artist friends and acquaintances, and reflections on art, art history, and his life, personal plans and aspirations.</p>  

<p>Printed material consists mainly of clippings about or mentioning Holty, and reviews and publicity relating to <emph render="italic">The Painter’s Mind</emph>, a book Holty wrote with Romare Bearden.  Miscellaneous records consist of a transcript of an interview with Carl Holty and an identification card issued to his father.</p>  

<p>Photographs are of artwork, people and places.  Also included are 6 photograph albums of Holty’s artwork, and a small number of negatives. The people pictured are mainly Holty, friends and family.  There is also a group photograph that includes Joan Miró.</p>
</scopecontent>


<!-- CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS GO HERE: -->


<controlaccess id="a12">
<head>Names and Subject Terms</head>
<p>This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms: </p>

<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects-Topical:</head>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Painting, Modern -- 20th century -- New York (state) -- New York</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Painters -- New York (State) -- New York</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Painting -- Study and teaching</subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Types of Materials:</head>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Photographs</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Photograph albums</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Interviews</genreform>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Names:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Hiler, Hilaire, 1898-1966</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Bearden, Romare, 1911-1988</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Byrne, Charles B. </persname>
</controlaccess>

</controlaccess>


<!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->

<!-- CONTINUE TOP-LEVEL METADATA HERE -->

<arrangement encodinganalog="351$b" id="a5">
<head>Arrangement</head>
<p>The collection is arranged as 5 series: </p>
<list>
<item>Series 1:  Correspondence, 1940-1972 (Box 1; 5 folders) </item> 
<item>Series 2:  Writings, 1944-1967 (Box 1; 0.6 linear ft.)</item>
<item>Series 3:  Printed Material, 1931-1972 (Box 1; 5 folders)</item>
<item>Series 4:  Miscellaneous Records, 1900, 1966 (Box 1; 2 folders)</item>
<item>Series 5:  Photographs, circa 1860s-1972 (Boxes 1-3; 0.9 linear ft.)</item>
</list>
</arrangement>



<!-- END TOP LEVEL METADATA -->



<!-- START DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->


<dsc type="combined" id="a23">
<head>Series Descriptions/Container Listing</head>

<!-- use this format if you have series only, no subseries -->
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 1: </unitid><unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1940-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 5 folders)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Carl Holty’s correspondence with Romare Bearden, Charles Byrne, and Hilaire Hiler concerns art, exhibitions and reviews, education, and news of mutual friends.  Also included are a letter from Margaret Bush-Brown, and a letter and postcard from Hélion.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Bearden Romare, <unitdate>1948-1952</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also Reel 670)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Bush-Brown, Marjorie, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also Reel 670)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Byrne, Charles, <unitdate>1966-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also Reel 1625)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Hélion, <unitdate>1948</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also Reel 670)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Hiler, Hilaire, <unitdate>1940-1962</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also Reel 670)</physdesc>
</did></c02>	
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 2: </unitid><unittitle>Writings, <unitdate>1944-1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Carl Holty’s writings consist of a journal, articles, autobiographical writings, and unpublished manuscripts of a monograph titled <emph render="italic">Art In America</emph>, and an untitled novel.</p>
	
<p>Journal entries include reminiscences of artist friends and acquaintances, as well as reflections on art, art history, past experiences, routine events of daily life, plans and aspirations.  Included is an incomplete, handwritten copy of Carl Holty’s journal covering the periods January 1963-October 1964 and April 1966-May 1967. </p>  
</scopecontent>


<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>Articles, "The Way to Creativity" and "Art," <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also Reel 670)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>Autobiographical Writings (7 mss.), <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also Reel N68-93)</physdesc>
</did></c02> 
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Book, <emph render="italic">Art in America</emph></unittitle><physdesc>(see also Reels N68-93 and 670)</physdesc></did>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>Outlines, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>Section I: "A Million People are Painting," <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle>Section I a: "Motives of the Amateur – From Without," <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle>Section I b: "Motives of the Amateur – From Within," <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">12</container>
<unittitle>Section III: [untitled], <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">13</container>
<unittitle>Section IV: "An Historical Survey of American Painting and Recent Trends in 
Our Taste," <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">14</container>
<unittitle>Section V: "The Amateur and Modern Art," <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">15</container>
<unittitle>Section VI:  "The Depression and Art in America," <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">16</container>
<unittitle>Section VII:  "Collectors and Patrons," <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">17</container>
<unittitle>Section VIII: "The Commercial Triumph of Modern Art (and the influence it 
exerts on all painting today)," <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">18</container>
<unittitle>Section IX:  "Art Appreciation," <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">19</container>
<unittitle>Section X: "Teaching," <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">20-22</container>
<unittitle>Journal, <unitdate>1963-1964, 1966-1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(3 folders; see also Reel N68-93)</physdesc>
</did></c02> 
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">23</container>
<unittitle>Novel (untitled, unfinished), <unitdate>1944</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also Reel 670)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 3: </unitid><unittitle>Printed Material, <unitdate>1931-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 5 folders)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Printed material primarily comprises clippings about or mentioning Holty, and reviews and publicity relating to <emph render="italic">The Painter’s Mind</emph>, a book Holty wrote with Romare Bearden.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">24</container>
<unittitle>Clippings about/mentioning Carl Holty, <unitdate>1931-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also Reel 1625)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">25</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Catalog and Announcement, <unitdate>1972, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also Reel 1625)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">26</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Printed Material, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c02> 
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">27</container>
<unittitle>Reviews and Publicity for The Painter’s Mind by Romare Bearden and Carl Holty, <unitdate>1969-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also Reel 670)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">28</container>
<unittitle>Reviews and Publicity for The Painter’s Mind by Romare Bearden and Carl Holty, <unitdate>1969</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 4: </unitid><unittitle>Miscellaneous Records, <unitdate>1900, 1966</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 2 folders)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Miscellaneous records consist of a transcript of an interview with Carl Holty and an identification card issued to his father.</p> 
</scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">29</container>
<unittitle>"Carl Holty Interviewed by Nina Wayne, New York University Art 
Department," <unitdate>1966</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also Reel 670)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">30</container>
<unittitle>University of Freiburg Identification Card issued to Dr. Karl Holty, <unitdate>1900</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 5: </unitid><unittitle>Photographs, <unitdate>circa 1860s-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Boxes 1-3; 0.9 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Photographs are mainly of Holty, friends and family. Among the folders titled "Carl Holty with Others" is a group shot that includes Joan Miró, as well as several classroom views with students.  The albums (6 vols.) contain photographs of art work by Holty, and a few of the artist posed with his paintings.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<arrangement><p>The series is arranged into 5 subseries:</p> 
<p>
<list> 
<item>5.1:  Artwork, circa 1925-1965</item>
<item>5.2:  People, circa 1860s-1972</item>
<item>5.3:  Places, 1962-1964</item>
<item>5.4:  Photograph Albums, 1936-1972</item>
<item>5.5:  Negatives, circa 1950s-circa 1970s</item>
</list> 
</p></arrangement>

<c02 level="subseries"><did><unitid>5.1: </unitid>
<unittitle>Artwork, <unitdate>circa 1925-1965</unitdate></unittitle></did>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">31</container>
<unittitle>By Holty, <unitdate>circa 1925-1965, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">32</container>
<unittitle>By Holty, <unitdate>1940-1963, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also Reel 1625)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">33</container>
<unittitle>By Others [student assignment?], <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
</c02>

<c02 level="subseries"><did><unitid>5.2: </unitid>
<unittitle>People, <unitdate>circa 1860s-1972</unitdate></unittitle></did>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">34</container>
<unittitle>Carl Holty, <unitdate>1936-1972, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">35</container>
<unittitle>Carl Holty in Studio (119 East 119th St., New York), <unitdate>1948</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also Reel 439: 1109)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">36</container>
<unittitle>Carl and Mrs. Holty; Mrs. Holty with Others, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">37</container>
<unittitle>Carl Holty with Others, <unitdate>1947, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">38</container>
<unittitle>Carl Holty with Students and Others, <unitdate>circa 1960s, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(see also Reel 1625)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">39</container>
<unittitle>Carl Holty with Students; Students in Classroom, <unitdate>1958, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Friends and Relatives</unittitle></did>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">40</container>
<unittitle>Clara (great aunt), <unitdate>circa 1870-1936</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">41</container>
<unittitle>Engelman, Peter; Geuder, George, Aunt Geuder, Tina Gauder (sic); Hofmann, 
<unitdate>circa 1890-1900</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">42</container>
<unittitle>Grandmother, <unitdate>circa 1860s</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">43</container>
<unittitle>Holty Family, <unitdate>1900-1938, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">44</container>
<unittitle>Jacoby, Sigmund; Kiewert (?); Kisling, Dr.; Kroeck, John, <unitdate>circa 1880s-circa 1900s</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">45</container>
<unittitle>Landauer Family, <unitdate>circa 1890s-1900s</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">46</container>
<unittitle>Landauer and Wallace Families, <unitdate>circa 1900</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">47</container>
<unittitle>Law, Adolf (great uncle); Rindstropp, Samuel; Seeman, John P.; Seligmann, 
Yetti, <unitdate>circa 1890s-1900s</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">48</container>
<unittitle>Stern Family, <unitdate>circa 1890s-1900s</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">49</container>
<unittitle>Wallace Family, <unitdate>circa 1890s-1920s</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">50</container>
<unittitle>Wasserman, Rabbi and Mrs. (Landauer relatives), <unitdate>circa 1870s-1890s</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">51</container>
<unittitle>Weinberg, E. Schaefer, <unitdate>circa 1900</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">52</container>
<unittitle>Unknown (identified, but illegible), <unitdate>1868-1892, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
</c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Unidentified</unittitle></did>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">53</container>
<unittitle>Children, <unitdate>circa 1870s-1900s</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">54</container>
<unittitle>Couples and Groups, <unitdate>circa 1860s-1926, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">55</container>
<unittitle>Men, circa <unitdate>1870s-1900s</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">56</container>
<unittitle>Women, <unitdate>circa 1870s-1900s</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
</c03>
</c02>

<c02 level="subseries"><did><unitid>5.3: </unitid>
<unittitle>Places, <unitdate>1962-1964</unitdate></unittitle></did>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">57</container>
<unittitle>Carl Holty’s Studio, <unitdate>1964, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03> 
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">58</container>
<unittitle>Interiors (unidentified) <unitdate>1962, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03> 
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container><container type="folder">59</container>
<unittitle>Lenz Farm; Buildings (unidentified); Landscape, "Near Amerika!!," <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03> 
</c02>

<c02 level="subseries"><did><unitid>5.4: </unitid>
<unittitle>Photographs Albums, <unitdate>1936-1972</unitdate></unittitle></did>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container><container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Vol. 1: <unitdate>1936-1942</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container><container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Vol. 2: <unitdate>1942-1948</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container><container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Vol. 3: <unitdate>1947-1950</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container><container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Vol. 4: <unitdate>1950-1957</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container><container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Vol. 5: <unitdate>1957-1959</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container><container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Vol. 6: <unitdate>1959-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
</c02>

<c02 level="subseries"><did><unitid>5.5: </unitid>
<unittitle>Negatives, <unitdate>circa 1950s-circa 1970s</unitdate></unittitle></did>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container><container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Artwork by Others [student assignment?], <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03> 
<c03><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container><container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Carl Holty with Students; Students in Classroom, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03> 
</c02>
</c01>

</dsc>

<!-- END DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->

<!-- OPTIONAL ARCHDESC ELEMENTS -->

<!-- END OPTIONAL ARCHDESC ELEMENTS -->


</archdesc>
</ead>




