<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "/eadcb/shared/ead/ead.dtd">

<ead audience="external" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
<eadid mainagencycode="DSI-AAA" countrycode="us" url="http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/findingaids/xml/karsdona.xml">karsdona</eadid>

<filedesc>
	<titlestmt>
		<titleproper>Donald H. Karshan Papers Relating to Alexander Archipenko</titleproper>
		<subtitle>A Finding Aid to the Donald H. Karshan Papers Relating to Alexander Archipenko, <date type="inclusive">1920-1973</date>, in the Archives of American Art</subtitle>
		<author>by Catherine S. Gaines</author>
	</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
	<publisher>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</publisher>
	<date type="publication">January 2003</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Christina Lehman,
<date>August 18, 2005</date>
</creation>
<langusage><language>English</language></langusage>
</profiledesc>
<revisiondesc>
<change>
<date>September 8, 2005</date>
<item>Finding aid updated from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by Stephanie Ashley
</item>
</change>
</revisiondesc>
</eadheader>

<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory">
<did>
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
		<corpname>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</corpname>
	</repository>

	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100">Donald H. Karshan</persname>
	</origination>

	<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Donald H. Karshan papers relating to Alexander Archipenko</unittitle>

	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f">1920-1973</unitdate>

	<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a">1.8 linear feet</physdesc>

	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">The Donald H. Karshan papers relating to Alexander Achipenko measure 1.8 linear feet and date from 1920 to 1973, (bulk dates 1966-1970). Karshan, a print expert and collector, served as Curator of the Archipenko Collection and Director of the Archipenko Archive from circa 1966 until circa 1973.  Exhibition files include records concerning University of California, Los Angeles's <emph render="italic">Alexander Archipenko Memorial Exhibition, 1967-1969</emph>, that traveled throughout the United States; an expanded version of the show was circulated in Europe by the Smithsonian Institution. The collection also contains general correspondence relating to the administration of the Archipenko Collection and Archipenko Archive, Leopold Survage, and writings on Archipenko's work and life by Karshan with related correspondence.</abstract>

	<langmaterial>The records are in English.<language></language>.
	</langmaterial>
</did>



<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GO HERE: -->


<bioghist altrender="biography" encodinganalog="545" id="a2">
<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>Donald H. Karshan (b. 1929) is a print expert and collector who in 1964 established the Museum of Graphic Art, New York City. He was Curator of the Archipenko Collection and Director of the Archipenko Archive from circa 1966 until circa 1973.  During this time, Karshan cataloged the estate collection and organized the archives. He was closely involved with the Archipenko memorial exhibition organized by UCLA in 1967 that traveled widely in the United States and an expanded version of the same show that was circulated Europe by the International Art Program of the Smithsonian Institution. Karshan wrote extensively on Archipenko and his oeuvre, including a catalogue raisonné of Archipenko's prints.  His book, <emph render="italic">Alexander Archipenko: International Visionary</emph>, was published by the Smithsonian Institution to accompany the European tour of the memorial exhibition, 1969-1970. </p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520" id="a3">
<head>Scope and Content Note</head>
<p>The Donald H. Karshan papers relating to Alexander Achipenko measure 1.8 linear feet and date from 1960 to 1973, (bulk dates 1966-1970). Exhibition files consist of records concerning UCLA's <emph render="italic">Alexander Archipenko Memorial Exhibition, 1967-1969</emph>, that traveled throughout the United States; an expanded version of the show that circulated in Europe by the Smithsonian Institution. The collection also contains general correspondence relating to the administration of the Archipenko Collection and Archipenko Archive, and writings on Archipenko's work and life by Karshan with related correspondence. Records pre-dating 1960 are printed matter and photocopies of Archipenko's correspondence with Leopold Survage gathered for reference purposes.</p>
<p>Exhibition files, 1960-1972, include correspondence, photographs, and printed matter relating to UCLA's <emph render="italic">Alexander Archipenko Memorial Exhibition, 1967-1969</emph> at its various venues in the United States and its European tour sponsored by International Art Program of the Smithsonian Institution.  There are similar records for <emph render="italic">Archipenko: The Parisian Years</emph>, an exhibition organized by the Museum of Modern Art.</p>
<p>General Correspondence, 1966-1973, relates to the Archipenko Collection and the Archipenko Archive, administered by Karshan and includes loan and reference requests, publication permissions, and sales information.  Of particular interest is a file on Leopold Survage compiled in 1969 and documenting an attempt to purchase a Survage painting for Mrs. Arhcipenko to donate to the Museum of Modern Art; included is reference material consisting of photocopies of Archipenko's letters to Survage and a letter from Theodore Doesburg,  printed matter, and photographs.</p>
<p>Writings by Donald H. Karshan, 1966-1968, consist of research notes and correspondence concerning his catalogue raisonné of Archipenko prints (1974). Also included are manuscripts of published articles and correspondence with editors.</p>
</scopecontent>

<arrangement encodinganalog="351$b" id="a5">
<head>Arrangement</head>
<p>The collection is arranged into three series: </p>
<list>
<item>Series 1: Exhibition Files, 1960-1972 (Boxes 1-2; 1.5 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 2: General Correspondence, 1920-1973 (Box 3; 0.25 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 3: Writings by Donald H. Karshan, 1966-1968 (Box 3; 0.25 linear feet)</item>
</list>
</arrangement>

<!-- END TOP LEVEL METADATA -->

<!-- CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS GO HERE: -->
  
<controlaccess id="a12">
<head>Index Terms</head>
<p>This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.</p>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Archipenko, Alexander, 1887-1964</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Survage, Leopold</persname>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects-Topical:</head>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Cubism</subject>
</controlaccess>

</controlaccess>

<!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->

<!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION GOES HERE: -->

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541" id="a19">
<head>Provenance</head>
<p>Gift of Frances Archipenko Gray, widow of Alexander Archipenko, 1982. Karshan's files were among the Alexander Archipenko Papers, and have been separated and arranged as a distinct collection.</p>
</acqinfo>

<accessrestrict id="a14" encodinganalog="506">
<head>Restrictions on Access</head>
<p>The collection is open for research.  Use requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington, D.C. research facility.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="a15">
<head>Ownership and Literary Rights</head>
<p>The Donald H. Karshan papers relating to Alexander Archipenko are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite encodinganalog="510" id="a18">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>The Donald H. Karshan papers relating to Alexander Archipenko, 1920-1973. Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
</prefercite>

<processinfo encodinganalog="583" id="a20">
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>The collection was processed by Catherine S. Gaines in 2002.</p>
</processinfo>


<!-- END ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->


<!-- START DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->


<dsc type="combined" id="a23">
<head>Series Descriptions/Container Listing</head>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 1: </unitid><unittitle>Exhibition Files, <unitdate>1960-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Boxes 1-2; 1.5 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Records regarding <emph render="italic">Alexander Archipenko: A Memorial Exhibition, 1967-1969</emph> consist of general administrative records and correspondence concerning the exhibition organized by UCLA, Dickson Art Center Galleries and production of its accompanying catalog, and includes a manuscript and reviews of the catalog. The exhibition's 1967-1969 tour to nine other cities in the United State is documented with correspondence, printed matter, and photographs arranged by venue. In Washington, UCLA exhibition was shown at the Smithsonian Institution's National Collection of Fine Arts, which issued its own catalog, <emph render="italic">Archipenko: International Visionary</emph>. Of particular interest is a file titled "Terra Cottas" containing correspondence regarding an exhibition of Archipenko's terra cottas planned to supplement the UCLA retrospective at NCFA but not implemented; catalog text is included. In addition, there are sound recordings of interviews w
 ith Frances Archipenko at NCFA, July 11, 1968 (1 reel) and an interview broadcast by Voice of America, July 14, 1968 (1 reel); and an interview with Donald H. Karshan about the NCFA exhibition broadcast by Voice of America in two parts, July 20 and 21, 1968 (2 reels).</p>
<p>An expanded version of the UCLA memorial exhibition was circulated in Europe between 1969 and 1970 by the Smithsonian's International Art Program. General administrative records regard the production of Karshan's book and its translation, and correspondence concerning the exhibition and arrangements for its showing in five European countries, insurance records, and detailed condition reports.  Files specifically relating to each venue include correspondence, photographs, and printed matter, and are arranged by country.  French and German editions of <emph render="italic">Archipenko: International Visionary</emph> by Donald H. Karshan were issued to accompany the exhibition's tour of Europe.  In Paris, the venue included Museé Rodin, Paris, des Beaux-Arts, Lyon, RJennes, Nantes; in Brussels at the Palais des Beaux-Arts; in Germany at  the Museum Folkwang, Essen; Neuen Staatsgalerie, Munich; Rheinisches Landesmuseum, Bonn; Mannheimer Kunstverein, Mannheim; in Geneva at the 
 Museé Rath; and in Ireland at the Municipal Gallery of Modern Art, Dublin.</p>
<p>Correspondence, printed matter, and photographs document <emph render="italic">Archipenko: The Parisian Years</emph> organized by the Museum of Modern Art. Loans to smaller exhibitions are documented in Series 2: General Correspondence.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<arrangement><p>This series is arranged into 2 subseries:</p> 
<p>
<list> 
<item>1.1: UCLA -- American Tour, <emph render="italic">Alexander Archipenko: A Memorial Exhibition, 1967-1969</emph>, 1960-1968</item> 
<item>1.2: Smithsonian Institution, International Art Program -- European Tour of <emph render="italic">Alexander Archipenko: A Memorial Exhibition, 1967-1969</emph>, 1969-1971</item>
<item>1.3: Museum of Modern Art, <emph render="italic">Archipenko: The Parisian Years</emph>, 1966-1972</item> 
</list> 
</p></arrangement>

<c02 level="subseries"><did><unitid>1.1: </unitid>
<unittitle>UCLA -- American Tour of <emph render="italic">Alexander Archipenko, A Memorial Exhibition, 1967-1969</emph>, <unitdate>1960-1971</unitdate></unittitle></did>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Archipenko Bibliography, <unitdate>1969, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Archipenko Biography, <unitdate>1960-1969, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Catalog, <unitdate>1966-1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(4 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1966-1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Crating and Transport, <unitdate>1965-1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Insurance, <unitdate>1966-1969</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Notes and Lists, <unitdate>1966-1967, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Photographs, <unitdate>1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Printed Matter, <unitdate>1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Walker Art Center, Minneapolis, Correspondence, <unitdate>1966-1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Walker Art Center, Minneapolis, Photographs, <unitdate>1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Walker Art Center, Minneapolis, Printed Matter, <unitdate>1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Fine Arts Center of San Diego, Correspondence, <unitdate>1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Fine Arts Center of San Diego, Minneapolis, Photographs, <unitdate>1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Fine Arts Center of San Diego, Minneapolis, Printed Matter, <unitdate>1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Phoenix Art Museum, Correspondence, <unitdate>1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Phoenix Art Museum, Photographs, <unitdate>1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Phoenix Art Museum, Printed Matter, <unitdate>1966-1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Dallas Museum of Fine Arts, Correspondence, <unitdate>1967-1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Dallas Museum of Fine Arts, Printed Matter, <unitdate>1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center, Correspondence, <unitdate>1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center, Photographs, <unitdate>1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center, Printed Matter, <unitdate>1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Washington University, Steinberg Gallery, St. Louis, Correspondence, <unitdate>1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Washington University, Steinberg Gallery, St. Louis, Photographs, <unitdate>1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Washington University, Steinberg Gallery, St. Louis, Printed Matter, <unitdate>1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Cincinnati Art Museum, Correspondence, <unitdate>1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Cincinnati Art Museum, Printed Matter, <unitdate>1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute, Utica, N.Y., Correspondence, <unitdate>1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute, Utica, N.Y., Photographs, <unitdate>1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Smithsonian Institution, National Collection of Fine Arts, Correspondence, <unitdate>1966-1969</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Smithsonian Institution, National Collection of Fine Arts, Photographs, <unitdate>1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Smithsonian Institution, National Collection of Fine Arts, Printed Matter, <unitdate>1968-1969</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Smithsonian Institution, National Collection of Fine Arts, Frances Archipenko interviews, <unitdate>1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 reels)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Smithsonian Institution, National Collection of Fine Arts, Donald H. Karshan interviews,  <unitdate>1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 reels)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Terra Cottas, <unitdate>1969-1971</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03> 

</c02>

<c02 level="subseries"><did><unitid>1.2: </unitid>
<unittitle>Smithsonian Institution, International Art Program -- European Tour of <emph render="italic">Alexander Archipenko, A Memorial Exhibition, 1967-1969</emph>, <unitdate>1969-1971</unitdate></unittitle></did>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle><emph render="italic">Archipenko: International Visionary</emph> Exhibition Catalog, English Edition, <unitdate>circa 1968-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(3 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle><emph render="italic">Archipenko: International Visionary</emph> Exhibition Catalog, French Edition, <unitdate>1968-1969</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle><emph render="italic">Archipenko: International Visionary</emph> Exhibition Catalog, German Edition, <unitdate>1968-1969</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>General Correspondence, <unitdate>1966-1970, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(3 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>General Insurance, <unitdate>1968-1971</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>General Travel Expense Receipts, <unitdate>1969-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>France, Correspondence, <unitdate>1969</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>France, Photographs, <unitdate>1969</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(3 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>France, Printed Matter, <unitdate>1960-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Brussels, Correspondence, <unitdate>1969-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Brussels, Printed Matter, <unitdate>1969</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Germany, Correspondence, <unitdate>1969-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Germany, Photographs, <unitdate>1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(3 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Germany, Printed Matter, <unitdate>1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(4 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Geneva, Photographs, <unitdate>1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Geneva, Printed Matter, <unitdate>1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Ireland, Printed Matter, <unitdate>1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03> 

</c02>

<c02 level="subseries"><did><unitid>1.3: </unitid>
<unittitle>Museum of Modern Art, <emph render="italic">Archipenko: The Parisian Years</emph>, <unitdate>1966-1972</unitdate></unittitle></did>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1966-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Photographs, <unitdate>1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">2 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Printed Matter, <unitdate>1970-1971</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c03> 

</c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 2: </unitid><unittitle>General Correspondence, <unitdate>1920-1973</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 3; 0.25 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Although many of these letters are addressed to Frances Archipenko, they were answered by Donald Karshan who, in his capacity as Curator of the Archipenko Estate Collection and Director of the Archipenko Archive, handled all art-related business matters. Correspondence concerns loans to exhibitions and museums. "Sculpture Correspondence" consists of reference requests, general information and inquiries regarding exhibitions.</p>
<p>Of particular interest is a file about painter Leopold Survage containing photocopies of a letter from Theodore Doesburg and Archipenko's letters to Survage, printed matter, and photographs compiled by Karshan for reference purposes when attempting to purchase a Survage for Frances Archipenko to donate to the Museum of Modern Art in 1969. The Archives of American Art file which includes transcripts of unidentified lectures-possibly by Karshan-about Archipenko's work.  Other correspondence of note is with the Whitney Museum of American Art consists of a telegram from Frances Archipenko objecting to <emph render="italic">Floating Torso</emph> being omitted from the museum's opening exhibition, and letters about the Whitney as a possible venue for the UCLA traveling exhibition; plans of the Ukrainian Institute of America, Inc. to open a memorial room to Archipenko and Dzus;  Karshan's donation of <emph render="italic">Queen of Sheba</emph> by Archipenko to UCLA's Sculpture Co
 urt; and attempts to locate a copy of the Folkwang Museum's catalog of its 1912 Archipenko exhibition.</p>
<p>The files are arranged in alphabetical order according to name and/or subject.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Archives of American Art, <unitdate>1966</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Arts Council of Great Britain, <unitdate>1973</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Folkwang Museum, <unitdate>1966-1971</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Loans to Museums, A-Z, <unitdate>1966-1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Publication Permissions, A-Z, <unitdate>1966-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Sales Pending, A-Z, <unitdate>1967-1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Sculpture Correspondence, A-Z, <unitdate>1966-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Survage, Leopold, <unitdate>1920-1969, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Taylor, Dorothy, <unitdate>1969-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Ukrainian Institute of America, Inc., <unitdate>1966</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Whitney Museum of American Art, <unitdate>1966-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 3: </unitid><unittitle>Writings by Donald H. Karshan, <unitdate>1962-1971</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 3; 0.25 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Research notes and correspondence relating to Karshan's catalogue raisonné of Archipenko prints published in 1974.  Also included are manuscripts of published articles and correspondence with editors; these folders also contain related correspondence, notes, and receipts.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Catalogue Raisonné, Correspondence, A-Z, <unitdate>1965-1971</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Catalogue Raisonné, Notes, <unitdate>1962-1968, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Catalogue Raisonné, Photo and Printing Orders, <unitdate>1966, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle>Catalogue Raisonné, Publicity, <unitdate>1966</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle><emph render="italic">Art In America</emph>, "Alexander Arhcipenko-In Retrospect," <unitdate>1966-1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle><emph render="italic">Artist's Proof</emph>, Footnotes for article on Archipenko's Graphics, <unitdate>1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3 (hol)</container>
<unittitle><emph render="italic">Arts Magazine</emph>, "Archipenko-A Modern Master Rediscovered," <unitdate>1967-1968</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

</c01>


</dsc>


<!-- END DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->
</archdesc>
</ead>



