<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "/eadcb/shared/ead/ead.dtd">

<ead audience="external" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
<eadid mainagencycode="DSI-AAA" countrycode="us" url="http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/findingaids/xml/knolflor.xml">knolflor</eadid>

<filedesc>
	<titlestmt>
		<titleproper>Florence Knoll Bassett</titleproper>
		<subtitle>A Finding Aid to the Florence Knoll Bassett Papers, <date type="inclusive">1932-2000</date>, in the Archives of American Art</subtitle>
		<author>by Stephanie Ashley</author>
<sponsor>Funding for the digitization of this collection was provided by the Terra Foundation for American Art.</sponsor>
	</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
	<publisher>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</publisher>
	<date type="publication">2001</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Apex Data Services; revised by Stephanie Ashley, 
<date>November, 2001</date>
</creation>
<langusage><language>English</language></langusage>
</profiledesc>
<revisiondesc>
<change>
<date>October 2005</date>
<item>Finding aid updated from EAD v. 1.0 to v. 2002 by Stephanie Ashley</item>
</change>
</revisiondesc>
</eadheader>

<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory">
<did>
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
		<corpname>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</corpname>
	</repository>

	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100">Knoll, Florence (Florence Knoll Bassett)</persname>
	</origination>

	<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Florence Knoll Bassett papers</unittitle>

	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f">1932-2000</unitdate>

	<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a">2.5 linear feet</physdesc>

	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">The papers of
architect and designer Florence Knoll Bassett, measure approximately 2.5 linear
feet dating from 1932 to 2000. Through correspondence, sketches, drawings,
designs, subject files, photographs, and printed material, the collection
selectively documents Knoll Bassett's education, her work with Knoll Associates
from the 1940s until her resignation in 1965, and projects undertaken since her
retirement. It is an important source of information on the development of
interior architecture and design from the 1940s to the 1970s.</abstract>
</did>

<!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION GOES HERE: -->

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541" id="a19">
<head>Provenance</head>
<p>The collection was donated to the Archives of American Art by
Florence Knoll Bassett in 2000.</p>
</acqinfo>

<accessrestrict id="a14" encodinganalog="506">
<head>Restrictions on Access</head>
<p>The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="a15">
<head>Ownership and Literary Rights</head>
<p>The Florence Knoll Bassett papers are owned by the Archives of
American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the
donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship.
The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite encodinganalog="510" id="a18">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Florence Knoll Bassett papers, 1932-2000. Archives of American Art,
Smithsonian Institution.</p>
</prefercite>

<altformavail id="a17" encodinganalog="530">
<head>Alternative Forms Available</head>
<p>The collection was digitized in 2007 and is available online via the Archives of American Art website.</p>
</altformavail>

<processinfo encodinganalog="583" id="a20">
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>Florence Knoll Bassett arranged the papers and designed their storage units
before donating them to the Archives of American Art. Stephanie Ashley
conducted minimal processing work on the collection in 2001, retaining the
original order of the papers, the labels, and the containers provided by the donor. The collection was digitized in 2007 with funding provided by the Terra Foundation for American Art.</p>
</processinfo>


<!-- END ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->

<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GO HERE: -->


<bioghist altrender="biography" encodinganalog="545" id="a2">
<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>Florence Knoll Bassett was born Florence Schust in 1917 and was
affectionately known as Shu by her colleagues and friends. She was orphaned at
age 12 and then cared for by Emile Tessin, a friend of the family whom her
mother had appointed as Florence's legal guardian in the event of her death.
When arrangements were being made for Florence to attend boarding school she
was given the opportunity to make the selection. Kingswood School in Bloomfield
Hills, Michigan, held a strong aesthetic appeal for her and she "made an
immediate decision that it was the right place for me," beginning her
architectural studies under the school's art director, Rachel de Wolfe
Raseman.</p> 
<p>At Kingswood Knoll Bassett met the Saarinen family, studying under
Eliel Saarinen and developing her interest in texture and color through her
friendship with Loja Saarinen who supervised the school's weaving studio.
Following Florence's graduation from Kingswood in 1934, Eliel Saarinen
encouraged her to spend some time at Cranbrook Academy of Art before attending
an accredited architecture school. She spent the next two years at Cranbrook
working closely with advanced students and artists such as the Saarinens and
Carl Milles, and gaining experience in all aspects of design.</p> 
<p>Knoll Bassett then studied for two years at the Architectural
Association in London, spending summers with the Saarinens in Europe. She
completed her formal training at the Illinois Institute of Technology where she
studied under Mies van der Rohe, whom she credits with having "a profound
effect on my design approach and the clarification of design."</p> 
<p>After graduation Knoll Bassett worked for architecture firms in Boston
and New York where she met Hans Knoll who was then in the process of
establishing a furniture business. In 1943 she began working for him in her
spare time as an interior space planner and designer. In 1946 the two were
married and formed Knoll Associates, Inc.</p> 
<p>As director of the Knoll Planning Unit, Knoll Bassett established
herself as one of the most important and influential interior planners and
designers of the second half of the twentieth century. Believing that
intelligent design "strikes at the root of living requirements and changing
habits," she established the practice of working closely with the corporate
sector to determine the needs of the people who would actually use the spaces
that her company designed. Her connections with leading contemporary architects
and designers, and the company's commitment to crediting designers by name and
paying them royalties, laid the foundations for the strong working
relationships upon which the commercial success of Knoll Associates was built.
Drawing on a pool of top architects and designers, many of whom were personal
friends, Knoll Bassett directed the company's Bauhaus approach, incorporating
design excellence, technological innovation, and mass production in a seamless
package of "total design."</p> 
<p>While Knoll Bassett oversaw the creative process of the Planning
Unit's operations in its entirety, she was also directly responsible for many
of the individual elements used in the Unit's projects. During the war years,
she worked with her designers to overcome the scarcity of materials,
establishing Knoll Textiles in response to the dearth of available fabrics and
textile colors, and developing the company's hallmark style of spare clean
lines and vibrant colors in a functional, comfortable, and aesthetically
appealing space. Finding that much of the "fill-in" furniture, primarily
cabinetry, that she envisaged in many of her plans was not available, Knoll
Bassett designed the pieces herself. She used the Knoll showrooms as "experimental laboratories" to convince clients to use modern ideas and
materials, showcasing and putting into production the classic designs of people
such as Eero Saarinen, Mies van der Rohe, Jens Risom, Harry Bertoia, Isamu
Noguchi, and Marcel Breuer.</p> 
<p>After the war Knoll Associates expanded to Europe through a series of
government contracts which resulted ultimately in the formation of Knoll
International. When Hans Knoll died suddenly in an automobile accident in 1955
Florence became president of the company. She married Harry Hood Bassett in
1958 and began to divide her time between New York and Florida. In 1959 she
sold her interest in Knoll Associates to Art Metal and retired as President of
the company the following year, while continuing to work as a consultant and
serving as Design Director. In 1961 she became the first woman to be awarded
the Gold Medal for Industrial Design by the American Institute of Architects,
one of many awards received over the course of her career. In 1965 she resigned
from Knoll Associates entirely after completing the interior design for the CBS
headquarters in New York.</p> 
<p>Following her retirement Knoll Bassett devoted more time to private
commissions and other interests such as her campaign against billboards in
Miami in the mid 1980s. She spent summers in Vermont and winters in Florida
with her husband, until his death in 1991. In July 2001, <emph
render="italic">Metropolis </emph>magazine published a rare interview with
Knoll Bassett in which she reflects upon the life she so skillfully documented
in the extraordinary gift of her archival papers to the Archives of American
Art.</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520" id="a3">
<head>Scope and Content Note</head>
<p>The papers of architect, and interior designer and planner Florence
Knoll Bassett, measure approximately 2.5 linear feet dating from 1932 to 2000.
The collection selectively documents Knoll Bassett's education and her career
at Knoll Associates, Inc. from the 1940s until her resignation in 1965, in
addition to personal design projects and other activities after leaving the
company. It is an important source of information on the development of
interior architecture and design from the 1940s to the 1970s, chronicling the
Knoll mission to synthesize space, furniture, and design by creating interiors
based on practical use, comfort, and aesthetics.</p> 
<p>The collection documents the growth of Knoll's international
reputation for its modern furnishings and interiors and the impact of a
business philosophy that encompassed design excellence, technological
innovation, and mass production. The material includes a chronology of Knoll
Bassett's career; a portfolio of sketches, drawings and designs; photographs of
Knoll Bassett and others; subject files containing sketches and photographic
material; letters from friends, colleagues, clients and others; awards received
by Knoll Bassett throughout her career; and printed material.</p> 
<p>Much of the material is annotated with historical and biographical
notes written by Knoll Bassett which provide invaluable contextual information
for the materials found therein. The notes are dated 1999 in the Container
Listing, under the assumption that they were written by Florence Knoll Bassett
as she was arranging her archival papers.</p> 
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351$b" id="a5">
<head>Arrangement</head>
<p>Before donating her papers to the Archives of American Art, Knoll
Bassett organized the material in portfolios and color-coded files and designed
four containers for them. Because the method of arrangement in itself provides
insight into Knoll Bassett's style and creativity the collection has been
minimally processed with the addition of acid-free materials for preservation
reasons and the transcription of labels which may, over time, become detached.
The original order of the collection has been retained throughout.</p> 
<p>The collection was organized into what Bassett termed "storage units,"
the first container being divided into three units and the collection as a
whole being divided into six units. Knoll Bassett supplied a detailed inventory
of the contents of each container and the subjects represented in each porfolio
or folder. Subject headings from this inventory have been used in the Series Description/Container Listing. Knoll Bassett also supplied a vita summarizing her career and copies
of this, and her original container inventory are enclosed with the collection
and can be consulted at AAA's research center in Washington D.C.</p> 
<p>The collection is arranged as seven series. These series represent
the categories into which Knoll Bassett organized the material, with the
exception that Letters and Awards are presented as two series in the finding
aid. Most of the items in Series 1 to 4 are presented as portfolios in
spiral-bound notebooks and the remainder of the collection is organized in
folders.</p> 
<list> 
<item>Series 1: Biographical Material, 1932-1999 (Box 1; 1
portfolio)</item> 
<item>Series 2: Selected Publications, 1946-1990, 1999 (Box 1; 1
portfolio)</item> 
<item>Series 3: Drawings, Sketches, and Designs, 1932-1984, 1999 (Boxes
1-2; 2 portfolios)</item> 
<item>Series 4: Photographs and Printed Material, 1956-1997, 1999 (Box
2; 1 portfolio)</item> 
<item>Series 5: Subject Files, circa 1930s-1999 (Box 3; 1.0 linear
ft.)</item> 
<item>Series 6: Letters, circa 1930s-2000 (Box 4; 7 folders)</item> 
<item>Series 7: Awards, 1954-1999 (Box 4; 6 folders)</item> 
</list> 
</arrangement>

<!-- END TOP LEVEL METADATA -->


<!-- CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS GO HERE: -->

<controlaccess id="a12">
<head>Names and Subject Terms</head>
<p>This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms: </p>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Saarinen, Eero, 1910-1961</persname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Cranbrook Academy of Art</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Knoll Associates, inc.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Cranbrook Kingswood School (Bloomfield Hills, Mich.)</corpname>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects-Topical:</head>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Architects</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women architects</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Interior decoration</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Interior decoration firms</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Interior decorators</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Design, Industrial</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Furniture designers</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women designers</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Designers</subject>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Types of Materials:</head> 
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Drawings</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Sketches</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Photographs</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Sketchbooks</genreform>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Names:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Miller, R. Craig</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Slavin, Maeve</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Saarinen, Eero, 1910-1961</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Saarinen, Eliel, 1873-1950</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Milles, Carl, 1875-1955</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Cheek, Leslie, 1908-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Eames, Charles</persname> 
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Gandhi, Indira, 1917-1984</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Graham, Katharine, 1917-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Johnson, Philip, 1906-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Reagan, Nancy, 1923-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Helm, John</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Knoll, Walter C.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Raseman, Rachel de Wolfe</persname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh">Hans G. Knoll Furniture Company</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh">Knoll Associates, inc.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh">Knoll International, inc.</corpname>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>


<!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->
<!-- START DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->


<dsc type="combined" id="a23">
<head>Series Descriptions/Container Listing</head>

<c01 level="series"> 
<did> 
<unitid>Series 1:</unitid> 
<unittitle>Biographical Material, 
<unitdate>1932-1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
<physdesc>(Box 1; 1 portfolio)</physdesc> 
</did> 
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series comprises a spiral-bound portfolio designed and
compiled by Knoll Bassett to "briefly chart the direction of my life from 1932
onward." The portfolio documents her artistic development during her years at
Kingswood School and Cranbrook Academy of Art; her work at Knoll Associates
including the presentation of Knoll showrooms and work undertaken for a variety
of corporate clients; and personal architecture projects in Vermont and
Florida. Included are copies of designs from all periods of her career, and
copies of letters and photographs of individuals and significant events
throughout her life. Biographical text, written by Knoll Bassett, accompanies
the material.</p> 
</scopecontent> 
<arrangement>
<p>Included are copies of designs from all periods of her career, and
copies of letters and photographs of individuals and significant events
throughout her life. Biographical text, written by Knoll Bassett, accompanies
the material.</p>
</arrangement> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">1</container> 
<container type="folder">1</container> 
<unittitle>Portfolio: A Chronology of Florence Knoll Bassett from
1932 Onward, compiled 
<unitdate>1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
</c01> 
<c01 level="series"> 
<did> 
<unitid>Series 2:</unitid> 
<unittitle>Selected Publications, 
<unitdate>1946-1990, 1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
<physdesc>(Box 1; 1 portfolio)</physdesc> 
</did> 
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series comprises a spiral-bound portfolio of copies of
articles documenting Knoll Bassett's career in various art and design
publications, newspapers, and encyclopedias. See Series 4 for additional printed material.</p> 
</scopecontent> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">1</container> 
<container type="folder">2</container> 
<unittitle>Portfolio: Selected Publications from 1946 until 1990,
compiled 
<unitdate>1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
</c01> 
<c01 level="series"> 
<did> 
<unitid>Series 3:</unitid> 
<unittitle>Drawings, Sketches, and Designs, 
<unitdate>1932-1984, 1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
<physdesc>(Boxes 1-2; 2 portfolios)</physdesc> 
</did> 
<scopecontent> 
<p>The first item in this series is a portfolio of original, and
copies of, drawings, sketches, plans, and miscellany, such as two greeting
cards designed by Hans and Florence Knoll, in addition to copies of printed
matter and photographs of projects undertaken by Knoll Associates. The majority
of the designs were executed by Knoll Bassett for her own use or as more formal
presentations for clients, but there are also copies of sketches by others
including Hans Knoll and Andy Warhol. The material includes the original
drawing for Knoll Bassett's first house design at Kingswood School, executed in
1932. Material relating to Knoll projects illustrate Knoll Bassett's practice
of using three-dimensional models with fabric swatches applied to furniture
layout plans for client presentations, a technique which later became a
standard in the profession. The portfolio is annotated by Knoll Bassett.</p> 
<p>A spiral-bound portfolio containing sketches by Knoll Bassett of a
cruise of the Greek Islands in 1967 can also be found here.</p> 
</scopecontent> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>  
<unittitle>Portfolio: Drawings and Sketches, 
<unitdate>1932-1984, compiled 1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">2</container> 
<container type="folder">1</container> 
<unittitle>Portfolio: Greek Islands, 
<unitdate>1967</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
</c01> 
<c01 level="series"> 
<did> 
<unitid>Series 4:</unitid> 
<unittitle>Photographs and Printed Material, 
<unitdate>1956-1997, 1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
<physdesc>(Box 2; 1 portfolio, 1 book)</physdesc> 
</did> 
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series contains a spiral-bound portfolio of six photographic
prints of Knoll Bassett with clients and colleagues, including Eero Saarinen,
from the 1950s and 1960s, followed by printed material from 1959 to 1997
documenting her career. A copy of the book, <emph render="italic">Knoll
Design</emph>, can also be found here. See Series 2 for additional printed material.</p> 
</scopecontent> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">2</container> 
<container type="folder">2</container> 
<unittitle>Portfolio: Photographs of Florence Knoll and Others and
Articles in Newspapers and Magazines, 
<unitdate>1956-1997, compiled 1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>  
<unittitle>Book: <emph render="italic">Knoll Design, </emph>by Eric
Larrabee and Massimo Vignelli, Harry N. Abrams Inc., New York, 
<unitdate>1985</unitdate></unittitle> 
<physdesc>(not scanned)</physdesc></did> 
</c02> 
</c01> 
<c01 level="series"> 
<did> 
<unitid>Series 5:</unitid> 
<unittitle>Subject Files, 
<unitdate>circa 1930s-1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
<physdesc>(Box 3; 1.0 linear ft.)</physdesc> 
</did> 
<scopecontent> 
<p>The series contains original, and copies of notes, letters,
drawings, sketches, plans, photographic material, and printed matter, as well
as historical notes written by Knoll Bassett. Originals of some of the material
in Series 1 can be found here.</p> 
<p>Folders 1 and 2 contain material relating to Knoll Bassett's
education and her relationship with the Saarinen family, including original
illustrated letters from Eero Saarinen. The majority of the material relates to
projects undertaken by the Knoll Planning Unit, including showroom designs and
some of the company's most important and innovative projects for corporate
clients. The files typically contain annotated plans and sketches in addition
to photographs, transparencies, and negatives of each project. Specific aspects
of the Planning Unit's operations, such as the development of textiles and
graphics, are also documented here, as are the individual contributions of
early Knoll designers. Material relating to personal projects undertaken by
Knoll Bassett in Vermont and Florida is also included here.</p> 
<p>This series was arranged by Knoll Bassett in numbered folders,
some of which contain two or more related sub folders which are indicated by
an indent in the Container Listing.</p> 
</scopecontent> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">1</container> 
<unittitle>Kingswood; Cranbrook Academy of Art,
<unitdate>circa 1930s, 1983-1994, undated</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
<scopecontent><p>(Kingswood includes photographs of
Rachel de Wolfe Raseman, taken 1936; Cranbrook includes photos of Eliel and Eero Saarinen and Carl Milles)</p></scopecontent>
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">2</container> 
<unittitle>Eero Saarinen, Letters and "Architecture History Lesson"
Drawings; Loja Saarinen, Original Model and Photographs of Model
of Dress, 
<unitdate>1935-1936, 1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">3</container> 
<unittitle>Coral Gables, Florida; New York City, 
<unitdate>circa 1950s, undated</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did>
<scopecontent><p>(includes photographs of Sutton Place and Manhattan house residences)</p></scopecontent> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>  
<unittitle>Vermont House: Main House, Guest House, Farm Buildings and View, Tennis Barn and Studio, <unitdate>circa 1980s-circa 1990s</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">5</container>  
<unittitle>Florence Knoll Furniture Designs: Article by Craig Miller, Seating and Tables, Storage Units, Office Furniture and Dormitory Design, <unitdate>circa 1940s-1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">6</container> 
<unittitle>Early Knoll Designers, Furniture, 
<unitdate>circa 1930s-circa 1940s, 1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">7</container> 
<unittitle>Knoll Graphics, Herbert Matter, 
<unitdate>circa 1950s-circa 1960s, 1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>  
<unittitle>Knoll Textiles, 
<unitdate>circa 1950s-circa 1960s, 1988, 1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">9</container> 
<unittitle>Knoll Exhibitions: Mies van der Rohe; Knoll au Louvre; Dow Chemical and Detroit Institute of Arts; Textilien aus U.S.A., <unitdate>circa 1940s-1999, undated</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">10</container>  
<unittitle>Knoll Showroom, 601 Madison Avenue, New York, 
<unitdate>1948, 1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">11</container> 
<unittitle>Knoll Showrooms, Dallas, Paris, and Miami, 
<unitdate>1947-1959</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">12</container> 
<unittitle>Knoll Showroom, 575 Madison Avenue, New York, 
<unitdate>1951, 1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">13</container> 
<unittitle>Knoll Showroom, Chicago, 
<unitdate>1953, 1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">14</container> 
<unittitle>Knoll Showroom, San Francisco, 
<unitdate>1954</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">15</container> 
<unittitle>Knoll Showroom, Milan, 
<unitdate>1956</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">16</container> 
<unittitle>Knoll Showroom, Los Angeles, 
<unitdate>1960</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">17</container>  
<unittitle>Columbia Broadcasting Systems, Inc. (CBS), Madison Avenue,
<unitdate>1952-1954, 1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">18</container> 
<unittitle>Look Publications, 
<unitdate>circa 1962</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">19</container>  
<unittitle>Connecticut General Building, 
<unitdate>circa 1950s, 1984</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">20</container> 
<unittitle>H. J. Heinz Company, 
<unitdate>1999, undated</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container> 
<container type="folder">21</container> 
<unittitle>First National Bank of Miami and Southeast Bank, 
<unitdate>1957, 1982, 1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">22</container>  
<unittitle>Columbia Broadcasting Systems, Inc. (CBS): General, 35th Floor, Frank Stanton's Office Suite, <unitdate>1964</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">23</container>  
<unittitle>Knoll Bassett's Inventory of Box 3, <unitdate>1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
</c01> 
<c01 level="series"> 
<did> 
<unitid>Series 6:</unitid> 
<unittitle>Letters, 
<unitdate>circa 1930s-2000</unitdate></unittitle> 
<physdesc>(Box 4; 7 folders)</physdesc> 
</did> 
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series contains letters selected by Knoll Bassett to document
significant events throughout her life and career. As in Series 5, the
originals for some of the material in Series 1 can be found here.
Correspondents include Carl Milles, Eero and Loja Saarinen, David Rockefeller,
Katharine Graham, Nancy Reagan, Indira Ghandi, Frank Stanton, and Isamu
Noguchi. In addition to letters the series also contains printed matter and
other material of interest, such as an original invitation with a guest list
and photographs from a 1947 party given by Howard Meyers, Editor-in-Chief of
<emph render="italic">Architectural Forum</emph> a wedding card made by Charles
and Ray Eames on the occasion of Florence Knoll's marriage to Harry Hood
Bassett in 1958; and an invitation from the White House from 1976.</p> 
<p>The letters are arranged by decade.</p> 
</scopecontent>
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">4</container> 
<container type="folder">1</container> 
<unittitle>Knoll Bassett's Inventory of Box 4, Letters,
<unitdate>1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02>  
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">4</container> 
<container type="folder">2</container> 
<unittitle>Letters (1930s-1940s), 
<unitdate>1936-1947, 1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">4</container> 
<container type="folder">3</container> 
<unittitle>Letters (1950s), 
<unitdate>1953-1959</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">4</container> 
<container type="folder">4</container> 
<unittitle>Letters (1960s), 
<unitdate>1961-1968</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">4</container> 
<container type="folder">5</container> 
<unittitle>Letters (1970s), 
<unitdate>1972-1978</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">4</container> 
<container type="folder">6</container> 
<unittitle>Letters (1980s), 
<unitdate>1980-2000</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">4</container> 
<container type="folder">7</container> 
<unittitle>Letters (1990s), 
<unitdate>1984, 1991-1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
</c01> 
<c01 level="series"> 
<did> 
<unitid>Series 7:</unitid> 
<unittitle>Awards, 
<unitdate>1954-1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
<physdesc>(Box 4; 6 folders)</physdesc> 
</did> 
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series documents some of the awards and honorary degrees
presented to Knoll Bassett over the course of her career, including the Gold
Medal for Industrial Design awarded by the American Institute of Architects in
1961 and the Total Design Award given by the American Society of Interior
Designers in 1977. Materials include award certificates with related
correspondence and printed material. In some cases there are also notes for, or
the text of, remarks given by Knoll Bassett upon acceptance of an award.</p> 
<p>The material is arranged by decade.</p> 
</scopecontent> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">4</container> 
<container type="folder">8</container> 
<unittitle>Knoll Bassett's Inventory of Box 4, Awards,
<unitdate>1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02>
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">4</container> 
<container type="folder">9</container> 
<unittitle>Awards (1950s), 
<unitdate>1954-1956</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">4</container> 
<container type="folder">10</container> 
<unittitle>Awards (1960s), 
<unitdate>1961-1965</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">4</container> 
<container type="folder">11</container> 
<unittitle>Awards (1970s), 
<unitdate>1976-1979</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">4</container> 
<container type="folder">12</container> 
<unittitle>Awards (1980s), 
<unitdate>1982-1989</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
<c02> 
<did> 
<container type="box">4</container> 
<container type="folder">13</container> 
<unittitle>Awards (1990s), 
<unitdate>1990-1999</unitdate></unittitle> 
</did> 
</c02> 
</c01> 


</dsc>


<!-- END DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->
</archdesc>
</ead>



