<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "/eadcb/shared/ead/ead.dtd">

<ead audience="external" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
<eadid mainagencycode="DSI-AAA" countrycode="us" url="http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/findingaids/xml/.xml"></eadid>

<filedesc>
	<titlestmt>
		<titleproper>Belle Krasne Ribicoff</titleproper>
		<subtitle>A Finding Aid to the Belle Krasne Ribicoff Papers, <date type="inclusive">1942-circa 2010</date>, <date type="bulk">  bulk 1945-2004</date>, in the Archives of American Art</subtitle>
		<author>by Joy Weiner</author>
	</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
	<publisher>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</publisher>
	<date type="publication">May 04, 2011</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Joy Weiner on
<date>May 04, 2011</date>
</creation>
<langusage><language>English</language></langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>

<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory">
<did>
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
		<corpname>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</corpname>
	</repository>

	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100">Krasne Ribicoff, Belle</persname>
	</origination>

	<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Belle Krasne Ribicoff papers</unittitle>

	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f">1942-circa 2010,  bulk 1945-2004</unitdate>

	<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a">1.6 linear feet</physdesc>

	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">The papers of Belle Krasne Ribicoff measure 1.6 linear feet and date from 1942-circa 2010, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1945-2004.  Papers include biographical materials; correspondence with artists, art historians, writers, museum directors, and others; individual files relating to Belle and Irving Ribicoff's art collection and the Friends of Abe Ribicoff's campaign for the United States Senate; artwork; printed material, e.g., clippings, announcements, exhibition catalogues, brochures; and photographs.  The collection documents Ribicoff's career as an arts editor, critic, and her involvement in civic and arts organizations for the State of Connecticut.
</abstract>  
<!-- ONLY USE LANGMATERIAL TO NOTE LANGUAGES OTHER THAN OR IN ADDITION TO ENGLISH -->
	
	<langmaterial label="Language of Materials:">Some records are in<language>
French</language> and <language>Italian</language>.
</langmaterial>
</did>


<!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION GOES HERE: -->

<acqinfo encodinganalog="561" id="a19">
<head>Provenance</head>
<p>The collection was donated by Belle Krasne Ribicoff to the Archives of American Art in 2008.</p>
</acqinfo>


<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 1" id="a6">
<head>Related Material</head>
<p>Also found at the Archives of American Art is Belle Krasne's letter to Philip Pavia,
May 14, 1954 on microfilm reel 3470.</p>
</relatedmaterial>

<processinfo encodinganalog="583" id="a20">
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>The collection was processed by Joy Weiner in 2011.</p>
</processinfo>

<prefercite encodinganalog="510" id="a18">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Belle Krasne Ribicoff papers, 1942-circa 2010  bulk 1945-2004. Archives of American
Art, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
</prefercite>

<accessrestrict id="a14" encodinganalog="506">
<head>Restrictions on Access</head>
<p>Use of original material requires an appointment.</p>
<p>Letters from Jean Bazaine to Belle Krasne Ribicoff and sketches of Sarai Ribicoff by William Bailey are access restricted. Their use requires written permission. </p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="a15">
<head>Ownership and Literary Rights</head>
<p>The Belle Krasne Ribicoff  papers are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
</userestrict>

<!-- END ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->

<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GO HERE: -->

<bioghist altrender="biography" encodinganalog="545" id="a2">
<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>Belle Krasne Ribicoff (b. 1924) lives in Hartford, Connecticut and has served as an arts editor, critic, and university administrator.</p>
<p>Ribicoff was born and raised in New York City.  She graduated Phi Beta Kappa with a degree in art history from Vassar College in 1945.  After a brief stint with an advertising agency in New York, Ribicoff became Assistant Editor at <emph render="italic">Magazine of Art</emph> (1946-1947), where she developed an interest in contemporary art.  She served as editor for such publications as <emph render="italic">Art News</emph> (1948-1949), <emph render="italic">Art Digest </emph>(1949-1954), and <emph render="italic">Craft Horizons </emph>(1954-1955).</p>
<p>In 1955, she married Irving S. Ribicoff (1915-1994), an attorney and moved to
Hartford, Connecticut.  The Ribicoffs' had two daughters, Dara (b. 1956) and
Sarai (1957-1980).</p>
<p>Ribicoff has held various positions at the University of Hartford:  Development Director at the Hartford School of Art (1980-1981), Development Liaison to the Office of President (1982-1988), and Associate Vice President for Public Affairs (1980-1983).  Belle Krasne Ribicoff has served as a professional volunteer for educational and cultural organizations in Connecticut; she has been involved in efforts to make the arts a part of the school curriculum.
She was Vice-President of the Hartford Board of Education (1961-1967; 1965-1971) and was Chairman of the State of Connecticut's Commission on the Arts (1965-1971).   Ribicoff is a Life Director at the Hartford Stage Company and a Life Regent at the University of Hartford.  She is a Sterling Fellows at Yale University and sits on the President's Advisory Committee at Vassar College.</p>
<p>Belle Krasne Ribicoff has received recognition for her professional and public service contributions by a number of institutions.  In 1954, she received the Frank Jewett Mather Award for critical writing from the College Art Association. Other honors have included: Charter Oak Leadership Medal for Distinguished Service (1968), the University of Hartford Medal for Distinguished Service (1995), and the Spirit of Vassar award for outstanding commitment and service to Vassar or another community (2005).</p>
<!-- add additional <p></p> tags as necessary -->


<!-- Delete the above, beginning with <chronlist> and ending with </chronlist> if the bioghist is text only: -->
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520" id="a3">
<head>Scope and Content Note</head>
<p>The papers of Belle Krasne Ribicoff measure 1.6 linear feet and date from 1942-circa
2010, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1945-2004.  Papers include biographical 
materials; correspondence with artists, art historians, writers, museum directors, and       
others; individual files relating to Belle and Irving Ribicoff's art collection and the Friends of Abe Ribicoff's campaign for the United States Senate; artwork; printed material, 
e.g., clippings, announcements, exhibition catalogues, brochures; and photographs.  The 
collection documents Ribicoff's career as an arts editor, critic, and her involvement in civic and arts organizations for the State of Connecticut.</p>
<p>Biographical materials include documentation of the Buttenweiser Prize awarded to Belle Krasne by the Art History Departmental Honors at Vassar College in 1945 and curriculum vitae.</p>
<p>Correspondence, primarily incoming letters consists of letters, postcards, draft versions, and copies of e-mails.  Belle Krasne Ribicoff was friends with many artists; their
letters focus on daily activities, work, and the art world.  Among the correspondents are Oscar and Eleanor Chelminsky, Joseph Cornell, Piero and Virginia Dorazio, John and Rae Ferren, Helen Frankenthaler, James Fitzsimmons, Adolph Gottlieb, John Graham, Ellsworth Kelly, Frank Modell, George L.K. Morris, Philip Pearlstein, Eero Saarinen, David Smith, and Adja Yunkers.  There is substantial correspondence from Ben Benn, Sidney Geist, Leon Hartley, Ralph Rosenborg, and Theodore Roszak.  Also found are love letters to Belle Krasne Ribicoff from Jean Bazaine.  Many of the artists' letters are illustrated.   Of note, are a letter from Carl Holty to J.B. Neumann and an artist's statement written by Adolph Gottlieb.</p>
<p>Ribicoff had a professional and personal relationship with a number of prominent writers, actors, and other individuals known for their work in the arts, such as Edward Albee, Claire Bloom, Peter DeVries, Horton Foote, Elia Kazan, Mark Lamos, Estelle Parsons, Karl Shapiro, Cornelia Otis Skinner, and P.L. Travers. There are letters from museum directors, art historians, and other well-known cultural figures, such as Dore Ashton, Clement Greenberg, Balcomb Greene, Rene d'Harnoncourt, Pierre Matisse, E. P. Richardson, Andrew C. Ritchie, Harry Salpeter, Curt  Valentin, and Mark Van Doren.   Also found are files of holiday cards, many original artwork; letters to Ribicoff upon her departure from <emph render="italic">Art Digest</emph>; letters from representatives at Storm King Art Center Museum and the Wadsworth Atheneum; and letters from unidentified correspondents. </p>
<p>The Ribicoff collection relates to the personal art collection of Belle and Irving Ribicoff; materials document the purchase and sale of artwork and the lending of artwork for exhibitions.  There is a file of petition letters sponsored by the Friends of Abe Ribicoff campaign for the United States Senate.</p>
<p>Original artwork includes prints by Jean Arp and Adja Yunkers and pencil sketches
of Sarai Ribicoff by William Bailey.  Printed material consists of news clippings;
a periodical; exhibition announcements; brochures; an offprint of an article by Cleve Gray; and miscellaneous printed material.</p>
<p>Photographs contain black and white photographs of Belle Krasne Ribicoff, Ben and   Velida Benn, Richard Krautheimer, and of the jurors attending the Carnegie International exhibition (circa 1954), including Jean Bazaine, Rico Lebrun, Eric Newton, and James Thrall Soby.</p> </scopecontent>

<arrangement encodinganalog="351$b" id="a5">
<head>Arrangement</head>
<p>The collection is arranged into 7 series: </p>
<list>
<item>Series 1: Biographical Material, 1945, circa 2010  (Box 1; 1 folder)</item>
<item>Series 2: Belle Krasne Ribicoff Correspondence, 1942-2007 (Boxes 1, 3; 1.0 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 3: The Ribicoff Collection, 1949-1988 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 4: Friends of Abe Ribicoff Campaign, 1968 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 5: Artwork, circa 1950s-1978 (Box 1, OV 4; 0.1 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 6: Printed Material, 1948-2000 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 7: Photographs, 1945-circa 2007 (Boxes 1-2; 0.1 linear feet)</item>
</list></arrangement>

<!-- END TOP LEVEL METADATA -->

<!-- CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS GO HERE: -->

<controlaccess id="a12">
<head>Names and Subject Terms</head>
<p>This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms: </p>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>

<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Albee, Edward, 1928-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Bloom, Claire, 1931-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">De Vries, Peter, 1910-1993</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Foote, Horton</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Kazan, Elia</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Lamos, Mark</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Lebrun, Rico, 1900-1964</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Parsons, Estelle</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Ribicoff, Abraham, 1910-1998</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Shapiro, Karl Jay, 1913-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Skinner, Cornelia Otis, 1901-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Soby, James Thrall, 1906-1979</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Travers, P. L.(Pamela Lyndon), 1899-1996</persname>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Storm King Art Center</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Wadsworth Atheneum</corpname>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects-Topical:</head>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Art, American</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Art--Collectors and collecting</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Art critics</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Editors</subject>
</controlaccess>


<controlaccess>
<head>Types of Materials:</head>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Christmas cards</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Drafts (documents)</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Illustrated letters</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Photographs</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Postcards</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Prints</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Sketches</genreform>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Names:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Arp, Jean, 1887-1966</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Ashton, Dore</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Bailey, William, 1930-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Bazaine, Jean, 1904-2001</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Benn, Ben, 1884-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Chelimsky, Oscar</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Cornell, Joseph</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">D'Harnoncourt, Rene, 1901-1968</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Dorazio, Virginia Dortch</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Dorazio, Piero, 1927-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Ferren, John, 1905-1970</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Fitzsimmons, James, 1919-1985</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Frankenthaler, Helen,1928-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Geist, Sidney</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Gottlieb, Adolph, 1903-1974</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Graham, John, 1887-1961</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Greenberg, Clement, 1909-1994</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Greene, Balcomb, 1904-1990</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Holty, Carl, 1900-1973</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Kelly, Ellsworth, 1923-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Krautheimer, Richard, 1897-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Matisse, Pierre, 1900-1989</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Morris, George L. K. 1905-1975</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Pearlstein, Philip, 1924-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Richardson, Edgar Preston, 1902-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Ritchie, Andrew Carnduff</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Rosenborg, Ralph M., 1913-1992</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Roszak, Theodore, 1907-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Saarinen, Eero, 1910-1961</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Salpeter, Harry</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Smith, David, 1906-1965</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Valentin, Curt, 1902-1954</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Van Doren, Mark, 1894-1972</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Yunkers, Adja, 1900-1983</persname>
</controlaccess>

</controlaccess>


<!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->

<!-- START DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->


<dsc type="combined" id="a23">
<head>Series Descriptions/Container Listing</head>

<!-- use this format if you have series only, no subseries -->
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 1: </unitid><unittitle>Biographical Material, <unitdate>1945, circa 2010   </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 1 folder)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series contains documentation for the Buttonweiser Prize awarded to Belle
Krasne Ribicoff by the Art History Department at Vassar College and curriculum vitae.</p>
<!-- If the series contains an index provide a link to the index here:

<note><p><ref target="seriesindex#"></ref></p></note>
--></scopecontent>

<c02><did>
	<container type="box">1</container>
	<container type="folder">1</container>
	<unittitle>Buttonweiser Prize and Curriculum Vitae, </unittitle><unitdate>1945, circa 2010</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 2: </unitid><unittitle>Belle Krasne Ribicoff Correspondence, 1942-2007  <unitdate> </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Boxes 1, 3; 1.0 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Correspondence spans over sixty years, with the bulk dating from 1949-2007.  Belle
Krasne Ribicoff's correspondence, mostly incoming letters, consists of letters, drafts,     
postcards, and copies of e-mails.  Some letters are illustrated; a few contain original 
artwork.  Many letters have attachments, such as invoices, price lists, notes, sketches, printed  material, clippings, exhibition catalogues, invitations, and photographs.</p>
<p>Ribicoff was friends with many artists. Their letters to her concern daily activities,
work, and the art world.  Among the correspondents were Charles Burchfield, Oscar and Eleanor Chelminsky, Joseph Cornell, Piero and Virginia Dorazio, John and Rae Ferren, Helen Frankenthaler, Alberto Giacometti, John Graham, Russell Lynes, Frank Modell, George L.K. Morris, Philip Pearlstein, David Smith, John Von Wicht, Adja Yunkers, among others.  There are individual artists' files for Ben Benn, Sidney Geist, Leon Hartley, Arnold Newman, Ralph Rosenborg, and Theodore Roszak. Two items of interest: Carl Holty's letter to J.B. Neumann discusses the use of realism in his work and an artist's statement by Adolph Gottlieb.  Marcel Duchamp correspondence consists of two black and white photographs of the artist: a print by Victor Obsatz inscribed to Belle Krasne Ribicoff and a print by Naomi Savage, and a reproduction of an artwork.</p>
<p>Ribicoff's friends and colleagues included writers, actors, and other well-known individuals associated with theatre and film, such as Edward Albee, Claire Bloom, Horton Foote, Elia Kazan, Peter De Vries, Mark Lamos, Estelle Parsons, Cornelia Otis Skinner, and P.T. Travers. Also found are letters from art historians, museum directors, gallery dealers, such as Dore Ashton, S. Lane Faison, Balcomb Greene, Rene d'Harnoncourt, Pierre Matisse, Andrew C. Ritchie, Harry Salpeter, Curt Valentin and others.  Files also contain letters to Belle Krasne Ribicoff from friends and colleagues relating to her departure from <emph render="italic">Art Digest</emph>; letters between Ribicoff and representatives of the Storm King Art Center Museum pertaining to her donation of unpublished letters by David Smith to the museum; and correspondence with the Wadsworth Atheneum.  Included is a small file of unidentified correspondents.</p> </scopecontent>
<arrangement><p>Correspondence, including files with individuals where there is substantive correspondence is arranged alphabetically; letters within the folders are filled in chronological order.</p></arrangement>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>A, <unitdate>1948-2007, undated </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc></did><scopecontent><p>
<list><head></head> 
<item>Addams, Charles</item>
<item>Albee, Edward</item>
<item>Ashton, Dore and Adja Yunkers</item>
<item>Arthur Lénars and Cie</item>
</list></p></scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>B-C, <unitdate>1950-1997</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc></did><scopecontent><p>
<list><head></head> 
<item>Bloom, Claire</item>
<item>Blumenthal, Charles</item>
<item>Burchfield, Charles</item>
<item>Carnegie Institute</item>
<item>Chelminsky, Oscar and Eleanor</item>
<item>Cisneros, Henry G.</item>
<item>College Art Association </item>
<item>Cornell, Joseph</item>
</list></p></scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>D-E, <unitdate>1954-1981, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc></did><scopecontent><p>
<list><head></head> 
<item>D'Harnoncourt, Rene</item>
<item>De Vries, Peter</item>
<item>Dorazio, Piero and Virginia</item>
<item>Edelman, Maurice</item>
<item>Ernst, Jimmy</item>
<item>Evergood, Philip</item>
</list></p></scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>F, <unitdate>1950-1999</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc></did><scopecontent><p>
<list><head></head> 
<item>Ferren, John and Rae</item>
<item>Fitzsimmons, James</item>
<item>Foote, Horton</item>
<item>Frankenthaler, Helen</item>
</list></p></scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>G, <unitdate>1950-1990</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc></did><scopecontent><p>
<list><head></head> 
<item>Gottlieb, Adolph</item>
<item>Glamer, Fritz</item>
<item>Graham, John</item>
<item>Grasso, Ella </item>
<item>Greenberg, Clement</item>
<item>Greene, Balcomb</item>
</list></p></scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>H-L, <unitdate>1950-1997, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc></did><scopecontent><p>
<list><head></head> 
<item>Hagenbech, Marguerite </item>
<item>Holmes, Willard</item>
<item>Holty, Carl</item>
<item>Horowitz, Glenn</item>
<item>J. D. Smith Inter-Ocean, Inc.</item>
<item>Kappel, Philip</item>
<item>Katz, Leslie</item>
<item>Kelly, Ellsworth</item>
<item>Lamos, Mark</item>
<item>Lynes, Russell</item>
</list></p></scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>M-P,<unitdate>1942-2004, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc></did><scopecontent><p>
<list><head></head> 
<item>Marca-Relli, Conrad</item>
<item>Matisse, Pierre</item>
<item>Modell, Frank</item>
<item>Morris, George, L. K.</item>
<item>Nesbit, Alexander</item>
<item>Parsons, Estelle</item>
<item>Pearlstein, Philip</item>
<item>Pittman, Hobson</item>
</list></p></scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>R-S,<unitdate>1946-2001, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc></did><scopecontent><p>
<list><head></head> 
<item></item>
<item>Richardson, E. P.</item>
<item>Ritchie, Andrew C. (The Museum of Modern Art, New York)</item>
<item>Robinson, Frank</item>
<item>Rowland, Governor John C. </item>
<item>Ryan, Anne</item>
<item>Saarinen, Eero</item>
<item>Salpeter, Harry</item>
<item>Schlesinger, Arthur, Jr.</item>
<item>Shapiro, Karl</item>
<item>Shikler, Aaron</item>
<item>Skinner, Cornelia Otis</item>
<item>Smith, David</item>
<item>Steinberg, Leo</item>
</list></p></scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle>T-Y, <unitdate>1946-1959, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc></did><scopecontent><p>
<list><head></head> 
<item></item>
<item>Toscano, Anonimo</item>
<item>Travers, P. L.</item>
<item>Valentin, Curt</item>
<item>Von Wicht, John</item>
<item>Yunkers, Adja</item>
</list></p></scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle>Bazaine, Jean, <unitdate>1953-1973 </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(See Box 3)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">12-15</container>
<unittitle>Benn, Ben, <unitdate>1954-1988, undated (4 folders)</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">16</container>
<unittitle>Duchamp, Marcel, <unitdate>1951, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">17-20</container>
<unittitle>Geist, Sidney, <unitdate>1953-2005 (4 folders)</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">21-23</container>
<unittitle>Hartley, Leon, <unitdate>1955-1964, undated (3 folders)</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">24</container>
<unittitle>Kazan, Elia, <unitdate>1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">25</container>
<unittitle>Newman, Arnold, <unitdate>1956-2003</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">26-28</container>
<unittitle>Rosenborg, Ralph, <unitdate>1955-1992 (3 folders)</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">29-30</container>
<unittitle>Roszak, Theodore, <unitdate>1951-1962 (2 folders)</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">31</container>
<unittitle>Van Doren, Mark,<unitdate>1967-1971</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">32</container>
<unittitle>Holiday Cards, including Original Artwork, <unitdate>1950-1989</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">33</container>
<unittitle>Letters relating to Belle Krasne Ribicoff's Departure from <emph render="italic">Art Digest,</emph><unitdate>1954</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">1-11</container>
<unittitle>Bazaine, Jean,<unitdate>1953-1973 (11 folders)</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 3: </unitid><unittitle>The Ribicoff Collection, <unitdate>1949-1988</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>The Ribicoff Collection consists of records maintained by Belle Krasne Ribicoff on the
Ribicoffs' personal art collection.  Files document works that were sold or donated and the
lending of artwork for exhibitions, mainly to university museums, including the Hopkins Center Art Galleries at Dartmouth College, Trinity College, Vassar College, and Williams College.</p>
<p>Materials include: correspondence with individuals at museums, galleries, publishers,
and framers; loan agreements, exhibition forms, delivery receipts, and an insurance
endorsement; receipts and invoices for frames and photographic prints of artwork; receipts for purchase of artwork; and consignment receipt, sales confirmation notice, post sales advice, and remittance advices for sale of artwork; and photographs of artwork.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">38-39</container>
<unittitle>	Correspondence, </unittitle><unitdate>1954-1982 (2 folders)</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">40</container>
<unittitle>Loan Agreements, Exhibition Forms, Receipts, and Insurance Endorsement, </unittitle><unitdate>1964</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">41</container>
<unittitle>Receipts and Invoices for Frames and Photographic Prints of Artwork,  </unittitle><unitdate>1955-1977, undated</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">42</container>
<unittitle>Receipts for Purchase of Artwork,1949-1951,undated</unittitle><unitdate></unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">43</container>
<unittitle>Consignment Receipt, Sales Confirmation Notice, Post Sales Advice, and Remittance Advices for Sale of Artwork, </unittitle><unitdate>1988</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">44</container>
<unittitle>Lists,</unittitle><unitdate>1959-1991, undated</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">45</container>
<unittitle>Various Printed Materials, </unittitle><unitdate>1971-1986, undated</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder"> 46-47	</container>
<unittitle>	Photographs of Artwork, </unittitle><unitdate>1988, undated (2 folders)</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 4: </unitid><unittitle>Friends of Abe Ribicoff Campaign, <unitdate>1968   </unitdate></unittitle><physdesc>(Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Files include petition letters for Abraham Ribicoff's reelection to the United States Senate for the State of Connecticut and a clipping of the campaign advertisement sponsored by the Friends of Abe Ribicoff that appeared in the <emph render="italic">New York Times</emph> featuring the list of signatories to the petition.</p>
<p>Scattered notes include individuals who had expressed interest in supporting Ribicoff's nomination.</p></scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">48</container>
<unittitle>	Letters in Support of Abe Ribicoff's Reelection to the United States Senate, </unittitle><unitdate>1968</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">49</container>
<unittitle>	Notes, Loose Envelopes, and Clipping,</unittitle><unitdate>1968</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 5: </unitid><unittitle>Artwork, <unitdate>circa 1950s-1978, </unitdate></unittitle><physdesc>(Boxes 1, OV 4; 0.1 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Artwork includes a color print of a figure by Jean Arp and cover art for <emph render="italic">Art Digest</emph> by Adja Yunkers.  There are two pencil sketches of Sarai Ribicoff by William Bailey.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">50</container>
<unittitle>	Print by Jean Arp, </unittitle><unitdate>undated</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">51 </container>
<unittitle>Cover Art for <emph render="italic">Art Digest</emph> by Adja Yunkers,</unittitle><unitdate>circa 1950s </unitdate>
<physdesc>(Oversized material housed in Box 2)</physdesc></did>	
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">52</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Sketch, </unittitle><unitdate>undated</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">53</container>
<unittitle>Sketches of Sarai Ribicoff by William Bailey, </unittitle><unitdate>1978  </unitdate>
<physdesc>(See OV 4)</physdesc></did>	
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Oversized Cover Art by Adja Yunkers, </unittitle><unitdate>circa 1950s</unitdate>
<physdesc> (Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 51)</physdesc></did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">OV 4</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Oversized Sketches of Sarai Ribicoff by William Bailey, </unittitle><unitdate>1978   </unitdate>
<physdesc> </physdesc></did>	
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 6: </unitid><unittitle>Printed Material, <unitdate>1948-2000 </unitdate></unittitle><physdesc>(Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Printed material houses clippings, mostly reviews of art exhibitions, announcements, exhibition catalogues, and an offprint of an article by Cleve Gray. Included are brochures for the elementary arts education program, Project CREATE directed by Belle Krasne Ribicoff.
</p></scopecontent>
<arrangement><p>Materials are arranged in chronological order.</p></arrangement>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">54</container>
<unittitle>Clippings, </unittitle><unitdate>1979-2000, undated</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">55</container>
<unittitle>Announcements,</unittitle><unitdate>1967-1991, 2004</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">56</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Catalogues, </unittitle><unitdate>1948-1954, 1979              </unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>	 
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">57</container>
<unittitle>Brochures, </unittitle><unitdate>circa 1969</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">58</container>
<unittitle>Offprint, <emph render="italic"> Narcissus in Chaos, Contemporary American Art </emph>by Cleve Gray, </unittitle><unitdate>1959</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>	
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">59</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Printed Material, </unittitle><unitdate>1951, 2000-2004, undated </unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc></did>	
</c02>	
</c01>	
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 7: </unitid><unittitle> Photographs <unitdate>1945-circa 2007  </unitdate></unittitle><physdesc>(Boxes, 1-2; 0.1 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series contains black and white prints of Belle Krasne Ribicoff, Ben and Velida Benn,
Richard Krautheimer and the Carnegie International jury featuring Jean Bazaine, Rico
Lebrun, Eric Newton, and James Thrall Soby. </p>
<p>Also included are black and white snapshots of Belle Krasne Ribicoff at Vassar College and color snapshots of Ribicoff with unidentified colleagues and friends.</p></scopecontent>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">60</container>
<unittitle>Belle Krasne Ribicoff,</unittitle><unitdate> 1945, undated</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">61</container>
<unittitle>Belle Krasne Ribicoff with Colleagues and Friends, </unittitle><unitdate>1940s-circa 2007</unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">62</container>
<unittitle>Ben and Velida Benn and Richard Krautheimer, </unittitle><unitdate>1963, undated </unitdate>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">63-64</container>
<unittitle>Carnegie International Jury, </unittitle><unitdate>circa 1954</unitdate>
<physdesc>(2 folders; Oversized material housed in Box 2)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Carnegie International Jury,</unittitle><unitdate>circa 1954 </unitdate>
<physdesc>(Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 63)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>
</dsc>















	



<!-- END DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->

<!-- OPTIONAL ARCHDESC ELEMENTS -->

<!-- If you have a non-series-related index encode it here: 

<odd encodinganalog="500" id="index1">
<head></head>
<p>
<list>
<item></item>
<item></item>
</list>
</p>
</odd>
-->


<!-- END OPTIONAL DSC ELEMENTS -->


</archdesc>
</ead>

