<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "/eadcb/shared/ead/ead.dtd">

<ead audience="external" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
<eadid mainagencycode="DSI-AAA" countrycode="us" url="http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/findingaids/xml/lemojean.xml">lemojean</eadid>

<filedesc>
	<titlestmt>
		<titleproper>Jean Gabriel Lemoine</titleproper>
		<subtitle>A Finding Aid to the Jean Gabriel Lemoine papers relating to Morgan Russell, <date type="inclusive">1921-1923, 1964</date>, in the Archives of American Art</subtitle>
		<author>by Eric Frazier and Erin Corley</author>
		<sponsor>Funding for the processing and digitization of this collection was provided by the Terra Foundation for American Art.</sponsor>
	</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
	<publisher>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</publisher>
	<date type="publication">August 31, 2007</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Erin Corley on
<date>August 31, 2007</date>
</creation>
<langusage><language></language></langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>

<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory">
<did>
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
		<corpname>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</corpname>
	</repository>

	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100">Lemoine, Jean Gabriel</persname>
	</origination>

	<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Jean Gabriel Lemoine papers relating to Morgan Russell</unittitle>

	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f">1921-1923, 1964 </unitdate>

	<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a">20 items</physdesc>

	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">The Jean Gabriel Lemoine papers relating to Morgan Russell are comprised of 20 items and date from 1921-1923, and 1964. The item dating from 1964 is a typescript of a letter fragment. Included are 17 letters and letter fragments written by Morgan Russell in 1923 to Jean Gabriel Lemoine, art critic for <emph render="italic">L'Echo de Paris</emph>.  In these letters Russell explains his art and the Synchromism style that he developed with Stanton MacDonald-Wright.  Also found are a one page list naming ten paintings in his studio, an article by Lemoine about Russell, and a typed extract about Russell from <emph render="italic">La Peinture Abstraite</emph> by Michel Senghor. </abstract>

	<langmaterial>The papers are in French<language></language>.
	</langmaterial>
</did>


<!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION GOES HERE: -->

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541" id="a19">
<head>Provenance</head>
<p>The papers were transferred to the Archives from the National Collection of Fine Arts (now the Smithsonian American Art Museum) in 1976.  NCFA acquired them as part of a purchase in 1972 of Russell's artwork from Lucien Goldschmidt, Inc.  </p>
</acqinfo>

<separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 0" id="a7">
<head>Separated Material</head>
<p>One annotated exhibition catalog, <emph render="italic">Les Synchromistes: Morgan Russell et S. Macdonald-Wright</emph>, from 1913, and four photographs of Russell's artwork were kept by the Smithsonian American Art Museum and Portrait Gallery Library when they transferred the collection to the Archives of American Art.  These items are also available on microfilm reel 1190 at the Archives of American Art.</p>
</separatedmaterial>

<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 1" id="a6">
<head>Related Material</head>
<p>Also available at the Archives of American Art are the Stanton Macdonald-Wright letters to Morgan Russell, 1913-1938, found on microfilm reel 1266.  Microfilm reels 4524-4542 contain Morgan Russell papers that were loaned for filming by the Montclair Art Museum  in 1991.</p>
</relatedmaterial>
 
<altformavail id="a17" encodinganalog="530">
<head>Alternative Forms Available</head>
<p>The Jean Gabriel Lemoine papers relating to Morgan Russell were digitized in 2008 and are available on the Archives of American Art's website.</p>
</altformavail>

<processinfo encodinganalog="583" id="a20">
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>The papers were microfilmed upon receipt on microfilm reel 1190. The collection was fully processed by Eric Frazier and Erin Corley in 2006-2007 and digitized in 2008 with funding provided by the Terra Foundation for American Art.</p>
</processinfo>

<prefercite encodinganalog="510" id="a18">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Jean Gabriel Lemoine papers relating to Morgan Russell, 1921-1923, 1964. Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
</prefercite>

<accessrestrict id="a14" encodinganalog="506">
<head>Restrictions on Access</head>
<p>The collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="a15">
<head>Ownership and Literary Rights</head>
<p>The Jean Gabriel Lemoine papers relating to Morgan Russell are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
</userestrict>


<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GO HERE: -->


<bioghist altrender="biography" encodinganalog="545" id="a2">
<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>Jean Gabriel Lemoine was an art critic for <emph render="italic">L'Echo de Paris</emph> at the time that he corresponded with abstract painter Morgan Russell (1886-1953).  Lemoine also wrote for <emph render="italic">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</emph>, <emph render="italic">Revue Belge d'Archeologie et d'histoire de l'Art</emph> and <emph render="italic">Beaux Arts Magazine</emph>.  Morgan Russell studied at the Art Students League in New York with James Earle Fraser and Robert Henri from 1906 to 1907. His first trip to Europe in 1906 was sponsored by Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, and he returned to Paris in 1908 and joined the Academie Matisse.  He settled in Paris and did not return to the United States until 1946.  In 1911 he studied with Canadian color theorist Ernest Tudor-Hart.  Also at this time he met fellow artist Stanton Macdonald-Wright with whom he developed the theories of Synchromism. In 1913 he and Macdonald-Wright exhibited together as Synchromists at the Bernheim-Jeune gallery, Paris, where they attracted the attention of French critics, including Lemoine.  Russell continued to paint abstract works until 1930 when he began painting large-scale religious works.</p>
<!-- add additional <p></p> tags as necessary -->
<!-- Delete the above, beginning with <chronlist> and ending with </chronlist> if the bioghist is text only: -->
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520" id="a3">
<head>Scope and Content Note</head>
<p>The Jean Gabriel Lemoine papers relating to Morgan Russell are comprised of 20 items and date from 1921-1923 and 1964.  Included are 17 letters and letter fragments written by Morgan Russell in 1923 to Jean Gabriel Lemoine, art critic for <emph render="italic">L'Echo de Paris</emph>.  One item dates from 1964 and is a typescript of a letter fragment.  In these letters Russell explains his art and the Synchromism style that he developed with Stanton MacDonald-Wright.  Also found are a one page list naming ten paintings in his studio, written in 1921 in Morgan Russell's hand, a news clipping of article by Lemoine about Russell, and a typed extract about Russell from <emph render="italic">La Peinture Abstraite</emph> by Michel Senghor. All of the items in the collection are in French.  The collection also includes a few notes about the items in each folder, probably  written by Lemoine.</p>
</scopecontent>

<controlaccess id="a12">
<head>Index Terms</head>
<p>This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:   </p>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>

<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Macdonald-Wright, Stanton, 1890-1973</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Russell, Morgan, 1886-1953</persname>

</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects-Topical:</head>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Art critics--France--Paris</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Synchromism (Art)</subject>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Names:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Senghor, Michael</persname>
</controlaccess>

</controlaccess>


<!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->

<!-- CONTINUE TOP-LEVEL METADATA HERE -->

<arrangement encodinganalog="351$b" id="a5">
<head>Arrangement</head>
<p>Due to the small size of this collection, items are arranged into one series. </p>
<list>
<item>Series 1: Jean Gabriel Lemoine papers relating to Morgan Russell, 1921-1923, 1964 (Box 1; 5 folders)</item>

</list>
</arrangement>

















<!-- START DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->

<dsc type="combined" id="a23">
<head>Series Descriptions/Container Listing</head>

<!-- use this format if you have series only, no subseries -->
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 1: </unitid><unittitle>Jean Gabriel Lemoine papers relating to Morgan Russell, <unitdate>1921-1923, 1964</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 5 folders)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>The Jean Gabriel Lemoine papers relating to Morgan Russell are comprised of 20 items dating from 1921-1923, and 1964. Included are 17 letters and letter fragments written by Morgan Russell in 1923 to Jean Gabriel Lemoine, art critic for <emph render="italic">L'Echo de Paris</emph>.  One letter fragment includes a typescript in French dating from 1964. In these letters Russell explains his art and the Synchromism style that he developed with Stanton MacDonald-Wright.  Also found are a one page list naming ten paintings in his studio, written in 1921 in Morgan Russell's hand, a news clipping of article by Lemoine about Russell, and a typed extract about Russell from <emph render="italic">La Peinture Abstraite</emph> by Michel Senghor. Also found are a few notes about the items in each folder, possibly written by Lemoine.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container> 
<container type="folder">1-2</container>
<unittitle>Letters from Morgan Russell to Jean Gabriel Lemoine, <unitdate>1923</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container> 
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>List of Works in Russell's Studio, <unitdate>1921</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container> 
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Typed Excerpt from <emph render="italic">Le Peinture Abstraite</emph> about Morgan Russell, <unitdate>1964</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container> 
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>News Clipping of Article by Lemoine about Russell, <unitdate>1921</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

</c01>
</dsc>


<!-- END DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->
</archdesc>
</ead>





