<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "/eadcb/shared/ead/ead.dtd">

<ead audience="external" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
<eadid mainagencycode="DSI-AAA" countrycode="us" url="http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/findingaids/xml/millflor.xml">millflor</eadid>

<filedesc>
	<titlestmt>
		<titleproper>Flora Whitney Miller</titleproper>
		<subtitle>A Finding Aid to the Flora Whitney Miller papers regarding Kay Sage, <date type="inclusive">1915-1982</date> <date type="bulk"></date>, in the Archives of American Art</subtitle>
		<author>by Erin Corley</author>
		<sponsor>Funding for the processing and digitization of this collection was provided by the Terra Foundation for American Art.</sponsor>
	</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
	<publisher>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</publisher>
	<date type="publication">December 18, 2006</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Erin Corley on
<date>December 18, 2006</date>
</creation>
<langusage><language>English</language></langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>

<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory">
<did>
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
		<corpname>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</corpname>
	</repository>

	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100">Miller, Flora Whitney </persname>
	</origination>

	<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Flora Whitney Miller papers regarding Kay Sage</unittitle>

	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f">1915-1982</unitdate>

	<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a">168 items</physdesc>

	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">This small collection of papers (168 items) of socialite, art collector and patron Flora Whitney Miller document Miller's life-long friendship with surrealist artist Kay Sage and date from 1915 to circa 1982. Found within the papers are 79 letters written to Miller by Sage; four letters written to Miller after Sage's suicide about Sage, and one reply letter; typescripts of 63 poems written by Sage, one handwritten poem by Sage, two Sage exhibition catalogs, and 18 snapshot photographs of Sage, Miller, and their friends. Documentation of Miller's career is not found within the papers. </abstract>

	
</did>



<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GO HERE: -->


<bioghist altrender="biography" encodinganalog="545" id="a2">
<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>Flora Whitney Miller (1897-1986) was born into two prominent New York families as the daughter of Gertrude Vanderbilt and Harry Payne Whitney.  She attended the Brearley School in New York and Foxcroft School in Middleburg, Virginia, where she met and became close life-long friends with the artist Kay Sage.  In 1916 Flora made her debut and, shortly after became engaged to Quentin Roosevelt, son of President Theodore Roosevelt.  Before they married, Quentin died tragically in 1918 when his plane was shot down in Germany.   While attending Columbia University, she met Roderick Tower and married him in 1920.  She gave birth to a daughter Pamela in 1921 and a son Whitney in 1923, and was divorced from Tower in France in 1925.  In 1927 she married G. Macculloch Miller and had another two children, Flora in 1928 and Leverett in 1931.</p><p>
Flora Whitney Miller grew up in New York and worked closely with her mother Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, meeting and befriending many artists, dealers, and art patrons.  She helped her mother plan the founding of the Whitney Museum of Art and served on the museum's board, serving as President after her mother's death in 1941 until 1966, and as Chairman from 1966 through 1974. Miller died on July 18, 1986. </p>
<!-- add additional <p></p> tags as necessary -->
<!-- Delete the above, beginning with <chronlist> and ending with </chronlist> if the bioghist is text only: -->
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520" id="a3">
<head>Scope and Content Note</head>
<p>This small collection of papers (168 items) of socialite, art collector and patron Flora Whitney Miller document Miller's life-long friendship with surrealist artist Kay Sage and date from 1915 to circa 1982.  Found within the papers are 79 letters written to Miller from Sage; four letters written to Miller about Sage after Sage's suicide, and one reply letter; typescripts of 63 poems written by Sage; one handwritten poem by Sage; two Sage exhibition catalogs; and 18 snapshot photographs of Sage, Miller, and their friends. Documentation of Miller's career is not found within the papers. </p>
<!-- add additional <p></p> tags as necessary -->
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351$b" id="a5">
<head>Arrangement</head>
<p>Due to the small size of this collection, the collection has been arranged as one series. </p><list>
<item>Series 1:  Flora Whitney Papers Regarding Kay Sage, 1915-1982 (Box 1; 9 folders)</item>
</list>

</arrangement>

<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 1" id="a6">
<head>Related Material</head>
<p>Also available at the Archives of American Art are the Kay Sage papers, which have been digitized and are available via the Archives of American Art's website, as well as <emph render="italic">China Eggs</emph>, Kay Sage's unpublished memoirs covering the period circa 1910 to 1935, available on microfilm reel 685.  The Archives also holds the papers of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, Miller's mother, which provide information about Miller's role in the founding and running of the Whitney Museum of Art.  </p>
</relatedmaterial>



<!-- END TOP LEVEL METADATA -->

<!-- CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS GO HERE: -->


<controlaccess id="a12">
<head>Index Terms</head>
<p>This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.</p>

<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects-Topical:</head>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Surrealism -- United States</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women painters</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Poetry</subject>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Types of Materials:</head>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Photographs</genreform>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Names:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Sage, Kay</persname>
</controlaccess>

</controlaccess>






<!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->

<!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION GOES HERE: -->

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541" id="a19">
<head>Provenance</head>
<p>The Flora Whitney Miller papers regarding Kay Sage were donated by Miller's daughter, Flora Miller Biddle, in 1990.</p>
</acqinfo>

<accessrestrict id="a14" encodinganalog="506">
<head>Restrictions on Access</head>
<p>The collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website.  </p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="a15">
<head>Ownership and Literary Rights</head>
<p>The Flora Whitney Miller papers regarding Kay Sage are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
</userestrict>

<altformavail id="a17" encodinganalog="530">
<head>Alternative Forms Available</head>
<p>The collection was digitized in 2007 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website.</p>
</altformavail>


<prefercite encodinganalog="510" id="a18">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Flora Whitney Miller papers regarding Kay Sage, 1915-1982. Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
</prefercite>

<processinfo encodinganalog="583" id="a20">
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>The collection was processed and a finding aid prepared by Erin Corley in 2006.  The collection was fully digitized in 2007 as part of the Terra Foundation for American Art Digitization Grant.</p>
</processinfo>


<!-- END ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->


<!-- START DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->


<dsc type="combined" id="a23">
<head>Series Descriptions/Container Listing</head>

<!-- use this format if you have series only, no subseries -->
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 1: </unitid><unittitle>Flora Whitney Miller papers regarding Kay Sage, <unitdate>1915-1982</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 9 folders)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This collection includes 79 letters written by artist Kay Sage to Flora Whitney Miller documenting their life-long friendship.   The letters discuss mutual friends and family, Sage's residence in Italy and her various travels, her marriage to Prince Ranieri di San Faustino, her studies and work, returning to the U.S. at the beginning of World War II, her first American exhibition, and her various thoughts on life, including the importance of this friendship.  One additional letter written to Miller by James Soby and Miller's reply concern Sage's bequest to the Museum of Modern Art. Three letters from art historian Stephen R. Miller concern her research on Kay Sage.   There are typescripts of 63 poems written by Sage and one handwritten poem, "To Quentin Roosevelt" written by Sage to Flora after the death of Flora's fiancé, Quentin Roosevelt.  Also found are 18 snapshot photographs of Sage and unidentified friends, and two catalogs for Kay Sage art exhibitions.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Kay Sage Letters to Flora Whitney Miller, Undated Letters, <unitdate>circa 1917-1940</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Kay Sage Letters to Flora Whitney Miller, <unitdate>1915, 1917</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Kay Sage Letters to Flora Whitney Miller, <unitdate>1918</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Kay Sage Letters to Flora Whitney Miller, <unitdate>1919</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Kay Sage Letters to Flora Whitney Miller, <unitdate>1920-1940</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence regarding Kay Sage, <unitdate>1965-1982</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>Poetry by Kay Sage (63 typescripts and one hand-written manuscript), <unitdate>1919-1926</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>Kay Sage Exhibition Catalogs, <unitdate>1965, 1977</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1 (pam)</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>Photographs, <unitdate>circa 1920</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

</c01>


</dsc>


<!-- END DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->
</archdesc>
</ead>


