<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "/eadcb/shared/ead/ead.dtd">

<ead audience="external" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
<eadid mainagencycode="DSI-AAA" countrycode="us" url="http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/findingaids/xml/partroi.xml">partroi</eadid>

<filedesc>
	<titlestmt>
		<titleproper>Roi Partridge</titleproper>
		<subtitle>A Finding Aid to the Roi Partridge Papers, <date type="inclusive">1909-2003</date> <date type="bulk"> (bulk 1909-1984) </date>, in the Archives of American Art</subtitle>
		<author>by Catherine Gaines</author>
		
	</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
	<publisher>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</publisher>
	<date type="publication">August 21, 2007</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Barbara Aikens on
<date>August 21, 2007</date>
</creation>
<langusage><language>English</language></langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>

<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory">
<did>
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
		<corpname>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</corpname>
	</repository>

	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100">Roi Partridge</persname>
	</origination>

	<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Roi Partridge papers</unittitle>

	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f">1909-2003 (bulk 1909-1984) </unitdate>

	<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a">1.0 linear feet</physdesc>

	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">The papers of California printmaker and educator Roi Partridge measure 1.0 linear foot and date from 1909-2003, with the bulk of the material dated 1909-1984.  Found here are scattered correspondence, notes and writings, a scrapbook, printed material, and photographs.  Several of the documents date from the time Partridge was married to photographer Imogen Cunningham, particularly family correspondence and a travel log of family car camping trips to the west.  The same travel log documents one sketching trip Partridge made with Eugen Neuhaus.  </abstract>


	
	
</did>



<!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION GOES HERE: -->

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541" id="a19">
<head>Provenance</head>
<p>Gryffyd Partridge donated his father's papers to the Archives of American art in 1992 and 1995.  A final gift was received from Janet [Mrs. Gryffyd] Partridge in 2003.  </p>
</acqinfo>

<separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 0" id="a7">
<head>Separated Material</head>
<p>A portion of the gifts received from Gryffyd Partridge were separated and filed with the Imogen Cunningham papers, some of which had been earlier donated by Gryffyd.</p>
</separatedmaterial>

<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 1" id="a6">
<head>Related Material</head>
<p>The Archives of American Art holds the papers of Imogen Cunningham, Partridge's first wife, which contain additional Partridge family correspondence and photographs. An untranscribed oral history interview of Roi Partridge conducted by Steve Steinberg in 1980 is also available.</p>
</relatedmaterial>

<altformavail id="a17" encodinganalog="530">
<head>Alternative Forms Available</head>
<p>A portion of the collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reel 5028 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan.  Note that the arrangement of re-processed papers may not match the microfilm. </p>
</altformavail>

<processinfo encodinganalog="583" id="a20">
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>The 1992 accession was processed and microfilmed on reel 5028 in 1995.  Two additions were merged and the collection was processed and described by Catherine S. Gaines in 2007.

</p>
</processinfo>

<prefercite encodinganalog="510" id="a18">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Roi Partridge papers, 1909-2003 (bulk 1909-1984). Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
</prefercite>

<accessrestrict id="a14" encodinganalog="506">
<head>Restrictions on Access</head>
<p>The collection is open for research.  Patrons must use microfilm copy. Use of the unmicrofilmed portion requires an appointment.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="a15">
<head>Ownership and Literary Rights</head>
<p>The Roi Partridge papers are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
</userestrict>




<!-- END ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->

<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GO HERE: -->



<bioghist altrender="biography" encodinganalog="545" id="a2">
<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>Roy George Partridge (later known as Roi) was born in Centralia, Washington, in 1888, the son of a newspaper publisher and a pianist mother who accompanied silent films in Seattle movie houses.  His mother enrolled him in a drawing and painting course at age 10.  By 1907, the family had moved to Kansas where Partridge enrolled in studio courses at the newly established Fine Arts Institute of Kansas City.  From there he then went to New York City to study at the school of the National Academy of Design during 1909 and 1910.</p>

<p>In 1910, with an art student friend from Seattle and enough cash to last a month, Partridge traveled to Europe and through a severe economy and by selling his etchings, managed to stay for four years.  Between 1910 and 1914, he studied etching with Brockhoff in Munich, and rented a studio in Paris from 1911-1914.  Once he had produced a sufficient number of prints, his friends John Butler and Clare Shepard arranged for an exhibition of his work in Seattle.  They were assisted by Imogen Cunningham who sent her photo to Partridge and began corresponding with him.</p> 

<p>The outbreak of World War I forced Partridge's return to Seattle where he and Imogen Cunningham finally met face to face.  They were married within a matter of months.  In their early years together, Roi managed to earn a living selling his prints and Imogen worked for Edward S. Curtis, whose photographs of American Indians had not yet achieved recognition.  The couple soon produced three sons, Gryffyd and twins Padraic and Rondal.  The family soon moved to San Francisco where Partridge worked as an artist in an advertising agency that also employed Maynard Dixon.  During this time, he became friendly with the young Dorothea Lange who worked at the shop where Partridge had his film developed. After their marriage, Dixon and Lange established a close, long term friendship with the Partridge family.</p> 

<p>In 1920, Partridge joined the faculty of Mills College as an art instructor, teaching design, painting, printmaking, lettering, and photography for 26 years. Partridge was such a popular teacher that the number of art students rose sharply and, for a time, art became the institution's most popular major.  He was named chairman of the Art Department in 1923, and served as the first director of the college's art gallery from 1925 through 1935.</p>   

<p>While teaching, Partridge remained an active artist and participated in exhibitions throughout the country at venues such as the Honolulu Art Academy, de Young Museum, Smithsonian Institution, Toronto Art Gallery, and the Museum of Modern Art.  Among the prizes and medals awarded him were: Alaska-Yukon-Pacific Exposition, Seattle (1909), National Academy of Design (1910), Panama Pacific Exposition (1915), Art Institute of Chicago (191), Brooklyn Museum (1921), San Francisco Museum (1921), Los Angeles Museum of Art (1922, 1925, 1929), California Society of  Print Makers (1929), and Library of Congress (1943).  Partridge is represented in the permanent collections of many museums, colleges, and libraries, among them: Walker Art Gallery, Honolulu Academy of Art, San Diego Fine Arts Society, Milwaukee Art Gallery, Mills College, Scripps College, New York Public Library, and Library of Congress.  Partridge also illustrated several books, and <emph render="italic">The Graphic Art of Roi Partridge: a Catalogue Raisonné</emph> by Anthony R. White was published in 1988.</p>  

<p>Imogen Cunningham and Roi Partridge, both strong-willed and not given to compromise, divorced in 1934. They reconciled in the 1960s and remained on friendly terms until her death in 1976.  Partridge's second wife, Marian Lyman, died in 1940.  The following year, he married May Ellen Fisher, a teacher, who survived him.</p>  

<p>In addition to his professional activities, Partridge pursued a wide variety of other interests.  During the 1920s, he, Imogen, and their boys took numerous camping trips throughout California and New Mexico.  With his third wife, May Ellen, he became an avid folk dancer and enthusiastic gardener, raised chickens and chinchillas, and kept bees.  They had the opportunity to travel to Hawaii and Japan.  In Japan, Partridge expanded his Japanese print collection which was eventually donated to the Mills College Art Gallery.</p>   

<p>Roi Partridge died in Walnut Creek, California, on January 25, 1984.
</p>
<!-- add additional <p></p> tags as necessary -->
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520" id="a3">
<head>Scope and Content Note</head>
<p>The papers of California printmaker and educator Roi Partridge measure 1.0 linear foot and date from 1909-2003, with the bulk of the material dated 1909-1984.  Found here are scattered correspondence, notes and writings, a scrapbook, printed material, and photographs.  Several of the documents date from the time Partridge was married to photographer Imogen Cunningham, particularly family correspondence and a travel log of family car camping trips to the west.  The same travel log documents one sketching trip Partridge made with Eugen Neuhaus.</p>

<p>General and family correspondence consists largely of incoming letters with some copies and drafts of outgoing letters.  General correspondence is mainly professional in nature and documents exhibitions, commissions, teaching, memberships in artists' organizations, and participation in the WPA Public Works of Art Project.  A small number of letters from friends concerning personal and social matters are scattered throughout.  Among the correspondents are Ansel Adams, Sherwood Anderson, John Taylor Arms, Hollywood Riviera Galleries, Dard Hunter, the Estate of Bertha Jacques [Elizabeth Linsky, executor], National Academy of Design, and Print Makers Society of California. Family correspondence includes letters to Roi Partridge from family members.  Letters to Gryffyd's family are from Imogen Cunningham and Roi Partridge; letters from others about family members are also included.</p>

<p>Among the notes and writings are a travel log that documents car camping trips through California and New Mexico taken by Roi Partridge, Imogen Cunningham, and their three sons between 1924 and 1926.  The volume also includes Roi's account of a 1926 sketching trip taken with Eugen Neuhaus along the California coast.</p>

<p>A scrapbook contains clippings and feature articles about Roi Partridge, along with exhibition announcements and reproductions.  Additional printed material is about or mentions Roi Partridge and his family, Ansel Adams, and Imogen Cunningham.  There are also family Christmas cards with reproductions of etchings and drawings by Roi Partridge.</p>

<p>Photographs are of people and art work, including photographs of  Roi and May Ellen Partridge, and Donald Bear, the first Director of the Santa Barbara Museum of Art (Janet Lineberger - later Mrs. Gryffyd Partridge - served as his assistant in the early 1940s).  There are numerous photographs and negatives of  art work by Roi Partridge (with appraisal and catalog information), and a photograph of Peter Blos' portrait of Partridge.
</p>
<!-- add additional <p></p> tags as necessary -->
</scopecontent>


<!-- CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS GO HERE: -->


<controlaccess id="a12">
<head>Index Terms</head>
<p>This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:  </p>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>

<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Cunningham, Imogen, 1883-1976</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Jacques, Bertha</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Neuhaus, Eugen, 1879-1963</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Partridge, Roi, 1888-1984</persname>

<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Public Works of Art Project</corpname>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects-Topical:</head>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Etchers--California--San Francisco</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Printmakers--California--San Francisco</subject>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Types of Materials:</head>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Christmas cards</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Drafts (documents)</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Notes</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Photographs</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Scrapbooks</genreform>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Travelogs</genreform>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Names:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Adams, Ansel, 1902-1984</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Anderson, Sherwood, 1876-1941</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Arms, John Taylor, 1887-1953</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Cunningham, Imogen, 1883-1976</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Hunter, Dard, 1883-1966</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Linsky, Elizabeth</persname>

<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh">National Academy of Design (U.S.)</corpname>
</controlaccess>

</controlaccess>

<!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->

<!-- CONTINUE TOP-LEVEL METADATA HERE -->

<arrangement encodinganalog="351$b" id="a5">
<head>Arrangement</head>
<p>The collection is arranged into 5 series: </p>
<list>
<item>Series 1: Correspondence, circa 1909-1993 (Box 1; 0.3 linear ft.; reel 5028)</item>
<item>Series 2: Notes and Writings, 1924-1964 (Box 1; 5 folders.; reel 5028)</item>
<item>Series 3: Scrapbook, 1922-1977 (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)</item>
<item>Series 4: Printed Material, 1913-2003 (Box 1; 0.25 linear ft.; reel 5028)</item>
<item>Series 5: Photographs, 1940-1987 (Box 1; 0.3 linear ft.; reel 5028)</item>
</list>
</arrangement>



<!-- END TOP LEVEL METADATA -->



<!-- START DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->


<dsc type="combined" id="a23">
<head>Series Descriptions/Container Listing</head>

<!-- use this format if you have series only, no subseries -->
<!-- use this format if you have series and subseries -->
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 1: </unitid><unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>circa 1909-1993</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 0.3 linear ft.; reel 5028)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>General and family correspondence consists largely of incoming letters with some copies and drafts of outgoing letters.  General correspondence is mainly professional in nature and documents exhibitions, commissions, teaching, memberships in artists organizations, and participation in the WPA Public Works of Art Project.  A small number of letters from friends concerning personal and social matters are scattered throughout.  Among the correspondents are Ansel Adams, <emph render="italic">American Artist, </emph>Sherwood Anderson, John Taylor Arms, <emph render="italic">Art Instruction</emph>, Hollywood Riviera Galleries, Dard Hunter, Estate of Bertha Jacques [Elizabeth Linsky, executor],  National Academy of Design, and Print Makers Society of California. Family correspondence includes letters to Roi Partridge from Uncle Arnold Frank George, his father, and son Padraic.  Letters addressed to Gryffyd and family are from Imogen Cunningham and Roi Partridge; letters from others about family members are also included. </p> 
</scopecontent>

<arrangement><p>The series is arranged into 2 subseries:</p> 
<p>
<list> 
<item>Subseries 1.1: General Correspondence, 1915-1993</item> 
<item>Subseries 1.2: Family, 1909-1985</item>
</list> 
</p></arrangement>


<c02 level="subseries"><did><unitid>Subseries 1.1</unitid>
<unittitle>General Correspondence, <unitdate>1915-1993</unitdate></unittitle></did>
<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Roi Partridge, <unitdate>1915-1993</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03> 

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Roi Partridge, <unitdate>1930-1934, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(reel 5028)</physdesc>
</did></c03> 
</c02>

<c02 level="subseries"><did><unitid>Subseries 1.2</unitid>
<unittitle>Family, <unitdate>1909-1985</unitdate></unittitle></did>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Roi Partridge<unitdate></unitdate></unittitle>
</did>

<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>From Arnold Frank George (Uncle Frank), <unitdate>1909-1916, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
 
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>From A. E. Partridge [father], <unitdate>1942-1944, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04> 

<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>From Padraic [son] and Marjorie Partridge, <unitdate>1960-1973, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04> 
</c03> 

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Gryffyd and Janet Partridge and Family<unitdate></unitdate></unittitle>
</did>

<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>From Imogen Cunningham [mother], <unitdate>1961-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04>
 
<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>From Roi Partridge [father], <unitdate>1947-1983, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(4 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c04> 

<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>From Roi Partridge [father], <unitdate>1955-1984, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(reel 5028)</physdesc>
</did></c04>

<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>From Others (re: Family), <unitdate>1942-1978</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c04> 

<c04><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>From Others (re: Family), <unitdate>1980-1985</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(reel 5028)</physdesc>
</did></c04>

</c03> 
</c02>
</c01>


<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 2: </unitid><unittitle>Notes and Writings, <unitdate>1924-1964</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 5 folders; reel 5028)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Found here are notes, lists, a poem, and a travel log that documents car camping trips through California and New Mexico taken by Roi Partridge, Imogen Cunningham, and their three sons between 1924 and 1926.  The same volume includes Roi's account of a 1926 sketching trip along the California coast with Eugen Neuhaus.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Lists of Prints by Roi Partridge, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Lists, <unitdate>1964, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Notes, Talk on the Differences between Engraving and Etching, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Notes, <unitdate>1976, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Poem by Roi Partridge, "To Our Friends Who Art Not in Heaven," <unitdate>undated </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(reel 5028)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Travel Log of Roi Partridge and Imogen Cunningham, <unitdate>1924-1946 </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(1 vol., reel 5028)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>


<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 3: </unitid><unittitle>Scrapbook,  <unitdate>1922-1977</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>A disbound scrapbook containing clippings and feature articles about Roi Partridge, along with exhibition announcements and reproductions.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Scrapbook, <unitdate>1922-1977</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c02>

</c01>


<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 4: </unitid><unittitle>Printed Material, <unitdate>1913-2003 </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 0.25 linear ft.; reel 5028)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Printed material consists mainly of articles and miscellaneous items about or mentioning Roi Partridge and family members, Ansel Adams, and Imogen Cunningham.  Also included are exhibition announcements of Roi Partridge, his photographer son Rondal, Imogen Cunningham, and other artists; <emph render="italic">A Seattle Heritage: The Fine Arts Society, </emph>a book by Anne H. Calhoun that mentions Partridge; and family Christmas cards with reproductions of etchings and drawings by Roi Partridge.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Articles<unitdate></unitdate></unittitle>
</did>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Ansel Adams, <unitdate>1982</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Imogen Cunningham, <unitdate>1951-2001, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Elizabeth Partridge, <unitdate>1995-1999</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Janet Lineberger [Partridge], <unitdate>1941</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Loren Partridge, <unitdate>2003</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Roi Partridge, <unitdate>1959</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(reel 5028)</physdesc>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Roi and May Ellen Partridge, <unitdate>1976-1995, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Rondal Partridge, <unitdate>1997-2003</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
</c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Book - <emph render="italic">A Seattle Heritage: The Fine Arts Society </emph> by Anne H. Calhoun, <unitdate>1942</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Announcements<unitdate></unitdate></unittitle>
</did>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Imogen Cunningham, <unitdate>1984-1999, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Roi Partridge, <unitdate>1977-1990</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Roi Partridge, <unitdate>1988, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Rondal Partridge, <unitdate>1996</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Other Artists, <unitdate>1981-1995, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
</c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Printed Material<unitdate></unitdate></unittitle>
</did>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Imogen Cunningham, <unitdate>1951-1993, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Roi Partridge, <unitdate>1988</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Rondal Partridge, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Arts Organizations and Museums, <unitdate>1913-1993</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
</c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Reproductions, Christmas Cards featuring Etchings by Roi Partridge,
<unitdate>1967-1981, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 5: </unitid><unittitle>Photographs, <unitdate>1940-1987</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Box 1; 0.3 linear ft.; reel 5028)</physdesc></did>

<scopecontent> 
<p>Photographs are of people and art work.  People depicted are Roi and May Ellen Partridge.  There is also one photograph of Donald Bear, the first Director of the Santa Barbara Museum of Art (Janet Lineberger - later Mrs. Gryffyd Partridge - served as Bear's assistant in the early 1940s). Photographs and negatives of art work by Roi Partridge (with appraisal and catalog information) were removed from an unknown number of three-ring binders.  In addition, there is a photograph of Peter Blos' portrait of Partridge.</p> 
</scopecontent>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Art Work by Peter Blos - Portrait of Roi Partridge, <unitdate>circa 1949 </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(reel 5028)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Art Work by Roi Partridge (with appraisal and catalog information)<unitdate></unitdate></unittitle>
</did>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Drawings of California, <unitdate>1987, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Drawings of Hawaii: Box 1, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Drawings of Hawaii: Box 2, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Drawings of Japan, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Photographs, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
</c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>People<unitdate></unitdate></unittitle>
</did>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Donald Bear (first Director, Santa Barbara Museum of Art), <unitdate>circa 1941</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Roi Partridge; Roi Partridge and May Ellen Partridge, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(reel 5028)</physdesc>
</did></c03>
</c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Negatives - Art Work by Roi Partridge<unitdate></unitdate></unittitle>
</did>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Drawings of California, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Drawings of Hawaii: Box 1, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Drawings of Hawaii: Box 2, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Drawings, Unidentified (California, Hawaii, and Japan), <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>

<c03><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<unittitle>Photographs, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
</did></c03>
</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>

<!-- END DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->

<!-- OPTIONAL ARCHDESC ELEMENTS -->

<!-- use odd for indexes -->
<odd encodinganalog="500" id="a11">
<head>Name of Index</head>
<p></p>
</odd>

<otherfindaid encodinganalog="555" id="a8">
<head>Other Finding Aid</head>
<p></p>
</otherfindaid>

<bibliography id="a10">
<head>Bibliography</head>
<p></p>
</bibliography>

<!-- END OPTIONAL ARCHDESC ELEMENTS -->


</archdesc>
</ead>



