<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "/eadcb/shared/ead/ead.dtd">

<ead audience="external" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
<eadid mainagencycode="DSI-AAA" countrycode="us" url="http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/findingaids/xml/savanaom.xml">savanaom</eadid>

<filedesc>
	<titlestmt>
		<titleproper>Naomi Savage Papers on Man Ray</titleproper>
		<subtitle>A Finding Aid to the Naomi Savage Papers on Man Ray, <date type="inclusive"> 1913-2005, </date> in the Archives of American Art</subtitle>
		<author>by Joy Weiner</author>
	</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
	<publisher>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</publisher>
	<date type="publication">August 11, 2009</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Joy Weiner on
<date>August 11, 2009</date>
</creation>
<langusage><language>English</language></langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>

<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory">
<did>
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
		<corpname>Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution</corpname>
	</repository>

	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100">Naomi Savage</persname>
	</origination>

	<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Naomi Savage Papers on Man Ray</unittitle>

	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f"> 1913-2005</unitdate>

	<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a">1.6 linear feet </physdesc>

	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">The Naomi Savage papers on Man Ray measure 1.6 
   linear feet and date from 1913-2005. The collection provides an overview of Man Ray's career as a photographer and 	
	painter through correspondence, exhibition files, writings, notes, artwork, printed material, 
   and photographs.</abstract>

<!-- ONLY USE LANGMATERIAL TO NOTE LANGUAGES OTHER THAN OR IN ADDITION TO ENGLISH -->
	
	<langmaterial label="Language of Materials:">Some records are in <language>French, </language> <language>German, </language> <language>Italian, </language> and <language>Japanese. </language> </langmaterial>
</did>

<!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION GOES HERE: -->

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541" id="a19">
<head>Provenance</head>
<p>The Naomi Savage papers were donated in 2007 by Lourie Savage Bates, Naomi Savage's daughter. Naomi Savage was Man Ray's niece.</p>
</acqinfo>

<processinfo encodinganalog="583" id="a20">
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>The collection was processed and a finding aid prepared by Joy Weiner in 2009.</p>
</processinfo>

<prefercite encodinganalog="510" id="a18">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Naomi Savage papers on Man Ray, 1913-2005. Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
</prefercite>

<accessrestrict id="a14" encodinganalog="506">
<head>Restrictions on Access</head>
<p>The collection is open for research. Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="a15">
<head>Ownership and Literary Rights</head>
<p>The Naomi Savage papers on Man Ray are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.</p>
</userestrict>

<!-- END ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->

<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GO HERE: -->


<bioghist altrender="biography" encodinganalog="545" id="a2">
<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>Photographer Naomi Siegler Savage (1927-2007) lived and worked in Princeton, New Jersey. While a teenager, Savage attended a photography class taught by Berenice Abbott and pursued this interest at Bennington College in Vermont. In California, Savage apprenticed with her uncle Man Ray, who was a close friend as well as mentor to his niece.</p>
<p>Influenced by Man Ray's experimental techniques with film, Naomi Savage pioneered the use of the photographic metal plate which produced a three dimensional form with a metallic surface. One of her best-known photographic engravings is a magnesium mural for the Johnson Library and Museum in Austin, Texas, depicting the national elective offices held by President Johnson and the various Presidents under which he served. In later years, Savage continued to experiment with the photographic process by using digital cameras, color photocopiers, and computer imaging.  </p>
<p>In 1952, Savage had her first exhibition at the Museum of Modern Art in New York. In addition to the Museum of Modern Art, Savage's work is also in the collections of the Art Institute of Chicago, the Fogg Museum at Harvard University, the International Center of Photography in New York, and the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston, Massachusetts.</p>
<p>Naomi Savage was married to the painter, sculptor, and architect, David Savage.  Naomi Savage died in Princeton, New Jersey in 2007.</p>
<p>Man Ray (1890-1976) lived and worked in New York and Paris, France and was best known for his painting and photography.</p>
<p>Man Ray was born Emmanuel Radnitsky in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania in 1890.  His family later moved to Brooklyn, New York. During this period, the family changed their name to Ray and Emmanuel shortened his first name to Man, gradually using Man Ray as his combined single name.  Man Ray attended Boys High School from 1904-1908 where he developed an interest in painting.  After high school, he worked as a commercial artist and technical illustrator in New York City while attending classes at the Art Students League, Ferrer School, and National Academy of Design.</p>
<p>Influenced by European artists, whose Modernist works were being shown at the 1913 Armory Show and Alfred Stieglitz's "292" Gallery, and other such venues, Man Ray began to incorporate elements of Cubism in his paintings and drawings.  In 1915, Man Ray met Marcel Duchamp (1887-1968) and they formed a lifelong friendship and professional partnership. That same year, the Dada group, founded by a Tristan Tzara and other artists in Zurich, Switzerland also took root in New York; Man Ray, Marcel Duchamp and Francis Picabia were credited for starting the New York Dada movement. </p>
<p>By 1921, Man Ray moved to Paris and became part of the circle that formed the Dada group. He photographed many of the Dada poets and writers, including Louis Aragon, André Breton, and Paul Eluard. Man Ray's work for André Breton established his reputation as a portrait photographer of artists, writers, and other prominent individuals, including George Antheil, Salvador Dalí, James Joyce, Sinclair Lewis, Gertrude Stein, and Virginia Woolf. In that same period, Man Ray pioneered the photographic process of rayographs (named after him) and he also participated in the first Surrealist exhibition at the Galerie Pierre. </p>
<p>Man Ray moved to Los Angeles, California in 1940.  There he met New York City-born Juliet Browner (1910-1991), a trained dancer and professional artists' model. They married in 1946 in a double wedding ceremony with their friends Max Ernst and Dorothea Tanning.  In 1951, Man Ray and Juliet Man Ray returned to live in the Montparnasse section of Paris. </p>
<p>In addition to an autobiography, <emph render="italic">Self-Portrait, </emph> published in 1963, Man Ray wrote a number of monographs and articles on photography that included <emph render="italic">Electricité</emph>, a portfolio of ten gravure prints of rayographs commissioned by the Paris electric company, Compagnie Parisenne de Distribution d'Electricité, 1931.</p>
<p>Man Ray received an honorary Master of Fine Arts degree from Freemont University, Los Angeles, 1948 and the gold medal for photography at the Venice Photo Biennale, 1962. In 1967, Man Ray received an award from the Philadelphia Arts Festival honoring its native son for his accomplishments.</p>
<p>Man Ray died in Paris in 1976.  Juliet Man Ray survived her husband and continued to live in Paris until her death in 1991.</p>

<!-- add additional <p></p> tags as necessary -->
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520" id="a3">
<head>Scope and Content Note</head>
<p>The Naomi Savage papers on Man Ray measure 1.6
linear feet and date from 1913-2005. The collection provides an overview of Man Ray's career as a photographer and 	
painter through correspondence, exhibition files, writings, notes, artwork, printed material, and photographs.</p>
<p>Correspondence primarily consists of incoming letters from art historians, students, publishers, museums, and galleries interested in obtaining biographical information, scheduling exhibitions, or seeking permission to reproduce artwork. Correspondents include Theodora Greenbaum, Sam Hunter, and Roberta Kimmel. Also found is a letter to Man Ray from Isamu Noguchi. </p>
<p>Exhibition files document some of Man Ray's solo and group exhibitions held at museums and galleries in the United States and abroad, including Galerie Anderson Mayer, the Philadelphia Museum of Art, Prakapas Gallery, Helen Serger, La Boetie, Inc., Ronny Van De Velde Gallery, Serpentine Gallery, Vered Gallery, and Zabriskie Gallery. </p>
<p>Writings and notes include typescripts of unpublished pieces on Man Ray and Surrealist photography and on Juliet Man Ray,
miscellaneous writings, and Naomi Savage's list of Man Ray published work. Artwork consists of an artist's proof of a print by Paul Levitt. </p>
<p>Printed material houses news and periodical clippings on Man Ray and Juliet Man Ray, newsletters, reproductions of artwork, and miscellaneous printed material. Clippings provide documentation on Man Ray's early commercial photography for advertisements and fashion magazines as well as his experimental photographic work.</p>
<p>Photographs include portrait photographs of Man Ray and Juliet Man Ray. There are photographs of Man Ray and Juliet with family, friends, and colleagues, including photographs of Marcel Duchamp and Teeny Duchamp.</p>
</scopecontent>

<arrangement encodinganalog="351$b" id="a5">
<head>Arrangement</head>
<p>The collection is arranged as 6 series: </p>
<list>
<item>Series 1: Naomi Savage Correspondence, 1939-1995 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 2: Man Ray Exhibition Files, 1941-1997 (Box 1, OV 4; 0.8 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 3: Writings and Notes, 1974-1998 (Box 1, OV 4; 0.1 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 4: Artwork, circa 1963 (Box 1; 1 folder)</item>
<item>Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1913-1998 (Boxes 1, 3; 0.2 linear feet)</item>
<item>Series 6: Photographs, 1913-1991 (Boxes 1-3; 0.4 linear feet)</item>
</list>
</arrangement>

<!-- END TOP LEVEL METADATA -->

<!-- CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS GO HERE: -->

<controlaccess id="a12">
<head>Names and Subject Terms</head>
<p>This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms: </p>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>

<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Duchamp, Alexina, 1906-1995</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Duchamp, Marcel, 1887-1968--Photographs</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Man Ray, Juliet, d. 1991</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Ray, Man, 1890-1976</persname>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects-Topical:</head>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Painters--France--Paris</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Painters--New York (State)--New York</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Photographers--France--Paris</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Photographers--New York (State)--New York</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Photography</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Surrealism</subject>
</controlaccess>


<controlaccess>
<head>Types of Materials:</head>
<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh">Photographs</genreform>
</controlaccess>

<controlaccess>
<head>Names:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Greenbaum, Theodora S.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Hunter, Sam, 1923-</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Kimmel, Roberta</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Noguchi, Isamu, 1904-1988</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Ray, Man, 1890-1976</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Savage, Naomi, 1927-2005</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcsh">Serger, Helen</persname>

<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh">Galerie Anderson Mayer</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh">La Boetie, Inc.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh">Philadelphia Museum of Art</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh">Prakapas Gallery</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcsh">Ronny Van de Velde (Gallery : Antwerp, Belgium)</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="711" source="lcsh">Serpentine Gallery</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="711" source="lcsh">Vered Gallery</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="711" source="lcsh">Zabriskie Gallery</corpname>
</controlaccess>

</controlaccess>

<!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->

<!-- START DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->
<dsc type="combined" id="a23">
<head>Series Descriptions/Container Listing</head>

<!-- use this format if you have series only, no subseries -->
<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 1: </unitid><unittitle>Naomi Savage Correspondence, <unitdate>1939-1995</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc> (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series primarily contains letters from art historians, students, and others, requesting biographical information on Man Ray, from publishers seeking to reproduce images of artwork in catalogs and textbooks, and from museums and galleries planning exhibitions on Man Ray. Also included is correspondence relating to the PBS <emph render="italic">American Masters</emph> documentary, "Man Ray, Prophet of the Avant Garde."</p>
<p>Files contain Naomi Savage's draft versions of letters; copies of letters; scattered greeting cards and postcards; a loan request; and exhibition invitations.</p></scopecontent> 
<arrangement>
<p>This series is arranged in chronological order. Correspondence can also be found in Series 2: Exhibition Files</p>
</arrangement>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Letter to Man Ray from Isamu Noguchi, <unitdate>1942</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Letter from Man Ray to Florence Bluementahl, <unitdate>1956</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1971-1979</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1988-1989</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>circa 1990s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1990-1991</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1992-1993</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1995</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1996</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1997</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate>1998</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">12</container>
<unittitle>Loose Envelopes, <unitdate>undated, 1939, 1982-1995</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 2: </unitid><unittitle>Man Ray Exhibition Files,  <unitdate>1941-1997</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc> (Box 1, OV 4; 0.8 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series documents several exhibitions held at galleries and museums during Man Ray's lifetime and after his death.   Files include: correspondence, checklists, loan forms, condition reports, an invoice, shipping receipt, press releases, printed material, clippings, newsletters, brochures, exhibition catalogs, and photographs. </p>
<p>Also found are invitations and announcements for exhibitions on Man Ray and other artists, exhibition catalogs and brochure; auction catalogs, exhibition posters, miscellaneous printed material, and loose envelopes.  </p></scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Files are arranged chronologically by year of exhibition. Exhibitions are also referred to in Series 1: Naomi Savage Correspondence, Series 5: Printed Material, and Series 6: Photographs.</p>
</arrangement>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">13</container>
<unittitle>Galerie Anderson Mayer -  "L'Architecture Sculpture" (1963 September 26-October
15), <unitdate>1963</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">14-16</container>
<unittitle>Philadelphia Arts Festival (1967 May 25), <unitdate>1967</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(3 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">17</container>
<unittitle>Helen Serger, La Boetie, Inc., "Works on Paper, 1910-1930" (1976) and "Constructivist and Other Abstractions" (1977),<unitdate>1976-1979</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>


<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">18</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition at Zabriskie Gallery includes printed material and newsletter, <unitdate>1981-1987</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">19</container>
<unittitle> Zabriskie Gallery - "Conspiratorial Laughter, A Friendship,"<unitdate>1995</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">20</container>
<unittitle>Zabriskie Gallery - "Man Ray at Rue Ferrou," <unitdate> 1996</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">21</container>
<unittitle>Zabriskie Gallery - "Man Ray at Rue Ferrou, 1915-1976" (1996 October 29-1997 January 4), <unitdate>1996</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">22-23</container>
<unittitle>Museum of Contemporary Art(MOCA) - "Perpetual Motif: The Art of Man Ray"  (1989 March 19-May 29), <unitdate>1989</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">24-26</container>
<unittitle>Philadelphia Museum of Art - "Perpetual Motif: The Art of Man Ray," <unitdate>1989</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(3 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">27</container>
<unittitle>Prakapas Gallery, <unitdate>circa 1989</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">28</container>
<unittitle>Vered Gallery - "Man Ray Photographs," <unitdate>1993</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">29-31</container>
<unittitle>Ronny Van de Velde Gallery - "Man Ray, 1890-1976" (1994 September 18-December 18), <unitdate>1994-1996</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(3 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">32-37</container>
<unittitle>Serpentine Gallery - "Man Ray, 1890-1976" (1995 January 18-March), <unitdate>1994-1995</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(6 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">38</container>
<unittitle>Other Exhibitions, <unitdate>circa 1970s-1995</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(6 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">39-46</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Invitations, <unitdate>undated, 1941-1997</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(8 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">47-48</container>
<unittitle>Announcements, <unitdate>undated, 1965-1990 </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">49-50</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Catalogs and Brochure, <unitdate>undated, 1948, 1980-1994</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">51-52</container>
<unittitle>Auction Catalogs of Man Ray's Artwork, <unitdate>1970-1995 </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">53</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Auction Catalogs, <unitdate>undated, 1991</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">54</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Posters, <unitdate>1966-1981 </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Oversized material housed in OV 4)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">55</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Printed Material, <unitdate>1970-1983</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">56</container>
<unittitle>Lecture by Man Ray at the Los Angeles Museum, <unitdate>1966</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Sound cassette; 90 minutes)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">57</container>
<unittitle>Loose Envelopes, <unitdate>undated, 1980-1990</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">OV 4</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Posters, <unitdate>1966-1981</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 54)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 3: </unitid><unittitle>Writings and Notes,  <unitdate>1974-1998</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc> (Box 1, OV 4; 0.1 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Writings and notes include typescripts, miscellaneous writings, a list, and scattered notes.  Included is Naomi Savage's list of Man Ray's work in her personal collection that was loaned to museums and galleries for exhibition purposes.</p> </scopecontent> 
<arrangement>
<p> Files are arranged in chronological order. </p> 
</arrangement>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">58</container>
<unittitle>"The Kiss of Time to Light: Man Ray, Lee Miller, and Surrealist Photography" by Andrew Dickensen, <unitdate>1990</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">59</container>
<unittitle>"Jewel from Bronx" by Judith Young Mallin, <unitdate>1991</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">60</container>
<unittitle>Various Writings,<unitdate>1974-1993</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Oversized material housed in OV 4)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">61</container>
<unittitle>List of Man Ray Publications Owned by Naomi Savage,<unitdate>circa 1998</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">62-63</container>
<unittitle>Notes,<unitdate>circa 1998</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">OV 4</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Various Writings, <emph render="italic">Elogio Della Disperazione/In Praise of Despair</emph>,<unitdate>1974</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 60)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 4: </unitid><unittitle>Artwork,<unitdate>circa 1963</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc> (Box 1; 1 folder)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Artwork consists of an artist's proof of a print by Paul Levitt that was produced for Man Ray's autobiography, <emph render="italic">Self Portrait</emph>. The print is a sketch of a beret; below the drawing is the caption "Ray 'Burray, The Hat Makes the Man.'" </p>  
</scopecontent> 

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">64</container>
<unittitle>Print by Paul Levitt for <emph render="italic">Self Portrait</emph> by Man Ray, <unitdate>circa 1963</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Artist's Proof)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 5: </unitid><unittitle>Printed Material,<unitdate> circa 1913-1998</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc> (Boxes 1, 3; 0.2 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>This series houses news and magazine clippings on Man Ray, including obituaries, clippings on Juliet Man Ray, newsletters, reproductions of Man Ray's artwork, and miscellaneous printed material.  Brief notes are attached to some of the clippings.</p> </scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>The series is arranged in chronological order.  Printed Material can also be found in Series 1: Naomi Savage Correspondence and Series 2: Man Ray Exhibition Files.</p>  </arrangement> 


<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">65</container>
<unittitle>News Clippings, Obituary Notices on Man Ray, <unitdate>1976</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">66-77</container>
<unittitle>Clippings on Man Ray, <unitdate>undated, 1940s-1996</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(12 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">78-79</container>
<unittitle>Clippings of Photographs by Man Ray, <unitdate>1923-1954
</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">80</container>
<unittitle>Clippings on Juliet Man Ray, <unitdate>undated, 1989-1991</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">81</container>
<unittitle>Various Clippings, <unitdate>1917, circa 1940s-1995</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">82</container>
<unittitle>Articles by Man Ray, <unitdate>1943-1944</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">83</container>
<unittitle>Walter Benjamin's German translation of <emph render="italic">Man Ray: Photographs from the Other Side</emph> by Tristan Tzara, <unitdate>1940s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">84-87</container>
<unittitle>Reviews on Man Ray, <unitdate>undated, 1920s-1997</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(4 folders, oversized material housed in Box 3)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">88</container>
<unittitle>Assorted Newsletters, <unitdate>1956-1989</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">89-90</container>
<unittitle>Reproductions of Man Ray's Artwork, 
<unitdate>circa 1913-1944</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders, oversized material housed in Box 3)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">91-92</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Printed Material, <unitdate>undated, 1944-1998</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders, oversized material housed in Box 3)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Reviews on Man Ray,<unitdate>1950-1995</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Oversized material from Box 1, Folders 84-87)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Reproductions of Man Ray's Artwork, <unitdate>undated, 1913-1944</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Oversized material from Box 1, Folders 89-90)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Printed Material, <unitdate>1945-1998 </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Oversized material from Box 1, Folders 91-92)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did><unitid>Series 6: </unitid><unittitle>Photographs,<unitdate> 1913-1991</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc> (Boxes 1-3; 0.4 linear feet)</physdesc></did>
<scopecontent> 
<p>Photographs are of Man Ray, Juliet Man Ray, family, friends, and colleagues. Many of the photographs of family and friends were taken by Naomi Savage; individuals are not identified. </p>
<p>Scattered photographs consist of exterior shots, including Man Ray's residence in Paris, exhibition installations, and of artwork. </p> </scopecontent> 
<arrangement>
<p>Photographs within the folders are arranged in chronological order.  Photographs can also be found in Series 2: Exhibition Files.</p> 
</arrangement>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">93-94</container>
<unittitle>Man Ray, <unitdate>circa 1920s-1970s,</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">95</container>
<unittitle>Man Ray and Juliet Man Ray, <unitdate>circa 1920s-1970s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">96</container>
<unittitle>Juliet Man Ray,  <unitdate> circa 1930s-1990s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Oversized material housed in Box 3)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">97</container>
<unittitle>Juliet Man Ray with Others, <unitdate>circa 1950s-1990s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Oversized material housed in Box 3)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">98</container>
<unittitle>Gravesite of Man Ray and Juliet Man Ray,  <unitdate>circa 1991</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">99</container>
<unittitle>Marcel Duchamp,  <unitdate>circa 1930s,</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">100-101</container>
<unittitle>Family, Friends, and Colleagues, <unitdate>circa 1920s-1980s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(2 folders, oversized material housed in Box 3)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Various Sites, <unitdate>circa 1920s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Exhibition Installations, <unitdate>circa 1930s, 1979 </unitdate> </unittitle>
<physdesc>(Oversized material housed in Box 3)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">3-13</container>
<unittitle>Artwork by Man Ray (executed circa 1915-1945), <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Oversized material housed in Box 3)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">14</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous Photographs,<unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc></physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">15-18</container>
<unittitle>Transparencies of Paintings by Man Ray (executed 1913-1963), <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(4 folders)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Photograph of Juliet Man Ray,  <unitdate>circa 1990s, </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 96)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Photograph of Juliet Man Ray with Others, <unitdate>circa 1950s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 97)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Photographs of Family, Friends, and Colleagues,  <unitdate>circa 1980s</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Oversized material from Box 1, Folders 100-101)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Photograph of Exhibition Installation, <unitdate> circa 1930s </unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Oversized material from Box 2, Folder 2)</physdesc>
</did></c02>

<c02><did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder"></container>
<unittitle>Photographs of Artwork by Man Ray (executed circa 1920s-1944), <unitdate> undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc>(Oversized material from Box 2, Folder 2)</physdesc>
</did></c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>







































<!-- If the series contains an index provide a link to the index here:

<note><p><ref target="seriesindex#"></ref></p></note>

-->


<!-- If the series contains an index encode it here: 

<odd encodinganalog="500" id="seriesindex#">
<head></head>
<p>
<list>
<item></item>
<item></item>
</list>
</p>
</odd>

-->





<!-- use this format if you have series and subseries -->

<!-- If the subseries contains an index provide a link to the index here:

<note><p><ref target="seriesindex#"></ref></p></note>

-->



<!-- If the subseries contains an index encode it here: 

<odd encodinganalog="500" id="seriesindex#">
<head></head>
<p>
<list>
<item></item>
<item></item>
</list>
</p>
</odd>

-->



<!-- use this format if you have series, subseries and sub-subseries -->




<!-- If the subsubseries contains an index provide a link to the index here:

<note><p><ref target="seriesindex#"></ref></p></note>

--> 



<!-- If the subsubseries contains an index encode it here: 

<odd encodinganalog="500" id="seriesindex#">
<head></head>
<p>
<list>
<item></item>
<item></item>
</list>
</p>
</odd>

-->	


   


<!-- END DESCRIPTION OF SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS-->

<!-- OPTIONAL ARCHDESC ELEMENTS -->

<!-- If you have a non-series-related index encode it here: 

<odd encodinganalog="500" id="index1">
<head></head>
<p>
<list>
<item></item>
<item></item>
</list>
</p>
</odd>
-->




<!-- END OPTIONAL DSC ELEMENTS -->









